<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Consortium</title>
<link>https://r-consortium.org/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://r-consortium.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.26</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A First for Pakistan: Karachi R User Group Builds R Ecosystem from Scratch</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/uzairdatascientist/">Muhammad Uzair Aslam</a>, founder of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/karachi-r-user-group/">Karachi R User Group</a>, spoke with the R Consortium about growing an open and volunteer-led R community in Pakistan—one of the first of its kind in the country. Since starting the group in 2023, Uzair has focused on building trust, increasing awareness of R, and creating accessible events for learners across cities. The R Consortium <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-for-public-health-data-analysis-in-karachi-pakistan/index.html">spoke with Uzair about the Karachi R User Group’s work with R for Public Health Data Analysis previously</a>. This time, Uzair is sharing how the group has evolved from informal online meetups to hosting international speakers and publishing sessions on YouTube. He also discussed the community’s rising interest in tools like Quarto and ggplot2, recent consulting work in industrial forecasting using R, and the ongoing challenge of encouraging more local contributions.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/UzairAslam.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<section id="please-update-us-on-how-the-group-has-been-doing-since-we-last-spoke-and-share-your-experience." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-update-us-on-how-the-group-has-been-doing-since-we-last-spoke-and-share-your-experience.">Please update us on how the group has been doing since we last spoke and share your experience.</h2>
<p>Since we last spoke, our user group has made significant strides in growth and community engagement. We started this initiative in 2023 with just 10 to 15 members. During that first year, our focus was on building the foundation—introducing the concept of an open, volunteer-led R community in Pakistan, which was the first of its kind in the country. One of our key challenges early on was gaining trust and clarifying that these events are completely free and community-driven, with no commercial backing.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/KarachiRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>In 2024, we began organising more frequent and structured events, which led to a noticeable increase in interest and participation. Our commitment to consistency and open learning helped establish our reputation, and we gradually grew to a community of over 500 members—a major milestone for us.</p>
<p>In 2025, we started inviting international speakers to bring in global perspectives and inspire our members. In April, we hosted <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jeremy-horne-datacove/">Jeremy Horne</a>, an experienced R practitioner, whose talk was very well-received and added tremendous value to our growing community.</p>
<p>While attendance started modestly at around 10 to 15 participants per session, we are now seeing numbers reach up to 20 attendees, reflecting a steady and encouraging upward trend. Overall, it’s been a rewarding journey, and we’re excited to continue expanding our reach and impact in the months ahead.</p>
</section>
<section id="are-you-hosting-all-your-events-online" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="are-you-hosting-all-your-events-online">Are you hosting all your events online?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>Currently, we are planning to host all our events online. The primary goal is to increase visibility and awareness of our meetup community and make participation more accessible for people across different cities. By focusing on building a consistent online presence, we aim to reach a wider audience and encourage regular engagement. Once we achieve a steady attendance of around 20 participants per session, we plan to transition into in-person meetups as well. Hosting physical events is one of our key objectives for this year, as it will allow us to strengthen community bonds and foster deeper collaboration among members.</p>
</section>
<section id="since-we-last-spoke-have-you-noticed-any-changes-in-the-r-community-in-pakistan-have-there-been-any-developments-or-shifts-in-how-r-is-being-adopted-or-perceived-locally" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="since-we-last-spoke-have-you-noticed-any-changes-in-the-r-community-in-pakistan-have-there-been-any-developments-or-shifts-in-how-r-is-being-adopted-or-perceived-locally">Since we last spoke, have you noticed any changes in the R community in Pakistan? Have there been any developments or shifts in how R is being adopted or perceived locally?</h2>
<p>Yes, since we last spoke, I’ve observed a noticeable and encouraging shift in the adoption of R within Pakistan. Through our regular community meetups and workshops, more individuals—especially students and early-career professionals—are beginning to explore and use R. While Python remains popular, our efforts in hosting free workshops and open community sessions have helped introduce R to a broader audience. This has contributed to a positive shift in perception across both industry and academia.</p>
<p>In academic circles, students increasingly find R accessible for statistical computing, data analysis, and academic publishing, thanks to its rich ecosystem of packages and reproducible reporting tools like Quarto. In the industry, there’s a gradual but growing recognition of R’s value, particularly in domains that require strong statistical modelling and data visualisation. Overall, the R community in Pakistan is slowly but steadily expanding, with a growing sense of curiosity, collaboration, and openness to learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="have-you-faced-specific-challenges-in-organising-this-group-so-far-are-there-any-tools-or-techniques-that-have-been-particularly-helpful-to-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="have-you-faced-specific-challenges-in-organising-this-group-so-far-are-there-any-tools-or-techniques-that-have-been-particularly-helpful-to-you">Have you faced specific challenges in organising this group so far? Are there any tools or techniques that have been particularly helpful to you?</h2>
<p>Building and organising our community has come with its fair share of challenges. One of the most persistent issues has been the lack of speaker availability. It’s often difficult to motivate individuals to present their work or actively participate in discussions. While I’ve delivered several talks myself—both within Pakistan and internationally—encouraging others to step up and share their knowledge remains a tough task. Another major challenge is attracting and retaining attendees. To address this, I created a dedicated <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/karachi-r-user-group/">LinkedIn page</a> for the Karachi User Group last year, aimed at raising awareness and promoting our meetups. Despite these efforts, generating consistent interest and boosting attendance continues to be an ongoing effort.</p>
<p>To improve engagement, I’ve been leveraging multiple social media platforms, including Facebook, LinkedIn, and WhatsApp, where I regularly post event updates in relevant groups. The WhatsApp group, in particular, has helped foster better communication and a sense of community among members. More recently, we launched a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Karachi_R_User_Group">YouTube</a> channel where we upload recordings of all our meetups. This not only ensures accessibility for those who can’t attend live but also helps us build a wider presence online. These tools and strategies have been instrumental in addressing some of our key challenges and continue to shape the way we grow our community.</p>
</section>
<section id="you-hosted-a-meetup-titled-reporting-champions-trophy-data-using-quarto-and-r-can-you-share-more-on-the-topic-covered-why-this-topic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-hosted-a-meetup-titled-reporting-champions-trophy-data-using-quarto-and-r-can-you-share-more-on-the-topic-covered-why-this-topic">You hosted a Meetup titled “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vIrSy5AXrz0">Reporting Champions Trophy Data using Quarto and R</a>,” can you share more on the topic covered? Why this topic?</h2>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/ChampionsTrophyDatausingR.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We recently hosted an engaging talk on our Meetup group by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/zahid-asghar/">Dr.&nbsp;Zahid Asghar</a> from Islamabad University titled “Reporting Champions Trophy Data using Quarto and R.” The session introduced the community to Quarto as a modern tool for creating parameterised, automated, and visually rich reports. Using real-world data from the ESPN Cricinfo API, Dr.&nbsp;Zahid demonstrated how to generate customised player statistics reports—blending R’s data manipulation capabilities with Quarto’s dynamic reporting features. This topic was chosen to help data professionals move beyond static dashboards and adopt reproducible, scalable reporting workflows, and it was well-received by attendees for its practical relevance and clarity.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in">Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</h2>
<p>At <a href="https://www.statdevs.com/">Stat Devs</a>, one of our recent consulting projects involved developing a long-term demand forecasting model for <a href="https://ffc.com.pk/">Fauji Fertiliser Company (FFC)</a>, using the R programming language. The goal was to project Urea sales demand for the next 15 years based on 29 years of historical data. We used multiple time series regression models in R, incorporating economic indicators like Gross Domestic Product (GDP) and external variables such as Cropped Acreage and Water Availability. R proved particularly effective due to its strong statistical modelling capabilities and advanced visualisation tools like <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot2</a>, which helped us uncover meaningful patterns and clearly communicate insights. The resulting forecasts supported FFC’s capacity planning and strategic decision-making, demonstrating the real-world value of R in industrial analytics.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rugs</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <category>asia</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-first-for-pakistan-karachi-r-user-group-builds-r-ecosstem-from-scratch/KarachiRUGlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Connecting Pharma, Students, and R: Ronak Shah on Strengthening the Pune R Ecosystem</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/shahronak47/?originalSubdomain=in">Ronak Shah</a>, co-organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/pune-r-userr-group/">Pune R User Group</a> in India, is energizing a growing R community that connects students, professionals, and data enthusiasts across the city. Through in-person and online meetups, the group fosters collaboration and learning while supporting R’s expanding role in India’s pharmaceutical industry. Ronak also discussed his side project, Package Reviewer, a Shiny app that enables users to rate and review R packages, helping others discover reliable tools within the R ecosystem.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/RonakShah.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>My name is Ronak, and I’m based in Pune, India. I have been using R for the last 11 years. This year, we launched the Pune R User Group, designed for R enthusiasts and colleagues who utilise R in their daily work or are interested in learning more about it.&nbsp;</p>
<p>As one of the co-organizers of the group, I am fortunate to have found other colleagues who share a strong interest in R. We are working to organize events and meet-ups in Pune to foster learning and growth within the R community.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-india" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-india">Can you share what the R community is like in India?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>The use of R has increased significantly over the past few years, particularly within the pharmaceutical industry. We are witnessing a growth in open-source tools, particularly within the pharma space, tools such as the <a href="https://pharmaverse.org/">Pharmaverse</a> and <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/teal/index.html">Teal</a> packages. Many pharmaceutical companies have established Global Capability Centers (GCCs) in India, not just in Pune.</p>
<p>Currently, I work with <a href="https://www.rocheindia.com/">Roche</a>, a pharmaceutical company that has its GCC setup in Pune. However, there are numerous other locations, such as Bangalore, Hyderabad, Delhi, and Mumbai, where many talented developers contribute to this ecosystem. The growth of these developers working with pharmaceutical companies is happening rapidly.</p>
<p>In Pune specifically, about 50% of our R user group consists of master’s students. They are studying R as part of their coursework and are also conducting projects using R. This has led to a strong interest in the meetups we organize, and I see a lot of traction and growth happening in this area as well.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/PuneRUGMeetup1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="are-you-currently-hosting-your-meetups-online-in-person-or-in-a-hybrid-format" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="are-you-currently-hosting-your-meetups-online-in-person-or-in-a-hybrid-format">Are you currently hosting your meetups online, in person, or in a hybrid format?</h2>
<p>We initially started with in-person meetups at Pune University, where we reserved some rooms to make it easier for students to join our community. This was one of the reasons why more students began participating. During the summer and monsoon seasons, especially when the rains were heavy, we also decided to incorporate online sessions. This not only allowed local enthusiasts to join but also attracted those situated outside Pune, helping us grow our user base. Going forward, we plan to maintain a mix of both virtual and on-site events, ensuring we cater to everyone’s preferences.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-your-plans-for-the-group-over-the-next-few-months" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-your-plans-for-the-group-over-the-next-few-months">What are your plans for the group over the next few months?</h2>
<p>When we started this year, the initial plan was to have one meetup every month. However, we have taken a brief break, and we haven’t met in August and September. After six months, we decided to regroup and reorganize to evaluate our approach and determine our satisfaction with it. Currently, we have five co-organizers who are primarily responsible for decision-making regarding the organization of these meetups and the topics we want to cover.&nbsp;</p>
<p>We want to analyze what has gone well and identify areas for improvement and change. We are currently working on this.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Initially, we focused on the basics of R, but now we plan to move on to some advanced topics. We have also hosted a couple of sessions on introduction to Shiny, including a hands-on workshop. We would now like to introduce more advanced-level topics in R, which we plan to cover in the coming months.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/PuneRUGMeetup2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="what-challenges-have-you-faced-while-organizing-the-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-challenges-have-you-faced-while-organizing-the-group">What challenges have you faced while organizing the group?</h2>
<p>We are facing a couple of challenges. First, it remains challenging to find enthusiasts who are interested in R and bring them together on a single online platform. We are exploring various initiatives to address this, including leveraging LinkedIn and utilizing our mutual connections. However, it remains a challenge to attract these individuals.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Even when we do find people, getting them to attend events can be difficult. We usually schedule these sessions on weekends when they are typically free, but we still encounter obstacles in encouraging their participation.&nbsp;</p>
<p>To encourage attendance, we are considering relocating our events to a more convenient location. For example, we might arrange to hold them in a café setting and provide coffee and snacks. This external motivation could encourage more participants to join us. We’re hopeful that these changes will be effective, and we look forward to seeing the results in upcoming months.</p>
<p>Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</p>
<p>One challenge I noticed is that, while there are many well-known packages, such as dplyr, data.table, and ggplot2, which are thoroughly tested and come with extensive user feedback, a vast array of other packages—over 20,000 on CRAN alone, with numerous more on GitHub—exist. This raises the question: how can users assess the quality of these lesser-known packages? Are they still being actively maintained? Is there someone available to respond to user reports?</p>
<p>To address this issue, I created a simple Shiny app called Package Reviewer. In this app, users can select any package they have tried and rate it on a scale of 0 to 5 stars. Users can give half-star ratings (e.g., 0.5, 1, 1.5, etc.) and add a brief comment to describe their experience with the package.</p>
<p>The goal of this project is to encourage enough user participation so that when someone is considering trying out a new package, they can visit Package Reviewer to see community reviews. This way, they can summarize feedback and understand how the package has been received, helping them make informed decisions about whether to use that package or seek alternatives. That’s the idea behind Package Reviewer.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://shahronak.shinyapps.io/packagerevieweR/">Package Reviewer</a> and share your thoughts on the R packages you use! Your reviews can help fellow R users find dependable tools and provide developers with valuable feedback to further improve their packages. (Note: Registration is not required to use Package Reviewer. On the main page, use the pulldown menu to select an R package review. For example, AATTools.)</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?&nbsp;</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rugs</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <category>pharma</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-pharma-students-and-r-ronak-shah-on-strengthening-pune-r-ecosystem/RonakShah-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="113" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>nlmixr2 is Becoming an R Consortium Working Group</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/nlmixr2-is-becoming-an-r-consortium-working-group/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Original post on the nlmixr2 project blog is <a href="https://blog.nlmixr2.org/blog/2025-11-23-r-consortium/">here</a>.</em></p>
<p>From the nlmixr2 project blog:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>We are very excited to announce we are joining the R consortium as a Working Group (WG). Our vision will remain the same:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The vision of nlmixr2 is to develop a R-based open-source nonlinear mixed-effects modeling software package that can compete with commercial pharmacometric tools and is suitable for regulatory submissions.”</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>Read the full post <a href="https://blog.nlmixr2.org/blog/2025-11-23-r-consortium/">here</a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/nlmixr2-is-becoming-an-r-consortium-working-group/nlmixr2.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<section id="get-involved-in-the-nlmixr2-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="get-involved-in-the-nlmixr2-working-group">Get involved in the nlmixr2 working group</h2>
<p>The nlmixr2 working group is open to anyone interested in contributing to the project. You can get involved by:</p>
<p>Main repo: <a href="https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2">https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2</a><br>
Issues: <a href="https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2/issues">https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2/issues</a><br>
Discussions: <a href="https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2/discussions">https://github.com/nlmixr2/nlmixr2/discussions</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>pharma</category>
  <category>submissions</category>
  <category>clinical research</category>
  <category>announcements</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/nlmixr2-is-becoming-an-r-consortium-working-group/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/nlmixr2-is-becoming-an-r-consortium-working-group/nlmixr2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="166" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From the adas.utils Package to R-Trento: Paolo Bosetti on Building Tools and Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://paolobosetti.quarto.pub/">Dr Paolo Bosetti</a>, Associate Professor at the University of Trento, Italy, recently spoke with the R Consortium about founding the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-trento-users-group/">R-Trento User Group</a> (R-TUG) and fostering collaboration between academia, industry, and the public sector in Italy. He shared how he uses R in teaching industrial engineering students, from integrating RStudio and Quarto into coursework to emphasizing reproducible analysis and reporting. Dr.&nbsp;Paolo also discussed the development of his <code>adas.utils</code> package for experimental design, the importance of documenting community activities through a group blog, and his vision for expanding the R community in Trento.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/PaoloBosetti.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>I am an Associate Professor at the University of Trento, working in academia. I have been a long-time user of R, having started around 2004 or 2005, which means I’ve been using R for about 20 years. I utilize R regularly for teaching purposes, particularly in my statistics and data analysis course for undergraduate industrial engineering students.</p>
<p>My focus is on the application of statistical methods in various contexts, including process control, experimental design, and industrial experiments. For teaching, I use R and specifically RStudio, which serves as the primary toolkit for my courses. I prepare all my teaching materials using RStudio and Quarto, including slides and handouts. The course is designed to be highly interactive; we begin with theoretical concepts presented on interactive slides prepared with Quarto, and then transition into RStudio for hands-on analysis, study, and data presentation from experiments.</p>
<p>Within my university, I have several colleagues across different departments—such as economics, industrial engineering, bioengineering, and information technology—who also use R as a tool for data analysis. To foster this community, I initiated a local R user group, known as <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-trento-users-group/">R-TUG</a>. We held our first meeting in late May 2025.</p>
<p>We are using Meetup to gather users, and the group currently has around over 80 members. At our inaugural meeting, approximately 30 users participated, and we conducted a total of four presentations on various topics over the course of three hours in the afternoon.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/RUsersTrentoLogo.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
</section>
<section id="was-your-first-meetup-held-in-person-or-online-what-format-do-you-plan-to-use-for-future-meetups" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="was-your-first-meetup-held-in-person-or-online-what-format-do-you-plan-to-use-for-future-meetups">Was your first meetup held in person or online? What format do you plan to use for future meetups?</h2>
<p>The first meeting was held in person because we wanted to foster connections. Since it was our initial gathering, it was essential for us to come together and get to know one another. Although we are all part of the same university, many of us only knew each other by name. This meeting provided an opportunity to see each other’s faces and establish those connections.</p>
<p>For future meetings, we plan to implement a hybrid format. We will continue to meet in person while also recording the sessions on Zoom and providing a link for others to participate remotely. This way, we can maintain our in-person interactions while accommodating those who wish to join online.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/RUsersTrentoMeetup.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-italy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-italy">Can you share what the R community is like in Italy?</h2>
<p>Our group consists of approximately half academics and half industry members, including some of my former students and representatives from the public sector. We have connections with local government statistical offices in industrial communities. One such community is <a href="https://www.confindustria.it/en/">Confindustria</a>, the association of local industries, which has a statistical study office that contributes to our group.</p>
<p>The strength of our collaboration lies in bridging the gap between academia and the broader world. We facilitate connections between academics and individuals with in-depth knowledge, particularly in the theoretical aspects of statistics and the R programming language. Conversely, we provide academics with access to real-world cases and practical applications, enabling them to gather new ideas and explore innovative applications related to their research.</p>
</section>
<section id="aside-from-meetup-which-other-platforms-are-you-using-for-your-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="aside-from-meetup-which-other-platforms-are-you-using-for-your-r-user-group">Aside from Meetup, which other platforms are you using for your R User Group?</h2>
<p>We also have a Quarto-based <a href="https://rtug.unitn.it/">website</a> for our group. It is organized as a blog where we publish small articles contributed by our members, as well as presentations given during meetings. Our goal is to maintain a dynamic online presence by publishing one or two posts per year and documenting our meetings and activities. For each meeting, we will list the topics discussed and make the presentations available. Lastly, we have a list of founding members and regular members, which is also available on Meetup. This captures the life of our group, showcasing our projects and contributions.</p>
<p>We also have a list of <a href="https://rtug.unitn.it/members.html">founding members</a> on our website. Most of the members joined on the first day, and they come from various departments at the same university. However, Maria Michela Dickson, a former member of the University of Trento, is currently a professor at the University of Padua in a different city.&nbsp;</p>
<p>We also maintain a list of regular members, comprising professionals from various sectors. This group consists of professors, representatives from the public sector, and employees from private companies in the mechanical sector. We are affiliated with the local industry association, which serves as a platform for industrial partners, and we also have members from public foundations.</p>
<p>Apart from this, there are spontaneously joining members on Meetup. I have been automating the process of connecting Meetup subscribers with our local Google email group. My university uses Google Workspace for emails, and we have a shared drive and a Google group for collecting members.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the Meetup API was recently changed, which has rendered previous automation packages ineffective. I attempted to write a new solution, but it remains unclear how to do so, and my efforts have not been successful. As a result, Meetup is not providing full access, and I find myself stuck.</p>
<p>This situation is frustrating because it requires considerable time to keep the Meetup user list synchronized with our internal user list. This issue will be resolved sooner or later.</p>
</section>
<section id="you-are-currently-working-in-academia.-how-do-you-use-r-in-your-teaching-and-research" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-are-currently-working-in-academia.-how-do-you-use-r-in-your-teaching-and-research">You are currently working in academia. How do you use R in your teaching and research?</h2>
<p>I’ve been using R for more than 20 years now, and I’ve recently completely transitioned to the latest features in R. I’m extensively using the Tidyverse package and have shifted from older methods to Tidyverse approaches. Nowadays, I only teach my students to use Tidyverse and Quarto. Everything we do is presented in a notebook style, utilizing Tidyverse, and I’m particularly focused on how to present analysis effectively. Our current environment is superior to others for this reason.</p>
<p>The quality of the documents we can create using RStudio, R, Tidyverse, and Quarto is significantly better than what can be achieved with other environments commonly used for data analysis, such as MATLAB or Python. Additionally, you can integrate both Python and R within RStudio, but that’s another story.</p>
<p>My primary focus in teaching prospective industrial engineers is to emphasize the quality of both analysis and presentation, as well as the automation of documentation production. This includes automated reports, weekly reports, and similar outputs.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-tell-us-about-your-adas.utils-package-what-makes-it-unique-compared-to-other-experimental-design-packages-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-tell-us-about-your-adas.utils-package-what-makes-it-unique-compared-to-other-experimental-design-packages-in-r">Can you tell us about your adas.utils package? What makes it unique compared to other experimental design packages in R?</h2>
<p>During this course, I also began developing a package called <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/adas.utils/index.html"><code>adas.utils</code></a>, which is currently on CRAN. Initially, it started as a collection of utility functions but has evolved into a complete set of objects and methods for applying Design of Experiments (DoE) techniques in a Tidyverse manner.</p>
<p>For example, I use <code>ggplot</code> for graphics, and functions have been designed to be sequentially piped with the <code>%&gt;%</code> operator. While other packages for designing experiments are already available on CRAN, they follow an “old school” approach and do not adhere to a Tidyverse interface. My package stands out because it employs the principles of piping operations and sequencing operations, and utilizes <code>ggplot</code> for visual outputs. The package is now relatively mature.</p>
<p>In our blog, you can find an <a href="https://rtug.unitn.it/posts/004-adas.utils/">introduction to the package</a>, which is designed to facilitate the creation of target plans and fractional factorial plans, as well as to analyze the alias structure in fractional factorial designs. The package also features functionalities not commonly available in R, such as normal probability plots and Pareto charts, both of which are not standard in the Tidyverse.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/Normalprobabilityplot.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">Learn more</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rugs</category>
  <category>eu</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/from-the-adas-utils-package-to-r-trento-paolo-bosetti-on-building-tools-and-community/PaoloBosetti.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="134" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Expanding the Reach of R Across Cleveland’s Data and Tech Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/expanding-the-reach-of-r-across-clevelands-data-and-tech-community/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alec-wong-67966242/">Alec Wong</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/cleveland-user-group/">Cleveland R Users Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about energizing the local R community and supporting data professionals in a rapidly changing job market. With a focus on inclusive learning and real-world applications, Alec and his co-organizers are creating events that connect students, analysts, and industry experts alike. Their recent “Career Planning” session brought together data scientists, hiring managers, and job seekers for an open conversation about navigating AI-driven changes in the workforce. Alec also shared how the group is expanding its reach through collaborations with other tech meetups and participation in Cleveland’s Best of Tech event.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/expanding-the-reach-of-r-across-clevelands-data-and-tech-community/AlecWong.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>My name is Alec Wong, and I am a co-organizer of the Cleveland R User Group alongside John Blischak and Tim Hoolihan. I have been a member of this group since 2019, and a co-organizer since 2022. John joined in 2018 and became a co-organizer in 2020. Tim joined in 2013 and became a co-organizer in 2015. We have a lot of dedication in this group and are constantly looking for new ways to engage with R users in the community!</p>
<p>I have worked at Progressive Insurance since 2019, and this year I moved into a data scientist position working to apply machine vision to automate the detection of damage on vehicles.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-cleveland" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-cleveland">Can you share what the R community is like in Cleveland?</h2>
<p>There is still interest in the R language, if our meetup attendance is any indicator. We typically see a few new faces each time we host a session, whether in-person or online. There are companies from a variety of industries situated in Cleveland – insurance, medical, financial, consulting, among other services – and you can find practicing data science professionals within all of these.</p>
<p>R is a pleasant and beautiful language to work in, and this is what I hope to share with people regardless of their background. The sessions that we host, and plan to host, are aimed at this objective in mind.</p>
</section>
<section id="you-hosted-a-career-planning-meetup-session.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-why-this-topic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-hosted-a-career-planning-meetup-session.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-why-this-topic">You hosted a “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/cleveland-user-group/events/309804784/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Career Planning</a>” meetup session. Can you share more about the topic? Why this topic?</h2>
<p>We, as data science professionals, are at a crossroad or inflection point in what it looks like to find a job and build a career right now. It’s been noted that since 2020, in the U.S., recent college graduates are seeing higher unemployment rates now relative to all workers, a departure from 30-year patterns according to the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics. Generative AI is developing into an arms race between those hiring and those seeking to be hired – applicants can fabricate resumes and submit more widely than ever before, while companies increase usage of automated screening tools (and occasionally automated interviewing) using AI. And regardless of the current efficacy of AI, there are grumblings of generative agentic AI supplanting entry-level positions. It’s a period of uncertainty.</p>
<p>In a primarily in-person event with a few online participants, we invited a panel of data science professionals who have either successfully navigated the job search environment recently, were in the process of searching for a job, or were making hiring decisions at their place of work. These were <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jairaj-ranchod-223b4975/">Jai Ranchod</a>, a business systems analyst working at Availity since 2023, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aaron-montgomery-6b17421b1/">Aaron Montgomery</a>, a data scientist consultant working at Valtech, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/josh-vanderleest-6674a87b/">Josh Vanderleest</a>, a manager of data science working at Progressive Insurance.</p>
<p>We asked the panel a variety of questions related to the hiring process today. Some examples were: How often did you get interviews from applications? How do you perceive the relative marketability of R versus Python today? Does generative technology help or hinder the job search? Emergent topics discussed were the added difficulty of the job search for international students and imposter syndrome among those seeking to break into the field.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>The consensus was that “hit rates” for interviews were fair – perhaps one in twenty – but not as egregious as some internet stories (one in hundreds).</p></li>
<li><p>Tooling (R vs.&nbsp;Python) was not at the forefront of managers’ minds; rather, it was the capability to reason well about data analytical problems that was more important.</p></li>
<li><p>Generative AI is a facet of modern job application – one audience member explained how it was used in a technical interview – but integrity and honesty nevertheless continue to be vital.</p></li>
<li><p>Resumes exist to get you in front of the hiring manager – and should be formatted explicitly demonstrating how you satisfy minimum qualifications.&nbsp;</p></li>
<li><p>Practicing interview questions using established methods like STAR can be very useful – check to see if answering questions in this format is a requirement of the organization.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>After the session, we offered resume review comments for all participants. We may not have solved the hiring process with this panel discussion, but it was an enlightening and engaging discussion.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="you-represented-the-cleveland-r-user-group-at-clevelands-best-of-tech-event.-could-you-share-more-about-that" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-represented-the-cleveland-r-user-group-at-clevelands-best-of-tech-event.-could-you-share-more-about-that">You represented the Cleveland R User Group at Cleveland’s Best of Tech event. Could you share more about that?</h2>
<p><a href="https://greatercle.com/events/2025/09/09/signature-event/best-of-tech-day-2025/">Cleveland’s Best of Tech</a> is an annual event hosting tech companies, organizations, and educators. The Greater Cleveland Partnership organizes it, and this year it was held at the Great Lakes Science Center. Our group was offered a booth spot to share our program with participants.</p>
<p>I was extremely pleased to meet the organizers of other tech groups in Cleveland. I met the organizers of the <a href="https://www.datadayscle.org/">Data Days Cleveland group</a> (April Urban, Will Skora), and I also met the organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/cleveland-area-python-interest-group/">Cleveland Python meetup</a> (CLEpy) for the first time – Anurag Saxena, who works at the Cleveland Clinic. I am inspired to interface more with these groups, and we discussed the possibility of hosting a joint R+Python meetup sometime next year, which I am excited to plan!</p>
<p>We had many other participants visit the booth, and a key takeaway for me was interest in beginner-level training in R. I have thought of this as something that the Cleveland R User group could offer in the future, possibly another activity that could be co-facilitated by the R and Python meetups.</p>
<p>Overall, I am happy to see the good health of the data profession scene in Cleveland. Meeting other group organizers has already expanded my network; I attended a Data Days workshop event soon thereafter and had the pleasure of meeting <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/drosohrabian/">Dro Sohrabian</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/samuel-martinez-975b37191/">Samuel Martinez</a> with the City of Cleveland, demonstrating their <a href="https://data.clevelandohio.gov/">Open Data Portal</a>. Further meshing with technical meetup leaders will open a lot more doors for connectivity and inspire interesting sessions in the future; I plan to introduce our members to the City’s data portal in our next guided walkthrough session.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a>&nbsp;</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rugs</category>
  <category>insurance/risk</category>
  <category>north america</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/expanding-the-reach-of-r-across-clevelands-data-and-tech-community/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/expanding-the-reach-of-r-across-clevelands-data-and-tech-community/AlecWong.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>kuzco | Computer Vision made easy</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/kuzco-computer-vision-made-easy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pt5-VSvuKMA" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="thursday-frank-hull-kuzco.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="advancing-computer-vision-with-kuzco-simplifying-the-complex" class="level1">
<h1>Advancing Computer Vision with <code>{kuzco}</code>: Simplifying the Complex</h1>
<p>In the realm of computer vision, developers and data enthusiasts often face a steep learning curve. However, thanks to the innovative R package <code>{kuzco}</code>, this complexity can be significantly alleviated. Frank Hull, a Director of Data Science &amp; Analytics in the energy sector, discussed at R+AI 2025 how <code>{kuzco}</code> leverages large language models (LLMs) to provide an intuitive approach to computer vision.</p>
<section id="understanding-the-traditional-computer-vision-framework" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understanding-the-traditional-computer-vision-framework">Understanding the Traditional Computer Vision Framework</h2>
<p>A typical computer vision framework involves several intricate steps. Building a model from scratch using TensorFlow demands a deep understanding of neural networks and image processing. While frameworks like Keras and Torch offer a less steep learning curve, they still require knowledge of tensors and image labeling. Utilizing pre-trained models like ResNet reduces complexity but remains constrained by the predefined contexts of those models. Analysts often encounter challenges like limited training images and incorrect labels, which complicate the process further.</p>
</section>
<section id="enter-kuzco-a-shift-to-llm-based-computer-vision" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="enter-kuzco-a-shift-to-llm-based-computer-vision">Enter <code>{kuzco}</code>: A Shift to LLM-Based Computer Vision</h2>
<p>Hull presents a compelling case for using <code>{kuzco}</code>, a package that harnesses LLMs to redefine how computer vision tasks are approached. By treating LLMs as pre-trained models, <code>{kuzco}</code> eliminates the need for traditional image pre-processing. The package allows for prompt-driven computer vision, where one can define roles and tasks within the LLM system prompt. This approach opens up possibilities for classification, object detection, sentiment analysis, and even optical character recognition (OCR) without the cumbersome setup of traditional frameworks.</p>
</section>
<section id="structured-outputs-for-ready-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="structured-outputs-for-ready-analysis">Structured Outputs for Ready Analysis</h2>
<p>One of the standout features of <code>{kuzco}</code> is its ability to return structured outputs. While LLMs typically produce streams of unstructured text, <code>{kuzco}</code> ensures that results are formatted in JSON, which can then be converted into data frames. This structured format is crucial for analysts who need to integrate computer vision results into broader data analysis workflows. <code>{kuzco}</code> facilitates this process, making it easier to perform detailed analyses with minimal hassle.</p>
</section>
<section id="comprehensive-analysis-toolkit-with-kuzco" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comprehensive-analysis-toolkit-with-kuzco">Comprehensive Analysis Toolkit with <code>{kuzco}</code></h2>
<p>Beyond structured outputs, <code>{kuzco}</code> offers a range of input and output helpers, along with a Shiny application for visualization. Users can easily install the package via <a href="https://github.com/frankiethull/kuzco">GitHub</a> or <a href="https://frankiethull.r-universe.dev/kuzco">R-universe</a>, and it includes functions for viewing images directly in R, a feature that simplifies the initial stages of analysis.</p>
<p>A key function within <code>{kuzco}</code> is image classification, which can be tailored to various LLM providers. This flexibility allows users to choose from a variety of models, including Anthropic, Mistral, and OpenAI, depending on their specific needs. The package also includes a GT table output for displaying results, enhancing the readability of analysis outputs.</p>
</section>
<section id="diverse-applications-and-tools" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="diverse-applications-and-tools">Diverse Applications and Tools</h2>
<p>From alt text generation to image recognition, <code>{kuzco}</code> supports a range of applications. The package offers tools for recognizing specific objects within images, a feature that is particularly useful for tasks like inventory management or wildlife monitoring. Additionally, the <code>{kuzco}</code> Shiny app provides a no-code solution for users who prefer a graphical interface over traditional coding methods.</p>
<p>The modular framework of <code>{kuzco}</code> means that users can easily add or remove functions to suit their specific workflows. This flexibility is invaluable for integrating <code>{kuzco}</code> into existing machine learning pipelines or for creating new ones.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-new-and-whats-coming" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-new-and-whats-coming">What’s New and What’s Coming</h2>
<p>Recent updates to <code>{kuzco}</code> include a custom function that allows users to define system and image prompts, complete with example data frames. This feature is particularly useful for conducting detailed analyses across multiple images. Upcoming developments for <code>{kuzco}</code> include enhanced developer tools for prompt editing and a potential release on CRAN, marking a significant milestone in the package’s evolution.</p>
</section>
<section id="embracing-the-future-of-computer-vision-with-kuzco" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embracing-the-future-of-computer-vision-with-kuzco">Embracing the Future of Computer Vision with <code>{kuzco}</code></h2>
<p>As <code>{kuzco}</code> continues to evolve, its potential applications are vast. From creating dynamic family photo timelines to identifying plant species during hikes, the package opens up a world of possibilities. By simplifying the complexities of computer vision, <code>{kuzco}</code> empowers users to explore new avenues of analysis and discovery.</p>
<p>In conclusion, <code>{kuzco}</code> represents a significant advancement in making computer vision accessible and manageable. Its use of LLMs simplifies traditional methodologies, offering structured outputs and a comprehensive toolkit for a wide array of applications. As the package grows, it promises to further democratize the field of computer vision, making it an exciting tool for the R community.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/kuzco-computer-vision-made-easy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/kuzco-computer-vision-made-easy/thumbnail-frank-hull.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing {geodl}: An R package for geospatial semantic segmentation</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-geodl-an-r-package-for-geospatial-semantic-segmentation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dvBmbYwb-JA" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="geodl-aaron-maxwell-rplusai-conference.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="introducing-geodl-gpu-accelerated-geospatial-deep-learning-in-r" class="level1">
<h1>Introducing <code>{geodl}</code>: GPU-Accelerated Geospatial Deep Learning in R</h1>
<p>In the dynamic world of data science, the R language consistently evolves, providing innovative solutions across various domains. One such advancement is the <code>{geodl}</code> package, a significant contribution to geospatial semantic segmentation. Introduced by Aaron Maxwell, an Associate Professor in the Department of Geology and Geography at West Virginia University, <code>{geodl}</code> builds upon <code>{torch}</code>, <code>{terra}</code>, and <code>{luz}</code> packages to offer a robust framework for pixel-level classification without the need for a Python/PyTorch environment.</p>
<section id="the-vision-behind-geodl" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-vision-behind-geodl">The Vision Behind <code>{geodl}</code></h2>
<p>Aaron Maxwell’s work in geospatial science and his role at the West Virginia GIS Tech Center have driven his passion for extracting actionable insights from geospatial data. The <code>{geodl}</code> package aligns with this vision, aiming to fill the gap in deep learning capabilities within R’s geospatial ecosystem. While R has strong support for spatial data through packages like <code>{sf}</code>, <code>{terra}</code>, and <code>{stars}</code>, <code>{geodl}</code> introduces cutting-edge deep learning approaches tailored for geospatial applications.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-power-of-semantic-segmentation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-power-of-semantic-segmentation">The Power of Semantic Segmentation</h2>
<p>Semantic segmentation is a pivotal task in computer vision, especially within geospatial sciences. Unlike scene classification or object detection, semantic segmentation assigns each pixel a label, enabling detailed land cover classification and vegetation type differentiation. This pixel-level precision is crucial for applications such as differentiating wetlands from uplands or forest types from grasslands. Aaron Maxwell highlights the significance of semantic segmentation in enhancing the accuracy and specificity of geospatial analyses.</p>
</section>
<section id="leveraging-advanced-architectures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leveraging-advanced-architectures">Leveraging Advanced Architectures</h2>
<p><code>{geodl}</code> incorporates several convolutional neural network (CNN)-based architectures, each offering unique advantages for geospatial deep learning:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>UNet</strong>: A versatile and configurable architecture that uses an encoder-decoder U-shape to create spatial abstractions of data. <code>{geodl}</code>’s implementation includes enhancements like residual connections and attention gates to improve classification performance.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>MobileUNet</strong>: Integrates a MobileNet-style encoder for efficient processing, utilizing depthwise separable convolution to optimize performance.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>UNet3+</strong>: Features dense connections between encoder and decoder blocks, enhancing information flow and improving classification accuracy without significantly increasing parameters.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>HRNet</strong>: Maintains high-resolution feature maps throughout the architecture, ideal for detecting small features within large spatial extents.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="streamlined-workflows-and-data-processing" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="streamlined-workflows-and-data-processing">Streamlined Workflows and Data Processing</h2>
<p><code>{geodl}</code> offers a comprehensive workflow for geospatial semantic segmentation, simplifying the process from data preparation to model deployment. Key components include:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Raster Mask and Chip Generation</strong>: Functions to create raster masks and break larger extents into smaller, manageable chips for training and validation.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Augmented Data Handling</strong>: Support for data augmentations such as rotations and flips to reduce overfitting and enhance model robustness.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Dynamic Prediction Capabilities</strong>: The predict_spatial function allows for seamless wall-to-wall predictions, automatically managing data chipping and merging for large spatial extents.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="future-developments-and-community-collaboration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-developments-and-community-collaboration">Future Developments and Community Collaboration</h2>
<p>Looking ahead, <code>{geodl}</code> aims to incorporate autoencoder architectures for feature reduction and anomaly detection, edge-weighted loss functions for improved predictions near boundaries, and additional architectures like DeepLab v3+ and transformer-based models. These enhancements will further solidify <code>{geodl}</code>’s position as a leader in geospatial deep learning within R.</p>
<p>Aaron Maxwell invites collaboration from the R community to expand <code>{geodl}</code>’s capabilities. His call for contributors highlights an opportunity for data scientists and developers to engage in the evolving field of geospatial deep learning, driving innovation and advancing the state of the art.</p>
</section>
<section id="explore-geodl" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="explore-geodl">Explore <code>{geodl}</code></h2>
<p>For those interested in exploring <code>{geodl}</code>, the package is available on <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/geodl/index.html">CRAN</a> and <a href="https://github.com/maxwell-geospatial/geodl">GitHub</a>. Additionally, chapters 15 and 16 of an online book on the West Virginia View website provide detailed insights into <code>{geodl}</code>’s functionalities and applications. This resource serves as a comprehensive guide for both new adopters and seasoned practitioners in geospatial data science.</p>
<p>The introduction of <code>{geodl}</code> marks a significant milestone in R’s geospatial capabilities, offering a powerful tool for researchers and professionals seeking to harness the potential of deep learning for geospatial data analysis. By embracing collaboration and continuous development, <code>{geodl}</code> stands poised to shape the future of geospatial deep learning in R.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-geodl-an-r-package-for-geospatial-semantic-segmentation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-geodl-an-r-package-for-geospatial-semantic-segmentation/thumbnail-aaron-maxwell.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Jarl: just another R linter</title>
  <dc:creator>Etienne Bacher</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/jarl-just-another-r-linter/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Original post here: <a href="https://www.etiennebacher.com/posts/2025-11-20-introducing-jarl/">Jarl: just another R linter</a></em></p>
<!-- DON'T FORGET ALT TEXT FOR GIFS -->
<p>I’m very excited to introduce Jarl<sup>1</sup>, a new R linter. A linter is a tool that statically parses code (meaning that it doesn’t run the code in question) and searches for patterns that are inefficient, hard to read, or likely bugs. Jarl can parse dozens of files and thousands of lines of code in milliseconds. Here is an example of Jarl running on <a href="https://github.com/wch/r-source/">r-source</a> (approximately 1000 files and 200k lines of R code) in about 700 milliseconds:</p>
<video width="100%" alt="Running `jarl check . --with-timing` on the 'r-source' repository. This runs in about 700ms and returns hundreds of rule violations detailing the diagnostic and how to fix it." controls="">
<source src="lint-r-source.webm" type="video/webm">
</video>
<p><br></p>
<p>On top of that, Jarl can apply automatic fixes<sup>2</sup>:</p>
<p>Suppose that we have the following file <code>foo.R</code>:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1">x <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">any</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">is.na</span>(mtcars))</span>
<span id="cb1-2"></span>
<span id="cb1-3">f <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(x) {</span>
<span id="cb1-4">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apply</span>(x, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, mean)</span>
<span id="cb1-5">}</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>There are two rule violations in this file:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><code>any(is.na(mtcars))</code> should be replaced by <code>anyNA(mtcars)</code><sup>3</sup></li>
<li><code>apply(x, 1, mean)</code> should be replaced by <code>rowMeans(x)</code><sup>4</sup></li>
</ol>
<p>Instead of fixing those cases by hand, we can run the following command in the terminal (not in the R console):</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">jarl</span> check foo.R <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--fix</span></span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>After running this, <code>foo.R</code> now contains the following code:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1">x <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">anyNA</span>(mtcars)</span>
<span id="cb3-2">f <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(x) {</span>
<span id="cb3-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">rowMeans</span>(x)</span>
<span id="cb3-4">}</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>(Note that <code>f</code> is now useless since it is equivalent to <code>rowMeans()</code>.)</p>
<p><br></p>
<p>Jarl stands on the shoulders of giants, in particular:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>lintr</code>: this R package provides dozens of rules for linting R code, and Jarl wouldn’t exist without this package. Jarl currently supports 25 <code>lintr</code> rules.</li>
<li>Air: this is a fast R formatter written in Rust, developed by Lionel Henry and Davis Vaughan, and released earlier this year. It is also a command-line tool that runs in the terminal. It is the technical foundation on which Jarl is built since Air provides the infrastructure to parse and manipulate R code.</li>
</ul>
<p>Jarl is a single binary, meaning that it doesn’t need an R installation to work. This makes it a very attractive option for continuous integration for instance, since it takes less than 10 seconds to download the binary and run it on the repository.</p>
<section id="using-jarl" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-jarl">Using Jarl</h2>
<p>There are two ways to use Jarl:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>via the terminal, using <code>jarl check [OPTIONS]</code>;</li>
<li>using the integration in your coding editor (at the time of writing, a Jarl extension is available in VS Code, Positron, and Zed).</li>
</ol>
<p>The Jarl extension enables code highlighting and quick fixes. The former means that code that violates any of the rules in your setup (more on this below) will be underlined and will show the exact violation when hovered.</p>
<video width="100%" alt="This shows the same file 'foo.R', but this time the two pieces of code that violate the rules are underlined in yellow. Hovering these two pieces of code show a popup detailing the diagnostic." controls="">
<source src="hover.webm" type="video/webm">
</video>
<p><br></p>
<p>The latter adds a lightbulb button next to rule violations, allowing you to selectively apply fixes.</p>
<video width="100%" height="100%" alt="This shows the same file 'foo.R'. This time, clicking on the code that violate the rules displays a small lightbulb icon that applies the automatic fix when clicked." controls="">
<source src="automatic-fixes.webm" type="video/webm">
</video>
<p>In the future, those extensions could have a “Fix on save” feature similar to the “Format on save” functionality provided by Air.</p>
</section>
<section id="configuring-jarl" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="configuring-jarl">Configuring Jarl</h2>
<p>By default, Jarl will report violations for almost of its rules. It is possible to configure its behavior using a configuration file named <code>jarl.toml</code>. In particular, in this file, you can specify:</p>
<ul>
<li>the rules you want to apply,</li>
<li>the files to include or exclude,</li>
<li>the rules for which you want to apply automatic fixes,</li>
</ul>
<p>and more.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Jarl is in its early days, there are more rules and options to add. Still, it can already be used in interactive use or in continuous integration (check out the <a href="https://github.com/etiennebacher/setup-jarl"><code>setup-jarl</code> workflow</a>!). Eventually, many <code>lintr</code> rules should be supported in Jarl, but the end goal is not to have perfect compatibility. <code>lintr</code> provides many rules related to code formatting (e.g.&nbsp;spaces_inside_linter). Those will not be integrated in Jarl since they are already covered by Air. Additionally (for now), Jarl cannot perform semantic analysis<sup>5</sup>, meaning that some <code>lintr</code> rules are out of scope (e.g.&nbsp;unreachable_code_linter).</p>
<p>This was a very light introduction, go to the <a href="https://jarl.etiennebacher.com/">Jarl website</a> for more information.</p>
<p>If you want to help developing Jarl, check out the <a href="https://jarl.etiennebacher.com/contributing">“Contributing” page</a>. Jarl is written in Rust, which may be a barrier to contributing but is also a very powerful language which is a real pleasure to use. I will add a more detailed tutorial soon so that this can also be a nice introduction to this language. You can also contribute to the documentation!</p>
</section>
<section id="acknowledgements" class="level1">
<h1>Acknowledgements</h1>
<p>As I said above, Jarl depends enormously on the work of <code>lintr</code> and Air developers, so thank you!</p>
<p>Jarl is also very inspired by similar tools in other languages, in particular <a href="https://docs.astral.sh/ruff/">Ruff</a> in Python and <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rust-clippy">Cargo clippy</a> in Rust.</p>
<p>Finally, thanks to the <a href="https://r-consortium.org/">R Consortium</a> for funding part of the development of Jarl via the ISC Grant Program.</p>
<p>And thank you, Maëlle, for improving the draft!</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Jarl stands for “Just Another R Linter”.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>This is not always possible, it depends on the rule.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p><code>anyNA(x)</code> is more efficient than <code>any(is.na(x)</code>).↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p><code>rowMeans(x)</code> is more efficient than <code>apply(x, 1, mean)</code>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Semantic analysis refers to using the context surrounding an expression to explore rule violations.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>infrastructure</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/jarl-just-another-r-linter/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/jarl-just-another-r-linter/etienne-bacher.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>mini007 - A Lightweight Framework for Multi-Agent Orchestration in R</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/mini007-a-lightweight-framework-for-multi-agent-orchestration-in-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ly7GqO4eLg8" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="mini007_slides.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="unlocking-the-power-of-multi-agent-frameworks-in-r-with-mini007" class="level1">
<h1>Unlocking the Power of Multi-Agent Frameworks in R with <code>mini007</code></h1>
<p>The R Consortium recently hosted a session on multi-agent orchestration at the R+AI 2025 conference featuring Mohamed El Fodil Ihaddaden, an analytics engineer at HDI Global SE. He introduced the R community to <code>mini007</code>, a groundbreaking package that facilitates the orchestration of multi-agent frameworks within R. As the world of large language models (LLMs) evolves, <code>mini007</code> provides a lightweight and robust solution to leverage multiple specialized agents for complex, multi-step tasks. This is an exciting development for data scientists and R users looking to enhance their workflows with process-level intelligence and seamless agent coordination.</p>
<section id="the-vision-behind-mini007" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-vision-behind-mini007">The Vision Behind <code>mini007</code></h2>
<p>Mohamed El Fodil Ihaddaden, hailing from Algiers and currently based in Hamburg, Germany, brings his extensive experience in data engineering and analytics to the development of <code>mini007</code>. The package emerged from a need to create a composable framework in R that can manage multiple specialized agents. With <code>mini007</code>, users can define and orchestrate agents that decompose and execute multi-faceted tasks, offering a modular and extensible system for LLM-based projects.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-features-of-mini007" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-features-of-mini007">Key Features of <code>mini007</code></h2>
<p><code>mini007</code> builds on the capabilities of the <code>ellmer</code> package to manage language model objects but introduces two primary abstractions: <code>Agent</code> and <code>LeadAgent</code>. Each agent operates with its own identity, instruction set, and memory, allowing it to specialize in specific tasks. The <code>LeadAgent</code>, on the other hand, is responsible for orchestrating the workflow, dividing the main task into logical subtasks, assigning them to appropriate agents, and integrating their responses into a coherent output. Here are some of the standout features of <code>mini007</code>:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Lightweight and Flexible:</strong> <code>mini007</code> is designed to be lightweight, utilizing minimal dependencies. It provides a high-level interface that is both simple and flexible to use. Creating an agent is straightforward, requiring just a single command.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Agent-Oriented Architecture:</strong> Each agent has its own context management and can be easily accessed and modified. The package supports budgeting and cost monitoring for each agent, ensuring efficient resource management.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Human-in-the-Loop:</strong> Users can stop, modify, or continue the workflow at any step, providing an interactive and dynamic approach to task management.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Advanced Orchestration:</strong> The <code>LeadAgent</code> handles the orchestration of tasks, ensuring seamless coordination between agents. It supports functionalities like generating and visualizing execution plans and broadcasting prompts to multiple agents.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="real-world-applications-and-demonstrations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-applications-and-demonstrations">Real-World Applications and Demonstrations</h2>
<p>During the presentation, Fodil demonstrated the practical applications of <code>mini007</code> by showcasing how to create and invoke agents, manage messages, and execute R code. He illustrated the package’s capabilities through a live demonstration, highlighting how it can be used for tasks such as information retrieval, summarization, and translation.</p>
<p>One of the compelling aspects of <code>mini007</code> is its ability to leverage different models for specific tasks. For example, users can choose to use cheaper models for simple tasks like translation while opting for more expensive models for complex reasoning tasks. This flexibility allows users to optimize performance and cost-effectiveness in their workflows.</p>
</section>
<section id="community-engagement-and-future-prospects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-engagement-and-future-prospects">Community Engagement and Future Prospects</h2>
<p>The presentation sparked significant interest and engagement from the R community. Attendees praised the innovative approach and the potential of <code>mini007</code> to enrich LLM-based projects. Fodil addressed several queries from the audience, including the potential for parallel processing of sub-agents and the package’s similarities with frameworks like Crew AI for Python.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, Fodil plans to continue developing <code>mini007</code>, with future updates potentially including parallel processing capabilities. The package’s popularity has already resulted in a high number of downloads, reflecting the community’s enthusiasm for this new tool.</p>
</section>
<section id="find-out-more" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="find-out-more">Find Out More</h2>
<p>For those interested in exploring <code>mini007</code>, the package is available on <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=mini007">CRAN</a> and <a href="https://github.com/feddelegrand7/mini007">GitHub</a>, with comprehensive documentation to guide users through its features and functionalities.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/mini007-a-lightweight-framework-for-multi-agent-orchestration-in-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/mini007-a-lightweight-framework-for-multi-agent-orchestration-in-r/thumbnail-fodil.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brand your docs, apps, and ggplots using LLMs</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/brand-your-docs-apps-and-ggplots-using-llms/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/828KuEORQdg" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here">Slides with resource links <a href="https://dru.quarto.pub/brandthis/#/title-slide">available here</a></h3>
</section>
<section id="branding-your-r-projects-with-ease-utilizing-the-brandthis-package" class="level1">
<h1>Branding Your R Projects with Ease: Utilizing the <code>{brandthis}</code> Package</h1>
<p>In the realm of data science, while achieving analytical accuracy is paramount, presenting those findings in an aesthetically appealing manner can make a significant difference. The amalgamation of data science with graphic design might seem daunting, but it is a crucial step to ensure that your work stands out and communicates effectively. Umar Dani, a data scientist from Prsage Group, offers an insightful look into harmonizing aesthetics with analytics using the <code>{brandthis}</code> R package. This package empowers users to create branded documents and visualizations with minimal effort, leveraging the power of large language models (LLMs) to make this process efficient.</p>
<section id="the-challenges-of-theming-in-data-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenges-of-theming-in-data-science">The Challenges of Theming in Data Science</h2>
<p>When embarking on a project, theming the output can be a task often overlooked until the end. However, theming is not just about making things look pretty; it ensures that the document or app resonates with the intended audience. A common starting point is company branding guidelines. But what if these do not exist, or the project is personal? The solution lies in choosing styles, colors, and fonts that are contextually appropriate.</p>
<p>Options like Quarto offer various theming capabilities for HTML and Reveal.js outputs. However, customizing these requires knowledge of CSS or SCSS, pushing data scientists into the domain of graphic design.</p>
</section>
<section id="introducing-the-brandthis-r-package" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introducing-the-brandthis-r-package">Introducing the <code>{brandthis}</code> R Package</h2>
<p>The <code>{brandthis}</code> R package seeks to simplify this theming process. By utilizing large language models, it allows users to create <code>_brand.yaml</code> files swiftly. These files serve as blueprints for theming all core outputs, like HTML, ggplot visualizations, and presentations. The package facilitates the incorporation of:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fonts</strong>: Import fonts from providers like Google Fonts to maintain consistency.</li>
<li><strong>Color Palettes</strong>: Generate palettes based on images or predefined colors.</li>
<li><strong>Custom Branding</strong>: Create personalized or company-specific themes effortlessly.</li>
</ul>
<p>The package primarily interacts with Google Gemini as its default LLM API, but it is flexible enough to accommodate other APIs supported by the Elmer package.</p>
</section>
<section id="streamlined-branding-with-create-branding-app" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="streamlined-branding-with-create-branding-app">Streamlined Branding with Create Branding App</h2>
<p><code>{brandthis}</code> includes the <code>create_brand</code> function, which provides a user-friendly interface for crafting brand files. Key features include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>LLM Interaction</strong>: Chat with an LLM API to generate brand files based on images or personal/company information.</li>
<li><strong>Code Insights</strong>: View and edit <code>_brand.yaml</code> configurations directly.</li>
<li><strong>Plot Customization</strong>: Generate plots and palettes aligned with the brand theme.</li>
</ul>
<p>This tool reduces the branding process to minutes, eliminating the need for extensive trial and error and in-depth design expertise.</p>
</section>
<section id="practical-application-generating-brand-files" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-application-generating-brand-files">Practical Application: Generating Brand Files</h2>
<p>Creating a brand file with <code>{brandthis}</code> is straightforward. For personal brands, users can input their name and an inspiring image, while for company brands, multiple images and detailed information can be provided. The <code>create_brand</code> function leverages <code>{ellmer}</code>’s tool-calling feature, integrating seamlessly with user prompts to craft comprehensive brand files.</p>
</section>
<section id="enhancing-visualizations-with-color-scales" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="enhancing-visualizations-with-color-scales">Enhancing Visualizations with Color Scales</h2>
<p>Beyond branding, <code>{brandthis}</code> aids in suggesting color scales suitable for ggplot2. Utilizing the <code>ragnar</code> R package, it performs retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) to store and retrieve relevant information, enhancing the accuracy of the suggested palettes.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-a-seamless-branding-experience" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-a-seamless-branding-experience">Conclusion: A Seamless Branding Experience</h2>
<p>The <code>{brandthis}</code> R package is a game-changer for those seeking to enhance the visual appeal of their R projects. It offers:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Efficiency</strong>: Quickly generates polished themes and palettes.</li>
<li><strong>Consistency</strong>: Ensures uniform branding across different outputs.</li>
<li><strong>Intelligence</strong>: Draws on LLM knowledge to provide informed theming suggestions.</li>
</ul>
<p>For data scientists aiming to present their analyses with professional flair, <code>{brandthis}</code> promises to be an invaluable tool. Explore its capabilities on GitHub and transform how your data is perceived by your audience.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/brand-your-docs-apps-and-ggplots-using-llms/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/brand-your-docs-apps-and-ggplots-using-llms/thumbnail-umair-durrani.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gradient Boosting Machines (GBMs) in the Age of LLMs and ChatGPT</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/gradient-boosting-machines-gbms-in-the-age-of-llms-and-chatgpt/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8pAv-aw8HYM" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="szilard_GBM_LLM.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="gradient-boosting-machines-are-they-still-relevant-in-the-era-of-ai-and-llms" class="level1">
<h1>Gradient Boosting Machines: Are They Still Relevant in the Era of AI and LLMs?</h1>
<p>Gradient Boosting Machines (GBMs) have long been hailed as the leading machine learning algorithm for structured and tabular data. This reputation has been firmly established over the past decade, particularly in business applications where accuracy and predictive analytics are paramount. However, as Large Language Models (LLMs) like ChatGPT rise to prominence, questions about the relevance and potential obsolescence of GBMs are becoming more frequent. <a href="https://szilard.github.io/aboutme/">Szilard Pafka, PhD, Chief Scientist at Epoch</a>, addressed this topic in a compelling talk at the R+AI 2025 event hosted by the R Consortium.</p>
<section id="the-proven-track-record-of-gbms" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-proven-track-record-of-gbms">The Proven Track Record of GBMs</h2>
<p>GBMs have been a cornerstone of machine learning since the 2000s, especially in business-related domains where tabular data is prevalent. This data type, organized in rows and columns, is typically stored in relational databases and is the backbone of many practical applications like fraud detection, credit scoring, and marketing analytics. GBMs’ superiority in handling such data is well-documented, with popular implementations like XGBoost, LightGBM, and h2o available as R packages.</p>
<section id="historical-context" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="historical-context">Historical Context</h3>
<p>The efficacy of GBMs in tabular data contexts is supported by numerous studies and benchmarks. A notable 2006 study compared several machine learning algorithms and found that random forests, neural networks, and GBMs consistently delivered the best performance across various datasets. Over the years, GBMs have maintained their status as the go-to solution for structured data, with prominent figures like Tianqi Chen, the creator of XGBoost, highlighting their dominance in competitive environments like Kaggle.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-deep-learning-challenge" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-deep-learning-challenge">The Deep Learning Challenge</h3>
<p>Despite the success of GBMs, the advent of deep learning over a decade ago promised to revolutionize machine learning. While deep learning conquered domains like computer vision and speech recognition, its application to structured data lagged behind. Szilard Pafka expressed skepticism about deep learning’s ability to outperform GBMs in tabular data contexts, a sentiment supported by empirical evidence and expert consensus.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-rise-of-large-language-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-rise-of-large-language-models">The Rise of Large Language Models</h2>
<p>The landscape began to shift with the emergence of LLMs such as ChatGPT, which showcased unprecedented capabilities in text understanding and generation. These models have transformed information retrieval and synthesis, often replacing traditional search engines and providing sophisticated code generation and data analysis assistance. However, their application to tabular data remains limited.</p>
<section id="the-role-of-llms-in-machine-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-llms-in-machine-learning">The Role of LLMs in Machine Learning</h3>
<p>While LLMs excel in text-based domains, their utility in tabular data tasks is still being explored. Pafka notes that LLMs can aid in idea generation, advice, and code generation, but they have yet to replace the specialized efficiency of GBMs in structured data scenarios. This is due to the inherent differences in data structure and the challenges LLMs face when handling large, complex datasets.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="benchmarking-gbms-and-llms" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="benchmarking-gbms-and-llms">Benchmarking GBMs and LLMs</h2>
<p>Pafka’s <a href="https://github.com/szilard/GBM-perf">GBM-perf benchmark</a>, maintained on GitHub, continues to demonstrate the strength of GBMs against newer algorithms, including those involving deep learning and LLMs. The findings consistently place GBMs like XGBoost and CatBoost at the top in terms of performance, especially in classification tasks with tabular data.</p>
<section id="practical-applications-and-deployment" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-applications-and-deployment">Practical Applications and Deployment</h3>
<p>The practical deployment of machine learning models is as crucial as their training. H2o.ai, for example, offers seamless integration and deployment capabilities, making it a preferred choice for real-time applications. The ease of deployment and efficient scoring are significant advantages of GBMs, which are often not matched by LLMs in structured data tasks.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="future-prospects-and-conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future-prospects-and-conclusion">Future Prospects and Conclusion</h2>
<p>As the AI landscape rapidly evolves, the question remains: can LLMs and other AI advancements supplant GBMs in the domain of tabular data? The current consensus, both among human experts and AI systems like ChatGPT, is that GBMs are still the optimal choice for these tasks. While LLMs hold potential for assisting in various stages of data analysis and machine learning, GBMs continue to be the workhorse for structured data.</p>
<p>The future is uncertain, and as AI technologies advance, new paradigms may emerge. However, for now, GBMs remain an indispensable tool in the data scientist’s arsenal, particularly for business applications involving structured data. Szilard Pafka’s insights reaffirm the enduring relevance of GBMs and highlight the need for continuous adaptation and learning in the face of technological progress.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/gradient-boosting-machines-gbms-in-the-age-of-llms-and-chatgpt/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/gradient-boosting-machines-gbms-in-the-age-of-llms-and-chatgpt/thumbnail-szilard-pafka.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Keeping LLMs in Their Lane: Focused AI for Data Science and Research</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/keeping-llms-in-their-lane-focused-ai-for-data-science-and-research/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ZlTKyBsLtag" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="joe_cheng_keynote_slides.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="harnessing-the-power-of-llms-for-responsible-data-science-and-research" class="level1">
<h1>Harnessing the Power of LLMs for Responsible Data Science and Research</h1>
<p>Joe Cheng, CTO of Posit, delivered a fanstastic keynote to kick off R+AI 2025, focusing on how Large Language Models (LLMs) can be effectively harnessed for data science and research. As the landscape of AI continues to evolve, Cheng emphasized the importance of utilizing LLMs in a responsible manner, adhering to principles such as correctness, transparency, and reproducibility.</p>
<section id="the-role-of-llms-beyond-conventional-tools" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-llms-beyond-conventional-tools">The Role of LLMs Beyond Conventional Tools</h2>
<p>Cheng set the stage by clarifying that while tools like ChatGPT and Copilot are well-known for their coding assistance, the potential of LLMs extends far beyond these applications. He introduced the concept of utilizing LLMs as custom agents, allowing users to integrate them into their workflows for more tailored and sophisticated tasks. This approach is facilitated by the R package <strong>Elmer</strong>, which allows users with a background in R to easily tap into the capabilities of LLMs.</p>
</section>
<section id="posits-mission-and-ethical-considerations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="posits-mission-and-ethical-considerations">Posit’s Mission and Ethical Considerations</h2>
<p>As a Public Benefit Corporation (PBC), Posit is committed to creating open-source software for data science, scientific research, and technical communication. The company is driven by a mission that emphasizes the importance of producing trustworthy results, especially in high-stakes scenarios such as healthcare data analysis, drug development, public policy, and environmental studies. Cheng underscores the ethical obligation to ensure that the software and analyses produced are reliable, as users often have no choice but to trust the results.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-challenges-of-llms-correctness-transparency-and-reproducibility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenges-of-llms-correctness-transparency-and-reproducibility">The Challenges of LLMs: Correctness, Transparency, and Reproducibility</h2>
<p>LLMs present inherent challenges when evaluated against the principles of correctness, transparency, and reproducibility. They are notorious for generating convincing but incorrect answers, operate as black boxes with limited transparency, and inherently lack reproducibility due to their non-deterministic nature. Despite these challenges, Cheng argued that LLMs can still be used responsibly with the right approaches.</p>
</section>
<section id="approaches-to-responsible-use-of-llms" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="approaches-to-responsible-use-of-llms">Approaches to Responsible Use of LLMs</h2>
<p>Chenged presents three approaches to responsibly leveraging LLMs in data science:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Constrained Use of LLMs</strong>: By identifying specific tasks that LLMs excel at, such as generating SQL queries, and constraining them to these tasks, users can mitigate the risk of errors. The use of deterministic software to augment LLM capabilities ensures that the results are trustworthy. This approach is exemplified by the use of SQL chatbots to drive Shiny dashboards, where the focus is on the correctness of SQL rather than the LLM’s broader capabilities.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Micromanaging the Model</strong>: This involves maintaining a tight feedback loop between the user and the LLM, allowing for immediate correction of errors. By taking small, manageable steps and closely overseeing the model’s outputs, users can ensure that mistakes are caught promptly. This approach is particularly useful in data visualization, where subjectivity allows for easy judgment of outcomes.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Deferred Review</strong>: In this approach, users allow the LLM to take larger steps, accumulating a “review debt” that is addressed before the final output is shared. This method offers rapid progress but requires a thorough review to ensure accuracy and reliability. Databot, Posit’s exploratory data analysis agent, exemplifies this approach by generating reproducible reports that users can review and refine.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="balancing-use-and-responsibility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="balancing-use-and-responsibility">Balancing Use and Responsibility</h2>
<p>The decision on how to responsibly use LLMs depends on the specific context and the risk tolerance of the user. For instance, those working in marketing may have a higher tolerance for risk compared to individuals in fields where lives are at stake. Cheng emphasized the importance of understanding the capabilities and limitations of LLMs and advises users to find a balance that aligns with their needs and ethical considerations.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Joe Cheng’s keynote at R+AI 2025 provided valuable insights into the responsible use of LLMs in data science and research. By focusing on principles of correctness, transparency, and reproducibility, and adopting approaches that mitigate risks, users can harness the power of LLMs to enhance their workflows while maintaining trust and reliability. Posit’s commitment to open-source software and ethical considerations serves as a strong example for the R community in navigating the evolving landscape of AI.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/keeping-llms-in-their-lane-focused-ai-for-data-science-and-research/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/keeping-llms-in-their-lane-focused-ai-for-data-science-and-research/thumbnail-joe-cheng.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Me, Myself, and Claude: Scaling an R Consultancy with AI-Assisted Development</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/me-myself-claude/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7uAf1Wz2gEQ" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here">Slides with resource links <a href="https://dalyanalytics.github.io/me-myself-claude-talk">available here</a></h3>
<p>Large language models entered many data scientists’ lives through small conveniences: better email replies, smoother vacation planning, quick summaries of documentation. For Jasmine Daly, Principal Consultant and Founder of Daly Analytics, the next step was less comfortable: AI could write decent R code and Shiny apps. Did that make years of R experience obsolete? Was this a shortcut that would quietly erode hard-won expertise?</p>
<p>In the R+AI talk “Me, Myself, and Claude: How I Leverage AI-Assisted Development to Scale My R-Based Data Science Consultancy,” Jasmine reframes those fears into a much more productive question: how can AI become a force multiplier for R developers, not a crutch?</p>
</section>
<section id="from-vibe-coding-to-accountable-ai-assisted-development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="from-vibe-coding-to-accountable-ai-assisted-development">From “vibe coding” to accountable AI-assisted development</h2>
<p>Jasmine starts with a term many R users have seen online: “vibe coding.” It captures that slightly chaotic feeling of pasting prompts into an AI, grabbing whatever comes out, and hoping it runs. It is funny—but also dangerous. The mindset behind it is essentially:</p>
<ul>
<li>try something</li>
<li>hope it works</li>
<li>do not look too closely at why</li>
</ul>
<p>Instead of “vibe coding,” Jasmine prefers “intentional, accountable AI-assisted development.” The shift is not about policing language; it is about accurately describing the work:</p>
<ul>
<li>there is a real system being built for real organizations<br>
</li>
<li>there are real risks around correctness, maintainability, and security<br>
</li>
<li>a human developer remains responsible for design decisions and outcomes</li>
</ul>
<p>For Jasmine, AI is “a new agentic tool in the toolbox,” not a replacement for R expertise. That language matters, especially inside a consultancy where clients rely on clear judgment, not just clever code.</p>
</section>
<section id="mental-bandwidth-as-the-real-bottleneck" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mental-bandwidth-as-the-real-bottleneck">Mental bandwidth as the real bottleneck</h2>
<p>As a solo consultant serving nonprofits and other mission-driven organizations, Jasmine used to spend most working hours writing code: Shiny apps, dashboards, R packages, data pipelines. The result: less time for the work that grows a sustainable practice and strengthens the R community.</p>
<p>AI-assisted development changed that balance. Instead of treating AI as “time savings on tasks already being done,” Jasmine treats it as a <strong>mental bandwidth reallocator</strong>. Offloading boilerplate and repetitive scaffolding frees attention for:</p>
<ul>
<li>improving business operations and systems<br>
</li>
<li>thinking clearly about pricing, profitability, and packaging of services<br>
</li>
<li>building relationships through networking, speaking, and community work</li>
</ul>
<p>Crucially, this is not about doing less technical work. Jasmine still writes R code nearly every day. The difference is that cognitive load is no longer consumed entirely by syntax and glue code; there is space for bigger-picture thinking and community contribution.</p>
</section>
<section id="turning-personal-tools-into-r-packages" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="turning-personal-tools-into-r-packages">Turning personal tools into R packages</h2>
<p>A good example of that shift is the evolution from one-off scripts to reusable packages.</p>
<section id="shinyfa-understanding-large-shiny-codebases" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="shinyfa-understanding-large-shiny-codebases"><code>{shinyfa}</code>: understanding large Shiny codebases</h3>
<p>A client Shiny app with a large, unfamiliar codebase was consuming huge onboarding time. To cope, Jasmine wrote ad hoc scripts—supported by Claude Code—to analyze file structure, track <code>render*()</code> and reactive functions, and surface where important logic lived.</p>
<p>Previously, those scripts would have stayed on a local machine. With more bandwidth and AI-assisted help, Jasmine turned that exploratory tooling into a reusable R package: <strong>{shinyfa}</strong>, now on CRAN, which analyzes large Shiny directories and extracts structured information about reactivity patterns and outputs for easier onboarding and refactoring.</p>
</section>
<section id="avilistr-a-weekend-package-powered-by-curiosity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="avilistr-a-weekend-package-powered-by-curiosity"><code>{avilistr}</code>: a weekend package powered by curiosity</h3>
<p>Another example came from a personal interest: bird taxonomy. Starting from an Excel file and the newly released AviList global bird checklist, Jasmine used Claude Code to help wrap the data, write documentation, and publish <strong>{avilistr}</strong>, an R package exposing the AviList global avian checklist to R users in a research-ready form.</p>
<p>The technical lift was not extreme. The point is what changed:</p>
<ul>
<li>before AI, that project would likely have stayed a “someday” idea<br>
</li>
<li>with AI-assisted development, it became a polished, documented R package released in a weekend</li>
</ul>
<p>For the R community, this is the upside: more of those “nice-to-have” tools actually get shipped.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="saying-yes-to-bigger-more-interesting-r-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="saying-yes-to-bigger-more-interesting-r-projects">Saying yes to bigger, more interesting R projects</h2>
<p>Jasmine also shows how AI changes the filter for accepting new work.</p>
<p>The old filter was purely capacity-driven:</p>
<ul>
<li>Can this be built in a reasonable timeframe?</li>
<li>With current skills?</li>
<li>Alongside existing client workload?</li>
</ul>
<p>With AI-assisted development, the filter becomes more strategic:</p>
<ul>
<li>The technical build is possible.<br>
</li>
<li>The key question is: can there be deep understanding of the client’s desired outcomes, their team’s strengths, and the right “size” of solution?</li>
</ul>
<p>That change leads to more ambitious, higher-impact problems—without requiring 80-hour weeks.</p>
</section>
<section id="claude-code-as-a-senior-and-sometimes-junior-developer" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="claude-code-as-a-senior-and-sometimes-junior-developer">Claude Code as a senior (and sometimes junior) developer</h2>
<p>A recurring theme in the talk is Jasmine’s mental model for working with Claude Code:</p>
<ul>
<li>Jasmine is the <strong>manager and technical lead</strong><br>
</li>
<li>Claude is a <strong>senior, sometimes junior, developer</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>That means Jasmine:</p>
<ul>
<li>sets direction and architecture<br>
</li>
<li>defines requirements in detail<br>
</li>
<li>reviews every pull request–equivalent output<br>
</li>
<li>remains in and on the loop at all times</li>
</ul>
<p>Practically, that looks like:</p>
<ul>
<li>being specific in prompts and requirements<br>
</li>
<li>always reviewing generated code and context files<br>
</li>
<li>using small, incremental commits to make AI changes auditable<br>
</li>
<li>feeding documentation links and relevant repos so the model has grounded context<br>
</li>
<li>sometimes asking for multiple options, then blending or choosing the simplest approach</li>
</ul>
<p>The R community takeaway: treat AI tools as part of a team that needs leadership, not as an infallible code generator.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-real-world-architecture-50-dashboards-github-actions-and-quarto" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-real-world-architecture-50-dashboards-github-actions-and-quarto">A real-world architecture: 50+ dashboards, GitHub Actions, and Quarto</h2>
<p>One of the most compelling case studies in the talk centers on a client with more than 50 dashboards that needed to scale. Jasmine describes using Claude Code to help assemble a sustainable architecture:</p>
<ul>
<li>GitHub Actions and YAML workflows to orchestrate builds<br>
</li>
<li>Railway as a virtual machine environment<br>
</li>
<li>Supabase with row-level security for multi-tenant isolation<br>
</li>
<li>Quarto dashboards, each pulling only its own data<br>
</li>
<li>A shared component library and template so features could be toggled on or off</li>
</ul>
<p>The result: “right-sized, enterprise-grade infrastructure” delivered in weeks instead of months, with Jasmine still firmly in technical control. Without AI assistance, that project might have been impractical or too risky for a solo consultant to accept.</p>
</section>
<section id="building-r-intuition-through-volume-not-shortcuts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="building-r-intuition-through-volume-not-shortcuts">Building R intuition through volume, not shortcuts</h2>
<p>A common fear in the R community is that relying on AI will erode skills. Jasmine’s experience is the opposite: <strong>AI increases the volume and variety of patterns seen</strong>, which, when handled deliberately, strengthens intuition.</p>
<p>She highlights three recurring categories of AI mistakes and what they teach:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Package confusion</strong> – e.g., misinterpreting <code>{shinyfa}</code> as related to Font Awesome. The fix is to feed documentation URLs and be explicit about which package is in use. This forces better documentation habits.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Data structure assumptions</strong> – incorrect column names or types, or confusing similar datasets. This encourages consistent use of <code>str()</code>, <code>glimpse()</code>, and other inspection tools, and can be mitigated by exposing the real R session via MCP tools so the model sees actual objects.</li>
<li><strong>Over-engineering</strong> – proposing complex graph-based or multi-package solutions where a simple <code>dplyr</code> pipeline would work. Asking for multiple options and explicitly requesting the simplest approach helps counter this tendency.</li>
</ul>
<p>Each mistake becomes a prompt-engineering lesson and a design pattern lesson at the same time. Instead of avoiding errors, Jasmine leans into high-volume iteration, using failures to refine both prompts and architectural judgment.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-simple-reflection-framework-for-rai-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-simple-reflection-framework-for-rai-projects">A simple reflection framework for R+AI projects</h2>
<p>In closing, Jasmine offers a practical reflection exercise for anyone starting an AI-assisted R project:</p>
<ul>
<li>What will always be done personally?<br>
</li>
<li>What can AI help with?<br>
</li>
<li>What needs to be understood deeply?<br>
</li>
<li>What is comfortable to delegate?</li>
</ul>
<p>Writing down the answers before starting a project makes the human/AI division of labor explicit. It also reinforces that responsibility for correctness, ethics, and impact stays with the human developer.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-this-means-for-the-r-community" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-this-means-for-the-r-community">What this means for the R community</h2>
<p>The core message to the R community is direct: AI does not automatically make developers lazy or dependent. Used with intention, it can:</p>
<ul>
<li>unlock time for community talks, open source work, and mentoring<br>
</li>
<li>turn private scripts into packages that benefit thousands of R users<br>
</li>
<li>enable R consultants to take on more ambitious, higher-impact projects<br>
</li>
<li>accelerate learning by exposing more patterns—while still demanding human judgment</li>
</ul>
<p>Jasmine’s journey from existential dread to strategic partnership with Claude is a blueprint many R users can follow. The tools may be new, but the craft is familiar: thoughtful design, careful review, and a commitment to building software that genuinely helps people.</p>
<p>The invitation is clear: stay human-in-the-loop, build with intention, keep learning—and bring that energy back into the R community.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/me-myself-claude/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/me-myself-claude/thumbnail-jasmine-daly.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tracking the Evolution of R and Python Tools for GenAI</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/tracking-the-evolution-of-r-and-python-tools-for-genai/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wYMzdAh8FyE" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf">Slides with resource links <a href="Xu_Fei_Tracking_the_Evolution.pdf">available here</a> (PDF)</h3>
</section>
<section id="building-genai-applications-lessons-from-r-and-python-tooling" class="level1">
<h1>Building GenAI Applications: Lessons from R and Python Tooling</h1>
<p>Generative AI (GenAI) has become an exciting frontier for developers and data scientists eager to infuse applications with intelligent features. The journey at A2-Ai, a team of scientists and developers skilled in languages like R, Python, JavaScript, and more, provides valuable insights into the interplay of R and Python in GenAI tooling. This post delves into key learnings and experiences from building GenAI applications, focusing on tools that enhance communication between elements and back-end systems.</p>
<section id="a-journey-into-genai-from-challenges-to-solutions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-journey-into-genai-from-challenges-to-solutions">A Journey into GenAI: From Challenges to Solutions</h2>
<p>A2-Ai’s exploration into GenAI began with a simple question: “How do I install the <code>dplyr</code> package?” While large language models like ChatGPT offered correct answers, they weren’t always applicable to internal processes. A2-Ai uses an internal tool written in Rust, called RB, for managing installations and environments for R packages. The need to incorporate such internal knowledge into a chatbot led to the development of a unique system built with Shiny for Python. The result was a chatbot capable of fetching precise information from the internal R repository, Prism, and making appropriate API calls.</p>
<p>For example, one colleague developed a Model Context Protocol (MCP) server in R, enabling natural language queries for exploratory data analysis within pharmacometrics workflows. This allowed scientists to interact with data by posing questions in English, prompting updates in plots and legends.</p>
<p>While applications are diverse, three core building blocks are essential for building GenAI applications: model interface, context handling, and result validation.</p>
</section>
<section id="core-building-blocks-of-genai-applications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-building-blocks-of-genai-applications">Core Building Blocks of GenAI Applications</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Model Interface</strong>: This manages Language Model (LM) API calls. Despite the dearth of R SDKs for providers like OpenAI, the package <code>{ellmer}</code> has emerged as the go-to tool for R developers. <code>{ellmer}</code> abstracts overhead from HTTP calls, allowing developers to focus on building rather than communication intricacies.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Context Handling</strong>: This involves determining the necessary context for LLMs to provide accurate responses. In enterprise environments, internal documentation, codebases, and workflows form part of this context. The robustness of the Python ecosystem, rich with tools for document processing, offers an advantage, but recent R developments are bridging some gaps.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Result Validation</strong>: Ensuring systematic output of desired results is crucial, given the non-deterministic behavior of LM applications. Tools like <code>vital</code> in R and <code>inspect</code> in Python offer mechanisms to evaluate GenAI applications systematically, ensuring improvements are tracked and validated.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="evolution-of-tooling-in-r-and-python" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="evolution-of-tooling-in-r-and-python">Evolution of Tooling in R and Python</h2>
<p>R and Python ecosystems have evolved with various packages dealing with model interfaces. The chronological development of these packages reveals a convergence towards <code>{ellmer}</code> for R, while Python’s ecosystem remains diverse due to original SDKs from model providers and other unifying libraries.</p>
<p>The Python ecosystem boasts high-level orchestration frameworks for different use cases, a result of foundational SDKs enabling diverse and rich use-case development. While R’s ecosystem is in a growth phase, new tools are helping it catch up.</p>
</section>
<section id="strategies-for-leveraging-r-and-python-together" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strategies-for-leveraging-r-and-python-together">Strategies for Leveraging R and Python Together</h2>
<p>Developers need not choose between R and Python. Several strategies exist to leverage both:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>R-Only Teams</strong>: Start with <code>{ellmer}</code> and explore packages like <code>{btw}</code> (from Posit), which allow interaction with LLMs within R environments.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Python-Only Tools</strong>: Use the <code>reticulate</code> package to call Python libraries and functions from R without switching languages entirely.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Multilingual Teams</strong>: Use REST APIs to expose tools to other teams, enabling interaction across different languages.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Model Context Protocol (MCP)</strong>: With MCP servers, developers can expose functions in any language as natural language queries, enhancing cross-language interactions.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusion-and-final-takeaways" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion-and-final-takeaways">Conclusion and Final Takeaways</h2>
<p>Building GenAI applications with R and Python is an exciting venture, enriched by rapidly evolving ecosystems. While Python offers maturity, R is catching up with robust tools like <code>{ellmer}</code>. The key is to start building and refine applications based on user interactions. Bridging gaps strategically through REST APIs and MCP servers ensures developers leverage the best of both worlds while being mindful of potential risks and vulnerabilities.</p>
<p>Engage with the GenAI community, share experiences, and continue learning for a rewarding journey in building innovative applications.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <category>software development</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/tracking-the-evolution-of-r-and-python-tools-for-genai/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/tracking-the-evolution-of-r-and-python-tools-for-genai/thumbnail-xu-fei.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R+AI: Use RAG from your database to gain insights into the R Consortium</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rplusai-use-rag-from-your-database-to-gain-insights-into-the-r-consortium/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h0ewziCZ0WI" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<section id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="slides-with-resource-links-available-here-pdf.">Slides with resource links <a href="RplusAI-Mark-Hornick-RAG.pdf">available here</a> (PDF).</h3>
<p>Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) is quickly becoming a core pattern for putting real-world data behind large language models (LLMs). At R+AI 2025, the session <strong>“R+AI: Use RAG from your database to gain insights into the R Consortium”</strong> put this pattern directly into the hands of R users.</p>
<p>Presented by <strong>Mark Hornick</strong> (Senior Director, Oracle Machine Learning) and <strong>Sherry LaMonica</strong> (Consulting MTS, Oracle Machine Learning), the session walks through how to turn the R Consortium’s blog archive into a searchable knowledge source using R, Oracle Autonomous AI Database, and Select AI’s built-in RAG capabilities.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="why-rag-matters-for-r-users" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-rag-matters-for-r-users">Why RAG matters for R users</h2>
<p>The session opens with a problem that every R user experimenting with LLMs has already run into: models are powerful, but their knowledge is frozen at a training cutoff date. They know a lot about R in general, but not necessarily about:</p>
<ul>
<li>Recent events such as R+AI 2025<br>
</li>
<li>Newly published R Consortium posts or announcements<br>
</li>
<li>Fresh community content, including RUG interviews and technical grant updates</li>
</ul>
<p>Without access to current, domain-specific content, a base LLM simply cannot answer many questions accurately—especially about a fast-moving ecosystem like R.</p>
<p>RAG solves this by combining:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Vector search</strong> over your own content (in this case, R Consortium blogs)<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Generative AI</strong> that uses the retrieved passages as grounded context</li>
</ul>
<p>Instead of asking an LLM to “remember everything,” RAG feeds it the exact snippets it needs at query time. The model generates text, but the facts come from your data.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="inside-a-rag-pipeline-from-chunks-to-answers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="inside-a-rag-pipeline-from-chunks-to-answers">Inside a RAG pipeline: from chunks to answers</h2>
<p>Hornick walks through a concise but clear mental model for RAG:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Chunk documents</strong><br>
R Consortium blog posts and related articles are split into text chunks using a sliding window approach, so each piece is big enough to be meaningful but small enough for precise retrieval.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Create embeddings and a vector index</strong><br>
Each chunk is converted into a high-dimensional vector using an embedding (transformer) model. These vectors are stored in a vector database and organized by a <strong>vector index</strong>, which makes similarity search fast and scalable, even with millions of chunks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Embed the user query</strong><br>
When a user asks a question in natural language, that question is also converted into a vector using the same embedding model.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Retrieve similar chunks</strong><br>
The system performs a semantic similarity search between the query vector and the document vectors, retrieving the top-k most relevant chunks.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Augment the prompt and call the LLM</strong><br>
Those chunks are combined with the user’s question to form an augmented prompt. The LLM then generates an answer grounded in the retrieved R Consortium content.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Return both answer and sources</strong><br>
In addition to the natural-language answer, the system can return which documents and offsets contributed to that response, giving transparency and traceability back to the original posts.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The key point: RAG injects fresh, trusted knowledge into the LLM at inference time, without retraining or fine-tuning the model.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="select-ai-and-autonomous-ai-database-rag-built-into-the-database" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="select-ai-and-autonomous-ai-database-rag-built-into-the-database">Select AI and Autonomous AI Database: RAG built into the database</h2>
<p>Rather than asking R users to handcraft all this orchestration with an external framework, the session leans on <strong>Oracle Autonomous AI Database</strong> and <strong>Select AI</strong>. In this architecture:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <strong>R Consortium blog archive</strong> is stored as HTML and text files in <strong>Oracle Object Storage</strong>.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Select AI RAG</strong> automates chunking, embedding, vector store creation, and index maintenance inside the database.<br>
</li>
<li>The entire RAG pipeline lives close to the data, which simplifies operations and improves performance.</li>
</ul>
<p>Select AI exposes a configuration object called an <strong>AI profile</strong>, which specifies:</p>
<ul>
<li>The AI provider and LLM to use (for example, an OCI Generative AI model)<br>
</li>
<li>The transformer (embedding) model<br>
</li>
<li>The vector index to query<br>
</li>
<li>Parameters like temperature, max tokens, and whether to return sources</li>
</ul>
<p>The talk shows how AI profiles become the control center for RAG: define them once, then reuse them across R sessions, workflows, and applications.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="building-rag-from-r-helper-functions-not-boilerplate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="building-rag-from-r-helper-functions-not-boilerplate">Building RAG from R: helper functions, not boilerplate</h2>
<p>From the R user’s perspective, the magic happens through a set of helper functions that wrap the underlying PL/SQL APIs in the database. LaMonica demonstrates this live from RStudio:</p>
<ul>
<li>An R function establishes a secure connection to Oracle Autonomous AI Database.<br>
</li>
<li>Another function creates an AI profile, passing in credentials, LLM configuration, and the name of the vector index.<br>
</li>
<li>A third function creates the vector index itself, handling options like chunk size, chunk overlap, and refresh behavior as new content is added to Object Storage.</li>
</ul>
<p>All of the PL/SQL complexity—JSON attribute strings, dynamic SQL, and calls to <code>DBMS_CLOUD_AI</code> procedures such as <code>CREATE_VECTOR_INDEX</code>—is hidden behind the R wrapper functions. R users stay in familiar territory while the database takes care of the heavy lifting.</p>
<p>Once everything is configured, a single R function can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Take a natural language prompt<br>
</li>
<li>Call the appropriate Select AI procedure under the hood<br>
</li>
<li>Return both the generated answer and the list of retrieved sources as a tidy R object</li>
</ul>
<p>This pattern makes it realistic for R teams to prototype and deploy RAG workflows without becoming experts in database internals.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="direct-llm-vs-rag-asking-about-rai-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="direct-llm-vs-rag-asking-about-rai-2025">Direct LLM vs RAG: asking about R+AI 2025</h2>
<p>One of the most compelling moments in the demo is a simple A/B test:</p>
<ul>
<li>First, LaMonica asks a base LLM (no RAG) about the <strong>R+AI 2025 conference</strong>. As expected, the model admits it has no information—this content postdates its training data.<br>
</li>
<li>Then, she repeats the same question using RAG backed by the R Consortium blog and conference pages.</li>
</ul>
<p>This time, the answer includes concrete details about R+AI 2025: dates, online format, and examples from the program, all drawn from the R Consortium’s own materials.</p>
<p>The difference is stark:</p>
<ul>
<li>Without RAG, the model is blind to R Consortium’s latest activities.<br>
</li>
<li>With RAG, it acts like a knowledgeable assistant that “reads” the current R Consortium site for every query.</li>
</ul>
<p>For anyone managing R content—websites, documentation, internal knowledge bases—the lesson is clear: RAG is how LLMs become truly useful on top of your own corpus.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="multilingual-retrieval-on-english-blog-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="multilingual-retrieval-on-english-blog-content">Multilingual retrieval on English blog content</h2>
<p>Another highlight is multilingual support. The R Consortium blog posts used in the demo are in English, but the speakers show queries issued in <strong>Italian, Spanish, and Brazilian Portuguese</strong>:</p>
<ul>
<li>The multilingual embedding model interprets the query in each language.<br>
</li>
<li>The system still retrieves relevant English-language blog chunks.<br>
</li>
<li>The LLM responds in the same language as the question, grounded in English content.</li>
</ul>
<p>For an international community like the R ecosystem—where user groups and contributors span Europe, Latin America, and beyond—this multilingual RAG pattern is powerful. It makes English-only technical content accessible through conversational queries in local languages, while still keeping a single canonical source of truth.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="under-the-hood-ai-profiles-vector-indexes-and-plsql" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="under-the-hood-ai-profiles-vector-indexes-and-plsql">Under the hood: AI profiles, vector indexes, and PL/SQL</h2>
<p>Toward the end of the session, the speakers briefly peel back the abstraction and show what the R helper functions are doing:</p>
<ul>
<li>A <strong>PL/SQL <code>CREATE_PROFILE</code> block</strong> configures the AI profile: provider, credentials, LLM, embedding model, vector index, and parameters such as temperature and max tokens.<br>
</li>
<li>A <strong><code>CREATE_VECTOR_INDEX</code> call</strong> specifies the vector database provider (Oracle), the location in Object Storage, vector dimensionality, distance metric, and chunking options like overlap and size.<br>
</li>
<li>Other procedures drop or refresh vector indexes, and control whether sources are returned with each answer.</li>
</ul>
<p>The R wrappers simply construct these PL/SQL calls as strings, execute them via a database connectivity package, and translate the results into forms that are easy to work with in R.</p>
<p>The message to R developers is not “learn PL/SQL,” but “understand that these building blocks exist and are automated for you.”</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="who-are-the-speakers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-are-the-speakers">Who are the speakers?</h2>
<p>The session is anchored by two long-time contributors at the intersection of databases, machine learning, and R:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Mark Hornick</strong> is Senior Director of Product Management for Oracle Machine Learning and Select AI. He has more than 25 years of experience integrating machine learning into Oracle products and is Oracle’s representative to the R Consortium, as well as an advisor to the Analytics and Data Oracle User Community.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sherry LaMonica</strong> works on Oracle’s AI and Machine Learning product management team, helping organizations integrate open-source and commercial data science tools into large-scale analytical environments. She brings decades of experience supporting data-driven innovation across industries.</p></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>events</category>
  <category>r+ai</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rplusai-use-rag-from-your-database-to-gain-insights-into-the-r-consortium/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rplusai-use-rag-from-your-database-to-gain-insights-into-the-r-consortium/thumbnail-oracle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Learning Shiny, Together: A Collaborative Reading Club Around Mastering Shiny in Buenos Aires</title>
  <dc:creator>R-Ladies Buenos Aires &amp; R in Buenos Aires User Group</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/portadashiny.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Have you ever wanted to read Mastering Shiny but kept postponing it for “when things calm down”? So did we! At <a href="https://rladiesba.netlify.app/">R-Ladies Buenos Aires</a> and <a href="https://renbaires.github.io/">R en Buenos Aires</a>, many of us had Mastering Shiny sitting on our virtual shelves, always waiting for the right moment. After months (okay, maybe years) of good intentions and no progress, we realized we needed a push, and that push came from the power of community.</p>
<section id="from-solo-intentions-to-collective-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="from-solo-intentions-to-collective-learning">From Solo Intentions to Collective Learning</h2>
<p>There is an African proverb that says, <em>If you want to go fast, go alone. If you want to go far, go together.</em> We decided to turn individual intentions into collective learning. Instead of trying to read the book on our own, we organized a <strong>community-based reading club</strong>: one where we could support each other, share our doubts, and celebrate our progress. Our goals were simple. We wanted to create a friendly, welcoming environment for learning Shiny, break down the book into manageable chunks, and make space for everyone, regardless of their experience, to learn and lead.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-we-organized-the-reading-club" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-we-organized-the-reading-club">How We Organized the Reading Club</h2>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:40%;">
<p><br></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/shiny1.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:90.0%" data-fig-cap="Virtual Meeting 9: Discussion of Chapters 14 of *Mastering Shiny*"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/shiny3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Virtual Meeting 9: Discussion of Chapters 14 of <em>Mastering Shiny</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div><div class="column" style="width:60%;">
<p>We organized the club around ten meetings, which took place between March and July. Although we initially planned to read the entire book, we decided that a shorter, time-bound version would be more realistic and sustainable for the organizing team and its participants. We began planning and organizing this large-scale activity in September 2024.</p>
<p>All sessions were held online, lasting between 60 and 90 minutes. Each one was led by a different person (or pair), who walked us through the content and exercises of the assigned chapters.</p>
<p>There was no expectation of being an expert. In fact, we explicitly encouraged people with little or no prior Shiny experience to join and to lead (and they did!). The only guideline was to read the chapters, try the exercises, and come ready to share. Presenters would explain what they understood from the chapters, highlight key concepts, and guide us through the exercises. Then the magic happened: we’d collectively fill in the gaps, ask questions, offer alternatives, and learn from one another.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Most presenters created slides or notebooks to guide their sessions (though this wasn’t mandatory). We collected all those materials in this <a href="https://github.com/RLadies-BA/mastering-shiny">public GitHub repository</a>, with a variety of formats and styles. We deliberately avoided imposing a specific format as we didn’t want technical barriers to stop anyone from sharing. Eventually, we plan to curate and organize the materials to make them easier to reuse, especially for Spanish-speaking learners. We believe there’s real added value in having community-built learning materials in Spanish.</p>
<p>Over time, participants started to share the Shiny apps they were building on their own. We added a small “Show and Tell” section to the beginning of some meetings, where people presented their work-in-progress and received feedback and encouragement. It was a space full of mutual support, curiosity, and honest learning.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/shiny2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Summary of the Reading Club’s Last Meeting</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Although we recorded the sessions, we decided to make them accessible only to attendees. This was different from our chapters’ usual practice, but we wanted to keep the sessions informal, comfortable, and pressure-free — more like a study group than a workshop. This allowed everyone to feel safe sharing unfinished work, asking questions, and making mistakes.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflections-and-lessons-learned" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflections-and-lessons-learned">Reflections and Lessons Learned</h2>
<p>Throughout the series, different people volunteered to lead the sessions. These volunteers included academics and industry professionals with a variety of backgrounds and levels of experience with R. Each volunteer brought their own style and perspective to the sessions, and all of them did a fantastic job. Although a small core group participated in most sessions, many others joined according to their interests or availability.</p>
<p>We were surprised to have new community members who took advantage of the virtual format to join us from other countries and cities in Argentina. This allowed us to break down the barriers of physical presence and discuss topics of interest from different professional areas in Spanish.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, one idea for a future iteration is to organize the sessions around building a single Shiny app together. We believe this could help sustain engagement, make the learning more tangible, and give participants the chance to immediately see how the book’s concepts connect in practice.</p>
<p>One of the most rewarding aspects of the book club was hearing what participants took away from the experience. Beyond Shiny itself, people highlighted the joy of learning together, the responsibility of having regular meetings, and the warmth of the community. By the end of the club, several participants left feeling motivated and thinking of strategies to improve their work by creating a Shiny app or exploring a topic to take their first steps with a dashboard.</p>
<section id="here-are-some-of-their-reflections-translated-from-spanish" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="here-are-some-of-their-reflections-translated-from-spanish">Here are some of their reflections (translated from Spanish):</h3>
<div class="html-div" style="text-align:center; font-style:italic; margin-bottom:2em;">
<p>“The format of coming together to analyze the chapters of a book with technical content seemed brilliant to me. It opens up an horizontal learning space that is very enriching.”</p>
<div style="text-align:right; font-style:italic;">
Graciela Bellotti
</div>
</div>
<div class="html-div" style="text-align:center; font-style:italic; margin-bottom:2em;">
<p>“I really liked that everyone shared everything, holding nothing back, and explained what they had understood—whether from prior experience or from their own research on the chapter’s content. They made it very enjoyable and not too heavy, so I was able to attend all the sessions”</p>
<div style="text-align:right; font-style:italic;">
Daniela Zacharías
</div>
</div>
<div class="html-div" style="text-align:center; font-style:italic; margin-bottom:2em;">
<p>“So much! Not only everything related to Shiny, but also the joy of sharing these meetings with such amazing people—both presenting and exchanging doubts or knowledge.”</p>
<div style="text-align:right; font-style:italic;">
Laura Misiani
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="wrapping-up" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h2>
<p>This reading club wasn’t just about working through a technical book. It was about carving out time for learning, growing confidence, building apps (and community!), and showing that you don’t need to know everything to lead or participate. If you’ve also been meaning to read Mastering Shiny, maybe this is your sign to gather your group and start together. Because when we learn together, we go further and we have more fun along the way.</p>
<section id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-ladies-buenos-aires-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-ladies-buenos-aires-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following">You can reach out to R-Ladies Buenos Aires &amp; R in Buenos Aires through the following:</h3>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/38664570?s=200&amp;v=4.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div><div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<ul>
<li><p>Linkedin: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rladies-ba/">https://www.linkedin.com/company/rladies-ba/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Instagram:<a href="https://www.instagram.com/rladiesba/?hl=en">https://www.instagram.com/rladiesba</a></p></li>
<li><p>X: <a href="https://twitter.com/rladiesba?lang=en">https://twitter.com/rladiesba</a></p></li>
<li><p>Website: <a href="https://rladiesba.netlify.app/">https://rladiesba.netlify.app/</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://renbaires.github.io/image/BA-1.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div><div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<ul>
<li><p>Linkedin: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires" class="uri">https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires</a></p></li>
<li><p>Instagram: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires">https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires</a></p></li>
<li><p>X: <a href="https://x.com/renbaires">https://x.com/renbaires</a></p></li>
<li><p>Website: <a href="https://renbaires.github.io/" class="uri">https://renbaires.github.io/</a></p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h3>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html" class="uri">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rugs</category>
  <category>south america</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/learning-shiny-together-a-collaborative-reading-club-around-mastering-shiny-in-buenos-aires/portadashiny.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Sovereign Tech Fund invests $450,000 in R Foundation to Enhance R’s Sustainability and Security</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/Rlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R ecosystem, a cornerstone of statistical computing and data science, is poised for significant enhancements in its long-term health and security. With a new investment of USD $450,000 (€392,000) from the <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/tech/r-project">Sovereign Tech Fund (STF)</a>, the <a href="https://www.r-project.org/foundation/">R Foundation</a> is embarking on a crucial project to modernize R’s core infrastructure, improve its maintainability, and fortify its supply chain.</p>
<p>This initiative is championed by the R Foundation and the R Core Team. The R Foundation is a not-for-profit organization providing crucial financial and logistical support for the R project. Established by the members of the R Core Team, its primary mission is to ensure the continued success and stability of R for the global community. The Foundation, based in Vienna, Austria, holds the copyright for R software and uses its resources to support development and foster innovation in statistical computing. The R Core Team is the dedicated group of developers with write access to the R source code, who volunteer their time to guide the technical evolution of the language.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/urbanek.jpg" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>To understand the impact of this grant, we sat down with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/simon-urbanek-08b973106/?originalSubdomain=nz">Simon Urbanek</a>, a key member of the R Core Team and an Associate Professor in Statistics at the University of Auckland. Simon shared his insights on what this funding means for the future of R and how the community can play a part.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>R Consortium: What core problem or opportunity does the commissioned work from the Sovereign Tech Fund help the R Foundation address?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> The main reason we are spearheading this effort is to increase the sustainability and maintainability of the R project. Sustainability, in the sense of making sure that the R codebase itself can be maintained long into the future, ensuring we have continuity and making that process easier.</p>
<p>This investment also helps us address increasing concerns around software supply chain security. This has to do with provenance and reliability—ensuring that users can be assured that a particular piece of software comes from the right source. This involves initiatives like signing sources and binaries to verify their origin.</p>
<p>Finally, a key component is reproducibility. We want to ensure that analyses and results can be reproduced reliably, both by the original authors and by others in the community.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: You mentioned provenance and the need for verification. Is this being driven by new regulations?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> Not directly by regulation, no. This is more of a proactive measure. Given the age of the R project, our distribution model has traditionally been a central repository where people can simply download files. While this has served us well, the open-source world has seen various security issues, making it clear that we need better ways to verify that software comes from a trusted source.</p>
<p>We already have binary signing for R itself on macOS and Windows, but this hasn’t been extended to packages. It’s an important step to take. While it’s not clear if platforms like Microsoft will officially require it, there are indications they may. We want to prepare for that possibility and strengthen the security of the ecosystem, especially for a central distribution hub like CRAN.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: Why is tackling this problem now timely for the R ecosystem and the wider open-source community?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> R has been around for over 25 years and has become part of the fabric of data analytics and statistical analysis in government, academia, and commercial entities. With this level of adoption, it’s critical that we can sustain the maintenance of R to support its community. The purely volunteer-driven effort that got us here may not be sufficient to address the increasing complexities and threats we see today.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: What tangible deliverables can the community expect, and on what timeline?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> The main improvements will be within R itself, and some may be under the hood. Deliverables include replacing legacy code and older third-party projects that were integrated into R for historical reasons. This will make R more maintainable, as we won’t have to oversee unmaintained code.</p>
<p>We are also focused on making it easier to port R to new platforms, such as the Windows ARM platform. Other improvements will be more visible to developers, including enhanced documentation and better tooling, with the goal of making it easier for new people to contribute to R.</p>
<p>The work is expected to take place over the next 18 months. We hope that the foundations we lay during this project will carry over and continue to be useful long after the project officially concludes.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: Who are the key people and teams involved in this initiative?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> A significant portion of the technical work—including bug triage, platform improvements, and replacing old infrastructure—will be done by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kalibera/?originalSubdomain=cz">Tomas Kalibera</a>. As a member of the R Core Team, Tomas is one of the most active developers of the R interpreter, and his deep expertise in R’s internals and build systems makes him uniquely suited to lead the modernization of R’s core. This grant provides vital support for him to dedicate his time to these foundational improvements that are critical for R’s long-term health.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/kalibera.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Other efforts, especially around documentation and community engagement, will be led by various R Core members. This entire project was conceived with the help of the R Foundation board members, and we also hope to collaborate with the R Consortium to bring in more contributors from the community.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: What makes the Sovereign Tech Fund a uniquely suitable partner for this initiative?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> The Sovereign Tech Fund is a really good match because its mission is perfectly aligned with our needs. Their main focus is on sustainability for open-source software and strengthening digital public infrastructure, which is exactly our primary concern at the moment. We want to ensure R’s development is sustainable and that the community itself can support it without having to rely on commercial partners.</p>
<p>This investment allows us to modernize the codebase to make it easier to maintain and, at the same time, build resources to encourage more community contributions.</p>
<p><strong>R Consortium: How can the R community get involved and contribute to this effort?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Simon Urbanek:</strong> There are many ways for the community to get involved. People can definitely provide feedback, especially as we add new user-facing features and create new documentation. We need to know if these resources are truly making it easier for the community to contribute.</p>
<p>Another area is bug triage. We aim to reduce the number of pending bugs, especially older ones, to make the bug tracker less overwhelming. The community can help identify and work on important issues.</p>
<p>Finally, we will need help with testing. This is true for improvements in R itself and for new infrastructure related to packages, such as containerized checks for reproducibility and the adoption of code signing. The community’s participation in testing, providing feedback, and adopting these new practices will be invaluable.</p>
<section id="r-foundation-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-foundation-resources">R Foundation resources</h2>
<p>Main site: <a href="https://www.r-project.org/foundation/">https://www.r-project.org/foundation/</a><br>
How you can contribute: <a href="https://contributor.r-project.org/">https://contributor.r-project.org/</a></p>
<p>The <a href="https://user2025.r-project.org/">useR! 2025</a> conference was held at Duke University, in Durham, NC, USA, on August 8-10. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/r-user-community_announcement-user-2026-conference-in-activity-7360399846479917058-IxDU/">Next year’s event will be in Warsaw, Poland.</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>announcements</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/sovereign-tech-fund-invests-450000-in-r-foundation-to-enhance-r-sustainability-and-security/Rlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="112" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Oracle R Distribution 4.4.1 Now Available with Enhanced Performance</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/oracle-r-distribution-441-now-available-with-enhanced-performance/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/oracle-r-distribution-441-now-available-with-enhanced-performance/oracle-machine-learning-header.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Oracle has released Oracle R Distribution 4.4.1, a free enhanced build of R with performance improvements of up to 2.5× in benchmark testing. These gains come from optimized use of Intel’s Math Kernel Library. ORD 4.4.1 is now available across supported platforms, offering R users faster computation and enterprise-level support.</p>
<p>For more details, see the full announcement blog from Oracle:</p>
<section id="oracle-r-distribution-4.4.1-now-available-with-enhanced-performance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="oracle-r-distribution-4.4.1-now-available-with-enhanced-performance"><a href="https://blogs.oracle.com/machinelearning/post/oracle-r-distribution-441-now-available-with-enhanced-performance">Oracle R Distribution 4.4.1 Now Available with Enhanced Performance</a></h3>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>announcements</category>
  <category>members</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/oracle-r-distribution-441-now-available-with-enhanced-performance/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/oracle-r-distribution-441-now-available-with-enhanced-performance/oracle-machine-learning-header.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="49" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>🚀 R Consortium Technical Grant Cycle Opens Today — Your Chance to Make a Mark</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-consortium-technical-grant-cycle-opens-today/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It’s official: the R Consortium Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC) has opened the second grant cycle of 2025 today, September 1, 2025. If you’ve ever thought, <em>“I have an idea that could make life better for R users everywhere”</em>, this is your chance.</p>
<section id="call-for-proposals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="call-for-proposals"><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">Call for Proposals</a></h2>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="what-the-isc-is-looking-for" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-the-isc-is-looking-for"><strong>What the ISC Is Looking For</strong></h2>
<p>The ISC focuses projects that deliver practical impact for the R community:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tools and packages</strong> that smooth workflows and make R more powerful.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Education resources</strong> like documentation, tutorials, reproducible workflows.<br>
</li>
<li><strong>Infrastructure</strong> that connects people, supports open science, or broadens access.</li>
</ul>
<p>The sweet spot? Proposals that are clear, scoped, and realistic. Don’t over-promise—break down big ideas into digestible, doable steps.</p>
<p>High-risk, high-reward moonshots aren’t the target here. ISC grants back low-to-medium-risk projects with clear deliverables. A bit of work done already—sketches, prototypes, drafts—shows you’re ready to go.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="whats-not-covered" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-not-covered"><strong>What’s Not Covered</strong></h2>
<p>Just so you don’t waste your time: events, conferences, and meetups belong under the <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html"><strong>RUGS funding program</strong></a>, not this one. ISC grants are for infrastructure and technical or social projects that scale across the community.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="how-to-apply" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-apply"><strong>How to Apply</strong></h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Download and use the ISC proposal template.<br>
</li>
<li>Build your submission as a single PDF—self-contained and clear.<br>
</li>
<li>Submit it through the Google Form (yes, you’ll need a Google account).<br>
</li>
<li>Look for a confirmation email with a subject <em>“Thank you for your proposal!”</em>—and check spam if you don’t see it.</li>
</ol>
<p>Bonus tip: Read the ISC’s standard agreement now so you’re not surprised later.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="why-bother-because-this-is-big" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-bother-because-this-is-big"><strong>Why Bother? Because This Is Big</strong></h2>
<p>This is one of only <strong>two ISC grant windows per year</strong>. Grants get paid in two chunks—half when you sign, half when you finish—so you know you’ll be supported from the start through the finish line.</p>
<p>Over the past few years, ISC grants have funded projects that strengthened core R tools, expanded internationalization, improved documentation, and built bridges across the ecosystem. It’s not just about money—it’s about visibility, credibility, and lasting community impact.</p>
<p>When you’re funded, your work gets showcased to the global R community. You’re not just solving your own problem—you’re leveling up tools and workflows for thousands of R users worldwide.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="time-to-jump-in" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="time-to-jump-in"><strong>Time to Jump In</strong></h2>
<p>If you’ve been tinkering on a package, sketching a new teaching resource, thinking of ways to make R more inclusive, or dreaming of infrastructure that smooths collaboration—this is your launchpad.</p>
<p>Don’t hold back. Share your idea, shape it into a proposal, and send it in.</p>
<p><strong>Submissions close October 1.</strong></p>
<p>Your idea could be the one that pushes the R ecosystem forward!</p>
</section>
<section id="call-for-proposals-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="call-for-proposals-1"><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">Call for Proposals</a></h2>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>grants</category>
  <category>infrastructure</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-consortium-technical-grant-cycle-opens-today/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-consortium-technical-grant-cycle-opens-today/apply-now.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Spotify Stats and Real Estate Insights: R User Group Finland Builds Practical Projects</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vboned/">Vicent Boned</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marc-eixarch/">Marc Eixarch</a>, organizers of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-finland/">R User Group Finland</a>, spoke with the R Consortium about how they revived the local R community by focusing on fun, practical applications of R. Drawing on their experience from Barcelona’s tech scene, they took over an inactive R group and began hosting engaging meetups focused on real-world applications of R. From building custom Spotify Wrapped-style reports to analyzing Helsinki’s real estate market, they’ve created a meetup environment where data enthusiasts can explore R through real-world use cases that go beyond the workplace.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/RUGFinlandorganizers.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>L-R: Hazel Kavili (R-Ladies Helsinki Organizer), Marc Eixarch, Vicent Boned</p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-in-the-rugs-group-or-the-r-community." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-in-the-rugs-group-or-the-r-community.">Please share your background and involvement in the RUGS group or the R Community.</h2>
<p><strong>Vicent:</strong> I’m a data analyst. I first learned R in university and used it for 10 to 12 years. We used to live in Barcelona, a large city with a very active tech community. We were involved with the R user group and another popular meetup called Data Beers. It’s still running, but we’ve attended many of those events and enjoyed them.</p>
<p>When we moved to Finland, I began searching for similar community activities, but I couldn’t find many. I found a meetup group, but it was inactive, so I reached out to the organizer. He told me he had moved out of Helsinki and was happy to pass on the group’s organization to someone new. That’s how we took over the R user group in Finland. We’re not Finnish, but now we’re working to organize events here and stay connected with other data analysts.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/RUGFinlandLogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="whats-your-level-of-experience-with-the-r-language" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-your-level-of-experience-with-the-r-language">What’s your level of experience with the R language?</h2>
<p><strong>Marc:</strong> I first encountered R in a university stats course, but I started working with it seriously once I became a data analyst. I’ve been in this role for approximately six or seven years, with a primary focus on data analysis. I work extensively with the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/">tidyverse</a> and <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot</a> for data visualization, preparation, and gathering data from various sources, such as APIs and databases. That’s my main strength in R.</p>
<p>Occasionally, I take on small projects to explore more technical areas, such as package development, but in those areas, I’m more of a casual user than an expert. So, that’s a good summary of my experience level.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/MarcExirach.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Vicent:</strong> I’ve used R throughout my career, mainly for data analysis and visualization. While I’ve explored other packages through side projects, my current work primarily revolves around tidyverse, ggplot, and <a href="https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/">dplyr</a> for tables and reporting. At my company, we also utilize some Posit tools, such as <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a>, and occasionally Shiny for prototyping.</p>
<p>I used Shiny years ago in my second job when it was a new package. I didn’t work with it for many years after that, so it’s been exciting to see how much it has evolved. I’ve also attended several RStudio conferences, and it has been great to follow the development of the Tidyverse over time.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/VicentBoned.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry">Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting related to your industry?</h2>
<p><strong>Vicent:</strong> At work, I use R for almost everything. I work for a gaming company, so my job involves analyzing user behavior and understanding how they interact with the app. This involves a significant amount of data exploration and visualization, as we have a wealth of data on nearly every action users take in the game. I often present my findings to non-technical team members, so I use R to create reports and presentations with Quarto, which I then share with the team. Your day-to-day work looks quite similar!</p>
<p>Recently—or, to be more precise, last year—I worked on a side project while searching for an apartment to buy in Helsinki. I used R to explore the real estate market, gathering data over a few months to track trends. I built a small tool to filter listings based on different criteria, which was helpful for my search.</p>
<p><strong>Marc:</strong> I’ve worked on a few small side projects, usually based on things I’m curious about or enjoy. I’m really into music, and one time, I discovered an API that lets you access Spotify data using R. With it, you can pull public data from Spotify and even create your own “Spotify Wrapped” experience. I liked this use case so much that I turned it into a <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-finland/events/291613918/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">workshop</a> for one of our events. I prepared a tutorial and shared the code in advance, and then about 10–15 of us walked through it together. Everyone can input their username to customize the script, which displays their top artists, playlist vibe, or other insights based on their Spotify data.</p>
<p>We have posted the project on GitHub, making it available for anyone to review. It was especially noteworthy because one attendee, Antti, took the project a step further by expanding it into a web application. He added functionality that allows you to type in something like “sad, melancholic metal,” which suggests a fitting band or song. He got creative; we even got permission to share the app link. It was one of my favorite projects to see grow beyond the workshop! <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/spotifyr/index.html">{spotifyr} on CRAN</a> and <a href="https://github.com/charlie86/spotifyr">on GitHub</a></p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/spotify-stats-and-real-estate-insights-r-user-group-finland-builds-practical-projects/RUGFinlandLogo-homepage.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="172" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
