<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Consortium</title>
<link>https://r-consortium.org/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://r-consortium.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.42</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>R Submissions Working Group: Pilot 5 Launch and more!</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/pilot5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="pilot-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5">Pilot 5</h3>
<p>Last year the <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">submission working group</a> was able to successfully deliver its third R-based submission to the FDA through the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/electronic-regulatory-submission-and-review/electronic-common-technical-document-ectd">eCTD portal</a> on September 20, 2024. We are excited to share news the Pilot 5 launch as we continue to demonstrate R’s capablities to deliver a high-quality drug submission.</p>
<p>A quick recap of previous Pilots:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/blog/2021/12/08/successful-r-based-test-package-submitted-to-fda">Pilot 1</a> delivered Tables and Figures to the FDA using R.</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/blog/2022/12/07/update-successful-r-based-package-submission-with-shiny-component-to-fda">Pilot 2</a> delivered the same Tables and Figures using a Shiny App using R. <a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/announcement/2023/10/05/shiny-app-successfully-reviewed-by-fda-cder-staff-pilot-2-announcement-2">Pilot 2 Announcement 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/news-from-r-submissions-working-group-pilot-3/">Pilot 3</a> delivered the Tables and Figures using R as well as the ADaMs…you guessed it using R.</li>
<li><a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/">Pilot 4</a> is in the process of delivering the Shiny App from Pilot 2 using webassembly and containers (almost completed!).</li>
</ul>
<p>For information on these Pilots navigate to our <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/pilot_background.html">Pilot’s background page on submission working group</a></p>
<p>Now in 2025, we are launching Pilot 5!! We will be using R again, but instead of delivering all the datasets as <code>xpt</code> files we will make use of the new <code>datasetjson</code> format via the eponymously named R package <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/">datasetjson</a> and hope to deliver two submissions for 2025 split into Part 1 and Part 2.</p>
<p><strong>Pilot 5 - Part 1</strong></p>
<p>Part 1 is going to replicate <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam">Pilot 3</a>. We will reuse the ADaMs, Tables and Figure programs that were written in R. However, the Pilot 3 ADaMs were written out as <code>xpt</code> files and we will instead use <code>datasetjson</code>! Hence Pilot 5 is really focused on using the new transport file type <code>datasetjson</code>.</p>
<p>Pilot 5 Part 1 will also submit all the other files you find in the Pilot 3 submission as part of our package. If you have a passion for submission work, R and <code>datasetjson</code> or just want to see what all the fuss is about then come and <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/rconsortium/shared_invite/zt-2w4t2jd38-Z7BYYse9tIlCZEmqHvHnbA">join us</a>!</p>
<p><strong>Pilot 5 - Part 2</strong></p>
<p>The Pilots are small! 5 ADaMs, 3 Tables and 1 Figure is not a typical submission package for a drug that can impact a patient’s health and well-being! The Pilots have always been about testing out and advocating that R can keep up with the best of the best. For Part 2, we want to build up this body of work and develop several more ADaMs and more Tables and Figures. As in Part 1, we will deliver everything using <code>datasetjson</code> that would of been delivered as an <code>xpt</code> file.</p>
<p>We plan on kicking Part 2 off mid-summer, but planning will probably start soon! Come <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/rconsortium/shared_invite/zt-2w4t2jd38-Z7BYYse9tIlCZEmqHvHnbA">join</a> in on the fun and help us build a larger body of work around drug submissions using R.</p>
</section>
<section id="progress-reports-and-future-plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="progress-reports-and-future-plans">Progress Reports and Future Plans</h2>
<p><strong>Updates on Pilot 4</strong></p>
<p>The objective of the R Consortium R submission <em>Pilot 4 </em>Project is to explore the use of novel technologies such as Linux containers and WebAssembly to bundle a Shiny application into a self-contained package, facilitating a smoother process of both transferring and executing the application. The application was built using the source data sets and analyses contained in the R submission <em>Pilot 1-3</em>. To our knowledge, this is the first publicly available submission package that includes a WebAssembly component. We hope this submission package and what we have learned can serve as a good reference for future regulatory submission efforts. The WebAssembly technology compiles applications into a portable, consistent environment driven by a web browser, allowing agency reviewers to easily run and evaluate software without complex setups. The second half of the Pilot 4 Project (leveraging container technology to package a Shiny application) will be submitted as an additional package later this year. Additional agency feedback will be shared in future communications.</p>
<p>The R Consortium is excited to announce that, on September 20, 2024, the R Submissions Working Group successfully submitted its test submission package—featuring a WebAssembly component—through the FDA’s Electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD) gateway! This marks a significant milestone as the FDA Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER) staff has officially received the submission package.</p>
<p>Statistician Eric Nantz at pharmaceuticals company Eli Lilly in Indianapolis, Indiana, says that using WebAssembly “will minimize, from the reviewer’s perspective, many of the steps that they had to take to get the application running on their machines.”</p>
<p><strong>Potential Pilot 6</strong></p>
<p>The Pilots have been making use of the original CDISC Pilot data from around 2008-2010 that were used as PoC for the FDA for CDISC standards. This data has been reused for many other projects across the industry as there is a severe lack of publicly available CDISC data. You can read about my quest to find some more data <a href="https://pharmaverse.github.io/blog/posts/2025-02-17_data__packages/data__packages.html">here</a>. The submissions working group would like to create new simulated data from raw, SDTM and ADaMs that could be used to test new techniques, ways of working, etc all brought up to modern standards. If interested get in touch!</p>
<p><strong>A re-envisioned ADRG</strong></p>
<p>The Analysis Data Reviewer’s Guide (ADRG) has been focused on the proprietary language SAS for delivering submissions over the many years. As open-source languages such as R are accepted as valid mechanisms to deliver a submission the ADRG needs to “re-envisioned” to accommodate these languages. The pilots have had questions on how document certain technical aspects in the ADRG of the R-based submission package, e.g.&nbsp;packages used and versions, R versions and layouts of the file folders.</p>
<p>Well we are in luck. Former Pilot members are working with the PHUSE Version Metadata for Open-Source Languages to support ADRG enhancements for open-source submissions and are sharing their recommendations to the Pilots. You can find out more at the below links:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://advance.hub.phuse.global/wiki/x/UzOZAQ">Communication of Version Metadata for Open-Source Languages</a></li>
<li><a href="https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/">Welcome to the PHUSE Open-Source Metadata Documentation Working Group Site</a></li>
<li><a href="https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/references/problem_statement.html">Problem Statement</a></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>More about the R Submissions Working Group</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">R Consortium R Submissions Working Group</a> is focused on improving practices for R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions.</p>
<p>Health authority agencies from different countries require electronic submission of data, computer programs, and relevant documentation to bring an experimental clinical product to market. In the past, submissions have mainly been based on the SAS language.</p>
<p>In recent years, the use of open source languages, especially the R language, has become very popular in the pharmaceutical industry and research institutions. Although the health authorities accept submissions based on open source programming languages, sponsors may be hesitant to conduct submissions using open source languages due to a lack of working examples.</p>
<p>Therefore, the R Submissions Working Group aims to provide R-based submission examples and identify potential gaps while submitting these example packages. All materials, including submission examples and communications, are publicly available on the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium">R consortium GitHub page.</a></p>
<p><strong>Join the R Submissions Working Group</strong></p>
<p>The R Submissions Working Group comprises members from over 10 pharmaceutical companies, as well as regulatory agencies. We are a collaborative community open to anyone interested in contributing to this important work. For more information, or to get involved, visit <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg">our website</a> or contact us directly at director@r-consortium.org.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/pilot5.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Seville R Users Group: R’s Role in Optimization Research and Stroke Prevention</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alberto-torrej%C3%B3n-valenzuela/?locale=en_US">Alberto Torrejon Valenzuela</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sevilla-r-users/">Seville R Users Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the dynamic growth of the R community in Seville and the group’s role in fostering collaboration across academia and industry. Alberto shared highlights from hosting the Third Spanish R Conference, which brought together local and international participants. He discussed the group’s initiatives, including monthly workshops and online outreach through platforms like YouTube. He also reflected on his research in optimization and a collaborative project analyzing stroke prevention, showcasing how R drives innovation in scientific research and community development.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/AlbertoValenzuela.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My name is Alberto Torrejon Valenzuela. I am from Los Barrios, a town in Cádiz, southern Spain. I have moved to Seville, which is a bit further north, where I studied for a double degree in Mathematics and Statistics. During my studies, one of my professors introduced me to R. Although I was learning several programming languages, I realized that I could accomplish everything I needed with just R. Since then, I have continued to use it throughout my studies.</p>
<p>I also joined the R group in Sevilla, which I discovered through Meetup. It was another motivation to enhance my R skills. The Sevilla R Users Group meets at the University of Sevilla’s facilities every one to two months. During these meetings, we discuss our work and share our experiences. Our group includes many users from academia and industry, making our discussions very diverse. We enjoy discussing our various implementation packages and applications; hearing from both perspectives is always interesting.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGOrganizers.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Your Group recently hosted the <a href="https://www.imus.us.es/congresos/IIIRqueR/">Third Spanish R Conference</a>. Please share some details about the event.</strong></p>
<p>The Third Spanish R Conference took place from November 6 to 8 in Seville, co-organized by the <a href="https://www.imus.us.es/www/">Institute of Mathematics at the University of Seville</a> and Sevilla R group, with support from the R Consortium and several other organizations.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference1.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>We used a catchy slogan for the conference: “R tiene un color especial” (R has a special color). This is a modification of the lyrics of a famous song about Seville that everyone in Spain knows. It became a hit!</p>
<p>The conference featured a wide range of activities from both scientific and social perspectives. We had four plenary speakers: <a href="https://jakubnowosad.com/">Jakub Nowosad</a>, from University of Münster, and <a href="https://www.frick.ws/">Hannah Frick</a> from POSIT, along with national speakers <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rosanaferrero/?originalSubdomain=es">Rosana Ferrero</a>, who is very active in social networking, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/javier-tejedor-aguilera/?originalSubdomain=es">Javier Tejedor Aguilera</a> from <a href="https://www.endesa.com/en">Endesa</a>, who represents the industry.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference2.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>Additionally, it’s important to mention that the group recognized the contributions of two founding members, <a href="https://frodriguezsanchez.net/">Francisco Rodriguez-Sanchez</a> and <a href="https://jeronimocarranza.github.io/">Jerónimo Carranza</a>, during the conference. We honored them with a gift to acknowledge their hard work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference3.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>Organizing a conference, like the one in Spain, is quite a significant undertaking. In addition to the conference, the group hosts monthly meetings called “TalleR”, the Spanish word for workshop. We typically emphasize the “R” at the end of the word. We exchange knowledge about our packages and various other topics during these meetings.</p>
<p>We primarily use social networks to connect with the local community, including the former <a href="https://x.com/_SevillaR">Twitter</a> (now known as X), <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/sevillar.bsky.social">BlueSky</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gruposevillar/">LinkedIn</a>. We rely on our Meetup page to organise the event, where we post details about our seminars or talleres. People can indicate whether they will attend in person or online, making this a helpful tool. Additionally, since some members are researchers and professors in the University of Seville, we have support from Microsoft Teams to stream and record these meetings, as many participants come from South American and Spanish-speaking countries. For example, in our last meeting, we had attendees from Panama and Colombia.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGMeeting.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>After the meeting, we usually post our recordings on our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4_SN0le5WFMu_LFaIufLbA">YouTube</a> channel. Every session is recorded there. We also have a <a href="https://sevillarusers.netlify.app/">website</a> and a <a href="https://t.me/+HE3IBL13swTfZwYI">Telegram</a> group where we engage in more active discussions. This is mainly for our meetings.</p>
<p>However, as you mentioned, organizing a large conference like the Spanish R Conference requires additional support. We received this support from the Institute of Mathematics at the University of Seville, which provided significant assistance regarding the location and logistics of our conference. Since our successful collaboration with the Institute of Mathematics, our local group has been keen to maintain and expand this partnership to enhance our meetings held at the Institute.</p>
<p>Additionally, a significant portion of our support came from the Spanish Association known as <a href="https://r-es.org/">R-Hispano</a>. They provided valuable tools and assistance when co-organizing our events, which has been incredibly helpful. We’re also thankful for financial support from the R Consortium.</p>
<p><strong>How do you use R for your work?</strong></p>
<p>I use both R and Python for my <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Alberto-Torrejon-Valenzuela">research</a>. I have two distinct lives: a professional and a personal one. In my free time, I enjoy programming, and I also need to program in my professional life. My research focuses on optimization.</p>
<p>Optimization models aim to find the best solution to a given problem. I work in a lab run by <a href="https://scholar.google.es/citations?user=koF66usAAAAJ&amp;hl=es">Justo Puerto</a>, a full professor in the Department of Statistics and Operations. One of the primary areas I’m involved in is ordered optimization, which involves sorting procedures to identify the best solutions to various combinatorial and decision optimization problems.</p>
<p>We study numerous problems, ranging from logistics issues, such as resource or facility location problems, to statistical issues like linear regression or efficient statistics computation. The framework of ordered optimization allows us to generalize these problems to include abstract concepts such as equity or minimizing envy among clients. For instance, we can optimize the location of a supermarket, hospital, voting center, or bus and train lines, ensuring equitable access so that no one feels envious of their neighbors.</p>
<p>Additionally, we apply these algorithms to statistical problems to improve the computation or estimators. The optimization community is familiar with Python algorithms and packages, but the R community is catching up. I use several R packages, including <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ROI/index.html">ROI</a> and <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ompr/index.html">OMPR</a>, allowing comprehensive data analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, primarily related to your industry?</strong></p>
<p>I am discussing a topic that highlights one of R’s best uses in boosting and supporting community initiatives. Since I work at the Institute of Mathematics, a research team from Hospital Universitario Virgen Macarena contacted us for statistical support. I was the first to volunteer, and we signed a collaboration contract to begin our work.</p>
<p>The project I’m currently involved in focuses on<a href="https://www.ibis-sevilla.es/es/investigacion/neurociencias/neurovascular/">studying and preventing strokes through analyzing large databases</a>. Stroke is one of the worst medical conditions from the point of view of rapid care for the affected person because when it occurs, there is usually a very short period of time until brain death is reached. Timely care is essential for improving outcomes.</p>
<p>This research is crucial for the team led by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joanmanelmontaner/?originalSubdomain=es">Joan Montaner</a>, which is focused on finding the best combination of drugs for stroke prevention. They aim to provide effective medications to individuals diagnosed with a stroke to improve their chances of survival, especially within the critical first 24 hours.</p>
<p>The team has access to a historical dataset of more than 100,000 patients, and I am analyzing this data using our software tools. We are uncovering some interesting insights, and we hope this information will assist them in testing these drug combinations. Ultimately, we aim to help develop more extensive protocols for administering these medications to patients.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGOrganizers.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Connecting Nebraska Through R: Jeffrey Stevens’ Journey of Community Building</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jeffreyrstevens/">Jeffrey Stevens</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/nebraskarusergroup/">Nebraska R User Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about his efforts to establish a vibrant R community across Nebraska. Jeffrey shared insights into the group’s activities, including fostering connections between academics, industry professionals, and nonprofits, and creating a hybrid model to engage participants from across the state. He also discussed his passion for package development, open science initiatives like the Many Dogs Project, and the challenges of building an inclusive R ecosystem in a geographically dispersed region.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/JeffreyStevens.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>I am a professor of psychology at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, where I lead the <a href="https://dogcog.unl.edu/">Canine Cognition and Human Interaction Lab</a>. My research focuses on animals, comparative psychology, and animal cognition, a field I have been involved in since the mid-1990s.</p>
<p>I have been using R for over 15 years, but I initially worked with S-Plus during my graduate studies in the late 1990s. For the past 15 years, R has been my primary tool for data analysis.</p>
<p>In the last three years, I have also ventured into package development. To date, I have published three packages on <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/">CRAN</a>. One package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/excluder/index.html">excluder</a> is designed for data wrangling specifically tailored for survey data that psychologists often encounter. Another package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/flashr/index.html">flashr</a> creates flashcard slide decks to assist learners in mastering R; it includes R functions and descriptions, allowing students to familiarize themselves with terms and functionalities. My most recent package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/cocoon/index.html">cocoon</a> takes statistical objects. It generates <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a> or <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a> text that can be easily inserted into documents, making extracting and presenting the statistics you need simpler.</p>
<p>I teach R to diverse learners, including undergraduates, graduate students, postdocs, lab managers, and some faculty members. Additionally, I serve as a data science mentor for <a href="https://posit.co/">Posit</a>, guiding corporate individuals through data science training programs. In this role, I lead cohorts of employees seeking to enhance their R and data science skills. I have participated in several of these mentoring sessions, and my extensive experience with R has made it an essential part of my daily work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebraskaRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="what-was-your-motivation-behind-starting-this-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-was-your-motivation-behind-starting-this-r-user-group">What was your motivation behind starting this R User group?</h2>
<p>I know a few people at my university who use R, but there are just a handful here and there—not many. Most of them were using it for their projects. Then, about two years ago, I discovered that there was a faculty member in the Statistics Department named <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/srvanderplas/">Susan VanderPlas</a>. She had joined the department a bit earlier, but that was when I first learned about her. I found out that she shared my passion for R; she is also an R user and an educator enthusiastic about building websites and engaging with the community. She was the first person at my university with whom I connected over our shared interest in R.</p>
<p>I proposed starting an R user group, but she initially suggested we take a different approach. Last year, instead of forming a formal user group, we contacted everyone on campus who used R. The goal was to gather and have informal monthly chats about R-related topics. During our meetings, we discussed various subjects. The first gathering occurred right after <a href="https://posit.co/conference/">Posit::Conf</a>, where we shared our experiences from that conference.</p>
<p>As we continued meeting, I realised that my original vision was establishing a dedicated user group for R enthusiasts. Susan and I started a user group after talking with others on board with the idea. I took the initiative to move forward with it, and the R consortium grant was the primary motivation that pushed us to get serious about this project. Preparing the grant proposal was what got things started. Without that grant, I’m not sure we would have progressed as far as we have.</p>
<p>While I’m leading this initiative, Susan is also helping out. It’s important to me that we extend our reach beyond the university. While most of my connections are within the university, I want to engage with other universities, government, and industry groups. That’s why we aim to connect with the broader community in Nebraska.</p>
<p>I learned there was a group in Omaha, about an hour from my location in Lincoln, Nebraska, but it has become inactive. We invited anyone from Omaha, Lincoln, and surrounding areas to join us.</p>
<p>Nebraska is not a very populous state. Most of the population is concentrated in Lincoln and Omaha, leaving many smaller towns with fewer residents. However, we wanted to ensure that people from these smaller areas also had the opportunity to participate, so we decided to make our initiative statewide rather than city-specific.</p>
<p>Traditionally, many of our user groups have focused on urban areas. Still, given Nebraska’s vast land area, creating a welcoming environment for those outside the major cities was important. Several hundred miles separate some of the smaller towns, and we want to ensure everyone feels included.</p>
<p>Our goal is to make as many of our meetings hybrid as possible. This way, we can include individuals in western Nebraska and other towns beyond Lincoln and Omaha. We want them to feel connected and engaged. Our first kickoff meeting was in person, but after that, we have implemented the hybrid model so that participants from all around Nebraska can join our discussions as well. It’s important to us to involve those outside the main urban centres.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-nebraska" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-nebraska">Can you share what the R community is like in Nebraska?</h2>
<p>Although I have little experience with industry connections, I want to involve more industry professionals in our group. I have sent out an email summarising our discussions. I encouraged industry professionals to reach out, as one of our kickoff meeting discussions focused on the topics people want to hear about in future talks.</p>
<p>All attendees at the kickoff meeting were from academia or involved in nonprofit or government roles, such as parks and recreation or public media. However, no one from a corporate background was present. A graduate student expressed a strong interest in moving from academia to industry and asked how a graduate student with academic skills can transition into an industry job.</p>
<p>I highlighted this topic in my email, emphasizing the desire for industry partners to participate and share their insights. The academic participants are significantly interested in how to transition to industry positions, an area I feel more comfortable discussing.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGCollinBerke.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: <a href="https://www.collinberke.com/">Collin Berke</a></p>
</section>
<section id="please-provide-details-about-the-kick-off-meeting-for-your-group.-what-topics-were-discussed-and-how-did-participants-respond" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-provide-details-about-the-kick-off-meeting-for-your-group.-what-topics-were-discussed-and-how-did-participants-respond">Please provide details about the kick-off meeting for your group. What topics were discussed, and how did participants respond?</h2>
<p>The kickoff meeting was fantastic. As I mentioned last year, the original group consisted of about five or six people from the university. Typically, only four of us met each month, which was relatively small. However, we had 20 people in attendance for the kickoff meeting, which was great! It was mostly folks from Lincoln; unfortunately, no one from Omaha could make it since the meeting was in person.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGRachelRogers.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rachelesrogers/">Rachel Rogers</a></p>
<p>I was excited about the turnout, mainly because most attendees were academics I already knew. Still, I also met a few new people from the university. Additionally, we had representatives from <a href="https://nebraskapublicmedia.org/en/watch/live/?gad_source=1&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiAqL28BhCrARIsACYJvkc0RJUmqAJrWTGT1J6o9P0anRam3rJyxk4FKHEJHotsnaxDMe_AClUaApW9EALw_wcB">Nebraska Public Media</a> and <a href="https://members.grownebraska.org/list/member/nebraska-game-and-parks-164?utm_source=google&amp;gad_source=1&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiAqL28BhCrARIsACYJvkdMY_i--W_KWOLTzLpze8Izpcet2qEWRrFwRpTk0UPC00QdMMI9Nd4aAkCIEALw_wcB">Nebraska Game and Parks</a>, which was exciting because it included some nonprofit and governmental groups.</p>
<p>We did not have a specific topic to discuss, as the main goal was to spend most of the time networking. I wanted everyone to talk, make connections, and meet new people.</p>
<p>My main goal for the kickoff meeting was facilitating communication among the attendees. We dedicated a significant portion of time to this at the beginning and end of the meeting to ensure everyone had ample opportunity to chat. I also made introductory announcements and introduced myself, outlining what we hoped to achieve with the group.</p>
<p>We included a couple of lightning talks in the agenda. These were short, five-minute presentations showcasing the various projects participants had been working on. The aim was to help everyone build connections and gain insight into their peers’ work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGParticipants.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: Participants</p>
<p>One graduate student discussed a package they developed based on their research, while a faculty member presented an R course they created along with its accompanying website. A representative from Nebraska Public Media shared how they utilize R in their daily operations. Lastly, I provided a brief overview of my flashcard package.</p>
<p>The goal was to provide a brief insight into what various people are doing from different perspectives. The event was very successful. The attendees enjoyed it; they were excited to learn about what others were doing and to get involved. Overall, I was pleased with how the kickoff meeting turned out.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-have-a-plan-for-this-year-what-is-the-frequency-of-the-events-you-plan-to-host-and-what-topics-will-you-cover" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-have-a-plan-for-this-year-what-is-the-frequency-of-the-events-you-plan-to-host-and-what-topics-will-you-cover">Do you have a plan for this year? What is the frequency of the events you plan to host, and what topics will you cover?</h2>
<p>I’m still working on that piece. I plan to hold these events roughly once a month during the academic year. So, starting in February, I envision having sessions in February, March, April, and May. Over the summer, we could get creative and consider doing something different instead of just talking. An in-person event could be a good option.</p>
<p>As mentioned, I want to involve some industry professionals. They would like to discuss the role of R in the industry and explore how people learning R can leverage their skills to seek job opportunities.</p>
<p>I recently attended our second meeting, which was our initial discussion. I asked the group if they wanted to share topics, ideas, or presentations. One suggestion was to have a “beginner’s night” for those with little exposure to the subject. This would help newcomers by introducing them to the basics.</p>
<p>User groups often contain members with varying experience levels, and it is essential to have a sense of how to cater to everyone. Our last meeting featured an advanced talk on extensions to <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot2</a>, specifically building geoms, which is quite complex. We want to ensure that we also engage those new to R. It’s essential that they feel included, have the opportunity to ask questions, and learn something valuable by attending the group.</p>
<p>I don’t have a fully developed plan yet, but I have two initial ideas I’m still working on. I aim to be as inclusive as possible, engaging participants from various experience levels and backgrounds—from the industry, academia, government, or non-profits. I want to involve everyone and see what we can achieve together.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-primarily-related-to-your-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-primarily-related-to-your-industry">Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting, primarily related to your industry?</h2>
<p>My work involves running the Canine Cognition and Human Interaction Lab with two main focuses. One focus is studying dog cognition. We invite pet dog owners to bring their dogs to our lab on campus, where we play games involving treats. We hide food in specific locations or provide choices, measuring the dogs’ decisions. These activities aim to understand how dogs think and process information.</p>
<p>One project I’m particularly excited about is called the <a href="https://manydogsproject.github.io/">Many Dogs Project</a>. This initiative is a consortium of dog labs from around the world. Several labs participate in a collaborative study, each conducting the same experiment in their respective locations. Ultimately, we aggregate all the data, allowing us to analyze a large sample size. For our first study, 20 labs tested 700 dogs, which provided us with a remarkable dataset for our behavioral research. I’m looking forward to the insights we can gain from these projects!</p>
<p>It’s a fantastic project because it brings together a diverse group. It’s collaborative and collegial, strongly emphasising open source and open science. We use R for our analyses; everything we do is made public, allowing everyone access to the data and scripts. I’m excited to be a part of this project. In fact, after my initial involvement, I ran to become the co-director of the Many Dogs Project, which I am now. I truly enjoy contributing to such initiatives.</p>
<p>I recently had the chance to work with Shiny for the first time. I developed my first <a href="https://manydogs.shinyapps.io/ManyDogs1/">Shiny app</a>, which allows users to explore some of the data collected from the Many Dogs Project. We gathered substantial information about the dogs, including their aggression, fearfulness, and training history. This app allows users to examine correlations, such as the relationship between a dog’s aggression and trainability.</p>
<p>I haven’t publicized the app yet because I want to get feedback from my colleagues in the Many Dogs Project before making it fully available. It’s been a fun experience. Initially, I hadn’t worked much with Shiny because it seemed different from R, and I was unsure if I could manage it. However, I attended a workshop on Shiny designed for data science mentors, and I decided to use it to build the Many Dogs Project app as my project for that workshop.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebraskaRUGlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="75" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New R User Group in Thailand is Building Awareness of R</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/logo_final-05.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/nwiroonsri/">Dr.&nbsp;Nathakhun Wiroonsri</a> is an academic at the Department of Mathematics, Faculty of Science, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi in Thailand. With a strong foundation in applied mathematics, Dr.&nbsp;Wiroonsri’s expertise lies in theoretical probability, machine learning, and statistical analysis. His research aims to bridge these areas to develop innovative methodologies for solving real-world problems, particularly in clustering and healthcare applications.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/nathakhun1.jpeg" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<p>Beyond his academic pursuits, Dr.&nbsp;Wiroonsri is deeply involved in promoting the use of R in Thailand. He founded <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rxthailand/">R x TH, Thailand’s R user group supported by the R Consortium</a>, to foster collaboration and build a vibrant community for R enthusiasts. His efforts include organizing workshops for beginners, experienced users, and professionals, aiming to make R more accessible and appealing across industries, especially among the younger generation.</p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-r-x-th." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-r-x-th.">Please share your background and involvement with R x TH.</h3>
<p>I’d like to share a bit about my personal background and my journey with R. I completed my PhD in applied mathematics at USC, focusing on theoretical probability. During that time, I didn’t use R extensively, but I was familiar with it and occasionally relied on it for simple simulations to validate my research results.</p>
<p>After graduating, I taught a statistical consulting course at USC, assisting my advisor, who used R in his teaching. That experience provided me with additional exposure to the language.</p>
<p>When I returned to Thailand, I was assigned to teach a statistics and data science program, which marked the beginning of my regular use of R. I also began conducting research in machine learning, where R became an integral tool in my work.</p>
<p>This year, I had the opportunity to attend the useR! conference in Salzburg, which was a fantastic experience.</p>
<p>Inspired by that event and recognizing a gap in Thailand, my students and I decided to establish R x TH, a user group for R enthusiasts in Thailand. At the time, there weren’t any Thai groups officially supported by the R Consortium, so we started this initiative to organize workshops for both beginners and experienced users. We also aim to foster research collaboration within the group.</p>
<p>To clarify, I’m based in Bangkok and work at the King Mongkut’s University of Technology under a government contract, which initially sent me to study in the U.S.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-bangkok-and-more-broadly-in-thailand" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-bangkok-and-more-broadly-in-thailand">Can you share what the R community is like in Bangkok and more broadly in Thailand?</h3>
<p>I’d say R isn’t very popular in Thailand, especially compared to Python, which dominates industry environments. However, there are some R users, particularly in sectors like insurance and also healthcare.</p>
<p>Before starting the R x TH user group, there were already a few R communities in Thailand, but they were mostly small and centered within universities. Many R users here work in academia, using it in traditional ways—primarily for teaching and data analysis in their fields.</p>
<p>A funny story: I recently met an old friend who graduated from UC San Diego and works in pure mathematics. He had never coded before and started learning Python to assist his new research. When I mentioned R, he thought it was some kind of instant software where you just input data, click a few times, and get results! I explained what R is, and he was intrigued, so I invited him to one of our workshops. Stories like this highlight how much awareness we still need to build around R.</p>
</section>
<section id="your-group-recently-held-its-very-first-event.-how-did-it-go-can-you-share-more-about-the-topics-covered" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-group-recently-held-its-very-first-event.-how-did-it-go-can-you-share-more-about-the-topics-covered">Your group recently held its very first event. How did it go? Can you share more about the topics covered?</h3>
<p>Our first event focused on providing a solid introduction to R. We covered foundational topics such as basic syntax, coding practices, and essential packages like ggplot2. The session was hands-on, starting with how to install R and the key packages, so participants could follow along easily.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/event-participants.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The event was a success, thanks in large part to my master’s students: Onthada and Noppanon, who played a key role in organizing and leading the workshop. It even sparked interest among younger students—several approached me afterward, eager to take my data science course next semester, even though it’s typically designed for junior students.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/speaker.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As for the course itself, I initiated it about four years ago as a special topic, and after receiving positive feedback, it became a core part of the program. For the workshop, we prepared tutorial materials that participants could follow step by step. Right now, those materials are only shared within the group, but we may consider making them public in the future.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/speaker2.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in">Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</h3>
<p>I’m currently wrapping up my grant, during which I published several papers related to cluster validity indices. My research focuses on cluster validation techniques, which are used to detect optimal clusters hidden in datasets. My team and I have also contributed to the R community by developing two R packages, <em><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/UniversalCVI/index.html">UniversalCVI</a></em> and <em><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/BayesCVI/index.html">BayesCVI</a></em>, both available on CRAN. These packages are specifically designed for those working with cluster analysis.</p>
<p>In addition, I’m collaborating with a medical doctor to develop a new methodology for classifying diabetes patients. Once this project is complete, we plan to create an R package based on our methodology. We also aim to organize a workshop for healthcare professionals who use R in their work.</p>
<p>Interestingly, R is still widely used in the healthcare sector in Thailand, particularly by doctors and researchers. However, I’ve noticed a shift among younger generations toward Python, but R remains prevalent in this field.</p>
<p>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</p>
<p>We had a great turnout at the event, but the level of interest varied among participants. Some attendees were genuinely enthusiastic, while others seemed to come along with friends or just to check things out. That was a bit of a challenge because we wanted everyone to feel engaged.</p>
<p>To address this, we reviewed the participant list and adjusted our approach. For those who seemed less familiar with the material, we made the content more beginner-friendly and interactive to capture their interest. We also added activities to make the event more fun and engaging, especially since many attendees were young and appreciated a lively atmosphere.</p>
<p>For example, we incorporated Q&amp;A sessions where participants could answer questions, and we gave out small prizes to encourage participation. This approach resulted in better engagement and made the event more enjoyable for everyone.</p>
</section>
<section id="which-isc-projects-have-you-used-if-none-which-ones-look-like-something-you-might-look-into-and-why" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-isc-projects-have-you-used-if-none-which-ones-look-like-something-you-might-look-into-and-why">Which <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/funded-projects.html">ISC project</a>(s) have you used? If none, which one(s) look like something you might look into (and why)?</h3>
<p>To be honest, I only recently realized that the R Consortium funds ISE projects after you sent me the question. I looked into them briefly, and they all seem quite interesting. One that caught my attention is <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/2023-group-1.html#autotest-automated-testing-of-r-packages">autotest</a>.</p>
<p>As someone with experience publishing R packages, I know how challenging it is to catch every error. Despite double- and triple-checking for issues, once a package is released and used by real users, unexpected errors often surface. A tool like <em>autotest</em>, which helps identify potential issues before publishing, would be incredibly helpful. Being able to ensure the package is as close to error-free as possible before release would make a big difference. I’m definitely planning to use <em>autotest</em> in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-trends-do-you-see-around-the-r-language" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-trends-do-you-see-around-the-r-language">What trends do you see around the R language?</h3>
<p>In Thailand, there’s a clear trend among the younger generation toward learning Python. Even students in our statistics and data science program express interest in Python. However, we still focus on using R in our curriculum. The challenge is that many R users in Thailand, particularly in academia, tend to use it in traditional ways—relying on existing packages for data analysis. This makes it harder to attract younger users to R.</p>
<p>When I attended the useR! conference this past year, I discovered many modern techniques and packages in R that could appeal to younger users, such as tools for creating content, slides, and publications—like Quarto. I tried Quarto myself recently and found it very promising. I believe introducing these modern tools through workshops could resonate with younger users and professionals in industry, showing them that R can be just as innovative and versatile as other tools.</p>
<p>Our user group is based at a university, so it naturally draws students. However, we’re also planning workshops tailored to professionals, starting with healthcare. Since we’re currently working on a project related to diabetes classification, we plan to hold a workshop for healthcare professionals once the project is complete. This will give us a chance to share our new methodology, demonstrate its applications in healthcare, and encourage attendees to explore R further. I think this approach will help us reach new audiences and grow interest in R.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/event-participants.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R en Buenos Aires: New Generations Working to Strengthen the Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community" class="level1">
<h1>R en Buenos Aires: New Generations Working to Strengthen the Community</h1>
<p><br> <br></p>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/andrea-gomez-vargas.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:5%;">

</div><div class="column" style="width:65%;">
<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed Andrea Gomez Vargas to find out about the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/en-AU/renbaires/">R in Buenos Aires</a> User Group. Andrea has a degree in sociology. Currently, she works as an analyst of population statistics at the National Institute of Statistics and Census - INDEC Argentina. She also teaches at universities in social science and data science.</p>
<p>Andrea has been an active member of the R community in Argentina and Latin America since 2018. She has been part of <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/">R-Ladies Buenos Aires</a> and is currently part of the R-Ladies global team and the LatinR organizing committee.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Andrea was part of the 2023-2024 cohort of the rOpenSci champions program, and in 2024 she decided to take over the leadership of R en Buenos Aires.</p>
<section id="why-did-you-decide-to-take-the-lead-of-the-chapter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-did-you-decide-to-take-the-lead-of-the-chapter">Why did you decide to take the lead of the chapter?</h3>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<p><br> I decided to take on the leadership of the chapter to actively contribute to the local impact of the R user community. Most of my knowledge has come from these communities - the trust and selfless support I’ve received has helped me grow as a professional and inspired me to take on projects I never thought I could. For this reason, I believe it is essential to reengage in activities to invite new generations to participate, explore new tools and opportunities, and collaborate in a space that welcomes all levels of experience and diverse professional backgrounds.</p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-motivates-you-to-continue-promoting-r-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-motivates-you-to-continue-promoting-r-learning">What motivates you to continue promoting R learning?</h3>
<p>Communities are essential spaces for breaking down barriers to access information and knowledge, especially when it comes to free and open-source software. When these resources are paid or only reach a small percentage of people, it creates inequities. As a public university teacher, I am driven by the belief that everyone, regardless of background, should have the opportunity to learn and grow in a collaborative, open environment. That’s what keeps me motivated to continue spreading R knowledge and ensuring it remains accessible for all.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants from the December 20th, 2024, meetup</em></p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-your-main-objectives-for-the-r-chapter-in-buenos-aires-and-what-challenges-do-you-anticipate-in-achieving-them" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-your-main-objectives-for-the-r-chapter-in-buenos-aires-and-what-challenges-do-you-anticipate-in-achieving-them">What are your main objectives for the R chapter in Buenos Aires, and what challenges do you anticipate in achieving them?</h3>
<p>The main objectives at this moment for the R chapter in Buenos Aires are to have more events to disseminate relevant topics in the community, such as the use of Quarto, Shiny, R packages, Git, and GitHub. A key challenge is ensuring that volunteer work doesn’t overwhelm us or lead to burnout, as organizing these events requires a lot of behind-the-scenes work. Currently, in addition to myself, Emanuel and Ariana are part of the local team coordinating activities—and although teamwork is essential, we must find a balance between collective effort and the well-being of the chapter members.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in">Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</h3>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<p><br> <br> I’m working on the development of the <code>arcenso</code> package, a package with census data from Argentina, now in its first version on Github, but we are looking to reach CRAN.</p>
<p><code>arcenso</code> is a project supported by the rOpenSci Champions Program cohort 2023-2024, with me as lead developer, Emanuel Ciardullo as co-developer and Luis D. Verde as mentor. It is a very important project because it makes census data accessible and homogenized in a way that any user can work with it in R.</p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><br> <br> <img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/arcenso.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Details from the arcenso page:</p>
<p>arcenso is a package under development that will allow access to the official data of the national population censuses in Argentina from the National Institute of Statistics and Census - INDEC. Currently, the results of the historical censuses of 1970, 1980, 1991, 2001, 2010 and 2022 are available in different formats through physical books, PDFs, Excel files or in REDATAM, without having a unified system or format that allows working with the data of these six census periods as a database. In addition, the presentation of the data is not homogeneous between the periods, making it difficult to make historical or serial comparisons of the available information.</p>
<p>This package aims to make census data available, homogenized and ready to use. It will include the census data from 1970 to 2022. Having a package of census information will allow the public and private sectors, citizens and other actors in society to access current and historical information on Argentina’s population, households and housing in a more accessible way.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For more information, see <a href="https://soyandrea.github.io/arcenso/">soyandrea.github.io/arcenso</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="what-r-resourcestechniques-dodid-you-use-posit-rstudio-github-tidyverse-etc." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-r-resourcestechniques-dodid-you-use-posit-rstudio-github-tidyverse-etc.">What R resources/techniques do/did you use? (Posit (RStudio), Github, Tidyverse, etc.)</h3>
<p>I use R on a daily basis to teach, work and collaborate in the community. Part of my work requires processing and combining various data sources (censuses, surveys and administrative records) to produce socio-demographic indicators for the country. I also design and develop digital statistical products, such as a Shiny app or dashboards. For all this I rely on several R packages for ETL and visualisation <em>(gt, tidyverse, expss, plotly, quarto, and many more).</em> And this is what I try to teach my students or the people who attend the workshops.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Photo of Betsy, Ariana, and Andrea, organizers of the October 29, 2024, meetup, from left to right</em></p>
</section>
<section id="you-had-a-meetup-on-october-29th-2024.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-had-a-meetup-on-october-29th-2024.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered">You had a Meetup on October 29th, 2024. Can you share more about the topic covered?</h3>
<p><em>[Editor’s note: There were two more events held by R en Buenos Aires at the end of 2024. Please see the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/en-AU/renbaires/events/?type=past">meetup page</a> for more information (in Spanish).]</em></p>
<p>The topic of the workshop was socio-demographic analysis in R using data from the Argentine Labour Force Survey. We learned about the R packages needed to calculate the indicators and how to present the results in graphs and tables.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The workshop was aimed at university students who are taking their first steps in R and who would like to do real-life practice guided by people from the community with experience in the field.</p>
<p>After the workshop a specific website <a href="https://r-unlam.netlify.app/">r-unlam.netlify.app</a> was created. We believe it is a good practice for people who cannot attend physically to have access to all the materials and to have the activities documented.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants from the October 29th, 2024, meetup</em></p>
</section>
<section id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following">You can reach out to R in Buenos Aires through the following:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Linkedin: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires/" class="uri">https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires/</a></li>
<li>Github: <a href="https://github.com/renbaires" class="uri">https://github.com/renbaires</a></li>
<li>X: <a href="https://x.com/renbaires">https://x.com/renbaires</a><br>
</li>
<li>Instagram: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires">https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h3>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html" class="uri">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Transforming Academic Research with R in Santa Rosa, Argentina</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marina-cock-49b1b5171/">Marina Cock</a>, co-organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-santa-rosa/">R-Ladies Santa Rosa</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the growth of the R community in La Pampa and the transformative role of R in local academic research. Marina shared insights into the community’s activities, including introducing students to R, organizing meetups, and encouraging advanced statistical techniques like generalized linear mixed models. She also highlighted the challenges of promoting R in her university setting and her efforts to foster a supportive environment for learning and collaboration.</p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h3>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/MarinaCock.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Marina Cock at first R ladies meet up in Santa Rosa, La Pampa</em></p>
<p>I am a natural resources engineer from the National University of La Pampa. I completed my PhD in plant ecology at the University of Buenos Aires. Currently, I work as both a teaching assistant and a research assistant at the National University of La Pampa.</p>
<p>I first engaged with the R community about seven years ago, roughly one year after I began using R. During that time, I was learning R. I shared my experiences and questions with <a href="https://yabellini.netlify.app/">Yanina Bellini</a>, founder of R-ladies Santa Rosa and a significant R-ladies member. [<em>Editor’s note: Bellini is also <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/governance.html">a member of the R Consortium Infrastructure Steering Committee</a>.</em>] She was also just starting and suggested that we join a global network to help each other, share our doubts, and expand our knowledge and ideas in La Pampa, specifically in our city, Santa Rosa. During that conversation, she invited me to organize the first meetup here.</p>
<p>We began our journey with R Ladies in Santa Rosa, La Pampa. Our first event occurred at a college, where we started engaging with students. We explained what R is, how we use it, and how they could apply it professionally. Yanina discussed data mining while I shared how I utilize R for generalized linear mixed models.</p>
<p>That meeting marked the beginning of our activities in Santa Rosa. Following this, Yanina invited me to join the committee for the <a href="https://latinr.org">Latin R Conference</a>. This key conference in Latin America showcased various uses and applications of R and was an opportunity to broaden my understanding of R.</p>
<p>Since then, I have shared knowledge and learned much about R from these communities. My journey with R started with a free online course, and after learning the basics, I began asking questions and learning from the global community.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/YaninaBellini.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Yanina Bellini at the Latin R conference</em></p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-la-pampa" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-la-pampa">Can you share what the R community is like in La Pampa?</h3>
<p>I can speak from my experience in academia, as this is where I primarily use R. I’ve noticed that R has become increasingly popular over the years. For instance, we didn’t use any software when I was studying for my degree. Now, I am a teaching assistant for statistics, and we teach R and its applications for research to our students.</p>
<p>While pursuing my PhD, only some people were using R, making me question my decision regarding data analysis. After I collected my data, I considered whether to analyze it using traditional software. At that time, it felt daunting because, in my location, there were few users of R. However, I decided to dedicate a summer to learning the R language. I applied what I learned to analyze my data, and it was a great experience. It opened up numerous possibilities for analysis and helped me develop valuable skills in data wrangling, such as organizing and cleaning the data.</p>
<p>Although I’m not an expert—just someone who has learned the basics—I found many helpful resources that have significantly enhanced my statistical skills.</p>
<p>That’s why I believe Yanina and I should spread the word about R. In my case, I tell the students that using R isn’t something to be afraid of. Many people think it’s impossible to learn, but that’s not true. Once you start using it, you’ll see that it’s manageable. There’s plenty of help available online and at the university, making it an excellent tool for our work. However, I still think we have much to do to alleviate the fear surrounding R. Many university students are still intimidated by it, and we should continue supporting each other in learning it.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry">Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting related to your industry?</h3>
<p>R became essential for me after I completed my PhD, mainly for data wrangling. During the last year of my PhD, I received a scholarship to spend three months in the US. Because it was a short-term stay, I could not take my research samples. Instead, I proposed carrying out a data analysis project. At that point, I needed to improve my data analysis skills, and my experience with R was limited. While in the US, I worked on a research question related to plant ecology, focusing mainly on plant-plant interactions, particularly positive plant facilitation. We were investigating whether plants that grow in association with others show different traits or strategies than those that grow in isolation.</p>
<p>There is already a significant amount of knowledge regarding how facilitation and positive interactions vary in stressful environments. However, we aimed to understand more about the types of plants that depend on being close to other plants for survival and reproduction.</p>
<p>I was provided with two large databases for my analysis. One database contained information on plants in alpine systems, including the richness and biodiversity of plants living close to each other versus those more isolated. Another included a big worldwide database about plant traits. Initially, I struggled to interpret the databases and sought help downloading their data. Once I obtained it, I began the process of data wrangling and tidying it up using the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/">tidyverse</a> and reshaping packages in R.</p>
<p>During the final phase of my PhD, I dedicated time to learning the basics of R, which enabled me to organize the data effectively. Ultimately, our analysis revealed no significant differences in traits between isolated plants and those associated with others. Nonetheless, this project underscored the importance of using R in my research.</p>
<p>I’m unsure how to analyze large databases with other software. The main project I worked on involved R, and after that, I continued my postdoctoral studies, still investigating some of that data. I primarily use generalized linear mixed models.</p>
<p>We often deal with hierarchical experimental designs in ecology, particularly plant ecology. For example, plants within fields are then within regions. It’s essential to account for this lack of independence in our data. Generalized linear mixed models have proven extremely helpful for ecologists. Our techniques and packages now enable us to perform analyses that we previously couldn’t even consider.</p>
<p>These models are fundamental tools for plant ecologists. Other types of ecologists, like those studying animals, may also use them, but they are particularly crucial for our study designs.</p>
<p>I gathered my courage and started creating some maps. Initially, I hesitated to make graphs because achieving them would require many scripts and specifications. However, I soon realized that graphs and maps are handy. I couldn’t believe the maps I could create in R! Now, as a research assistant, I might be asked to make maps or handle a lot of data wrangling for various research projects that have accumulated over time.</p>
<p>I organize all the data needed to perform analyses, and I often tell people here that I strive to incorporate more R into our statistics courses. We encourage students to integrate more R into learning and embrace modern tools and techniques. Other universities might use R more extensively than we do, but we have been growing in our use of R over the past few years.</p>
<p>If you have any questions, ideas, or suggestions, my email is <a href="marinacock@gmail.com">marinacock@gmail.com</a>.</p>
<p>You can also contact <a href="mailto:yabellini@gmail.com">Yanina Bellini Saibene</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/MarinaCock.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Clinical Reporting Collaborative Triumph: Roche’s NEST and Admiral Teams</title>
  <dc:creator>Joe Zhu, Leena Khatri, Emily de la Rua, Edoardo Mancini, Kangjie Zhang, Daphne Grasselly</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Guest Post contributed by Joe Zhu, Leena Khatri, Emily de la Rua, Edoardo Mancini, Kangjie Zhang, Daphne Grasselly</em></p>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In the dynamic world of clinical research, innovation and collaboration are key drivers of success. The NEST and admiral teams exemplify this through their groundbreaking partnership. By leveraging open-source tools and fostering a community-driven approach, they have significantly advanced data integration and reporting methodologies in the clinical research setting. This story celebrates their journey and achievements.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/nest-admiral.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="the-nest-team" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-nest-team">The NEST Team</h2>
<p>The NEST team, an acronym for <a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/nest/">Next-Generation Exploratory and Standardized Tools</a>, has pioneered a collection of open-sourced R packages designed to expedite insight generation under clinical research settings. Originating at Roche, NEST has attracted a diverse array of collaborators from academia, the pharmaceutical industry, and clinical research institutes, largely due to efforts like <a href="https://pharmaverse.org/">pharmaverse</a>. Their mission is to accelerate clinical reporting and welcome contributions from the broader scientific community.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-admiral-team" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-admiral-team">The Admiral Team</h2>
<p>Focused on a complementary goal, the admiral team is dedicated to providing an <a href="https://pharmaverse.github.io/admiral/">open-source, modularized toolbox for creating ADaM datasets in R</a>. Their approach is transparent and collaborative, empowering users to co-create and refine a harmonized methodology for ADaM development across the pharmaceutical industry. The admiral team designs their tools to be user-friendly and versatile, capable of addressing a wide range of data requirements.</p>
</section>
<section id="setting-the-stage-for-collaboration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="setting-the-stage-for-collaboration">Setting the Stage for Collaboration</h2>
<p>Recognizing the potential for synergies, the NEST and Admiral teams embarked on a collaborative journey to enhance their respective toolsets.</p>
<p>Their shared objectives included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Developing a robust toolbox of reusable functions and utilities for ADaM dataset creation and Tables/Listings/Graphs creation.</li>
<li>Ensuring comprehensive documentation and testing of these functions.</li>
<li>Creating detailed vignettes to guide users in generating and manipulating various datasets, and for subsequent tabulation.</li>
<li>Encouraging contributions from the pharmaceutical community to foster a unified and robust development environment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="overcoming-initial-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overcoming-initial-challenges">Overcoming Initial Challenges</h2>
<p>Initially, the NEST team relied on simulated data for integration testing, which often lacked realism and failed to cover corner cases or expose software limitations. The opportunity arose to address these challenges by switching to using the more realistic test data offered by the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pharmaverseadam/index.html">{pharmaverseadam} package</a>, whose original source is real SDTM data published through the CDISC Test Data pilot. This pivot allowed the NEST team to achieve more realistic and comprehensive testing, thus enhancing the robustness of their development work, and the {pharmaverseadam}/{admiral} team to improve the quality of their templates and test data through the constructive feedback that was received during the implementation phase.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-milestones-achieved" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-milestones-achieved">Key Milestones Achieved:</h2>
<p><strong>Realistic Data Integration:</strong> Transitioning from simulated to more realistic data provided the NEST team with more accurate and relevant testing conditions. This change was crucial in identifying and rectifying potential software limitations.</p>
<p><strong>Scope and Dependency Management:</strong> Both teams agreed to avoid creating strong interdependencies that could extend release cycles. NEST packages maintained minimal data for documentation purposes, while admiral preserved extensive datasets separately.</p>
<p><strong>CI Integration and Automation:</strong> New CI integration tests ensured that template updates were automatically verified against stored pharmaverseadam datasets. This maintained consistency and allowed users to identify intended changes promptly.</p>
<p><strong>Strategic Pipelines:</strong> An automated pipeline was established to update pharmaverseadam ADaMs for each new release, reflecting any template changes Accurately.</p>
</section>
<section id="recent-developments" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-developments">Recent Developments</h2>
<p>The collaboration bore fruit as the teams uncovered critical insights and improvements:</p>
<p>Using pharmaverseadam data in the scda.test package helped the NEST team identify and correct issues in their table template development, specifically in calculating denominator values.</p>
<p>The realistic test data also revealed minor inconsistencies in the derivation of ECG data within the admiral framework, which were promptly addressed, enhancing data accuracy.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The collaboration between the NEST and admiral teams showcases the power of open-source initiatives and community-driven efforts such as the pharmaverse in advancing clinical research. By integrating realistic data and refining their testing processes, they have significantly enhanced the robustness and reliability of their tools. This partnership not only accelerates insight generation but also cultivates a culture of collaboration and innovation, benefiting the broader pharmaverse community.</p>
<p>The success of this collaboration highlights the profound impact of shared goals and collective innovation, paving the way for future advancements in clinical research methodologies and outcomes.</p>
<section id="acknowledgement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h3>
<p>We would like to thank Ben Straub, Jeff Dickinson, Stefan Bundfuss, Ross Farrugia, Zelos Zhu’s valuable contributions to this collaborative work.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/nest-admiral.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>User-Friendly Technical Cookbook-Style CRAN Guide for New R Programmers Ready</title>
  <dc:creator>Jasmine Daly, Beni Altmann</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/user-friendly-technical-cookbook-style-cran-guide-for-new-r-programmers-ready/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Guest blog post contributed by Jasmine Daly, Principal Consultant &amp; Founder of <a href="https://www.dalyanalytics.com/">Daly Analytics</a>, maintainer of 2 CRAN packages, and Beni Altmann, Student, assistant member of the CRAN Team working on CRAN submissions</em></p>
<section id="making-the-cran-submission-process-easy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-the-cran-submission-process-easy">Making the CRAN Submission Process Easy</h2>
<p>As we close out the first phase of the project - Improving the Skills of R Package Maintainers, also known as <a href="https://contributor.r-project.org/cran-cookbook/">The CRAN Cookbook</a> - we’re reflecting on its journey and impact. This initiative began with an ambitious but focused goal: to create a user-friendly, technical cookbook-style guide to help new R programmers and package maintainers navigate the CRAN submission process. The ultimate vision was to streamline this process, reduce common frustrations, and elevate the quality of open-source contributions to the R ecosystem.</p>
<p>The CRAN Cookbook aimed to provide clear, explainable solutions for frequent errors while supporting maintainers in producing high-quality software.</p>
<p>We’ve come a long way in a short time. We’re excited to share what we’ve accomplished!</p>
<p>If you want to help contribute, please see: <a href="https://github.com/r-devel/cran-cookbook/wiki/Contributors-Guide">https://github.com/r-devel/cran-cookbook/wiki/Contributors-Guide</a></p>
</section>
<section id="overview-of-what-we-have-currently-published" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview-of-what-we-have-currently-published">Overview of what we have currently published</h2>
<p>After nearly 6 months of collaboration, we’ve published a comprehensive cookbook addressing the most common issues encountered during the CRAN submissions. Our work benefited greatly from Beni Altmann’s deep experience as a member of the CRAN team, where he has spent a lot of time interfacing with maintainers.</p>
<p>The CRAN Cookbook includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>General Issues</strong>: Best practices and tips guidance for CRAN submissions.</li>
<li><strong>Manuals &amp; Documentation Issues</strong>: Tips on creating clear, accurate, and compliant help documentation files, using roxygen2, and creating examples, vignettes, and tests..</li>
<li><strong>Code Issues</strong>: Addressing common challenges in writing functions, managing file and directory operations, and handling installation and compute resources.</li>
<li><strong>DESCRIPTION File Issues</strong>: Essential guidance for crafting a compliant and informative DESCRIPTION file.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-its-getting-used-by-the-cran-team" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-its-getting-used-by-the-cran-team">How it’s getting used by the CRAN Team</h2>
<p>The CRAN team has already integrated the cookbook into their workflows. When encountering these common issues during package reviews, they refer maintainers to specific sections of the cookbook in their email correspondence. This approach not only expedites resolution but also empowers maintainers to tackle future challenges independently. It’s been gratifying to see the cookbook become a practical tool for fostering a more efficient submission process.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-we-learned-or-impressions-of-working-on-this-project" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-learned-or-impressions-of-working-on-this-project">What we learned or impressions of working on this project</h2>
<p>Jasmine: “I’m grateful for the opportunity to contribute a valuable resource to the R community in the form of new, user-friendly technical documentation. I deeply valued the experience of collaborating with my co-writer, Beni and working together to hopefully improve the CRAN submission process.”</p>
<p>Beni: “We, the CRAN team, see the same kind of issues for most packages. The cookbook style resource fitted perfectly for this project. It allowed for a jigsaw-like approach, writing piece after piece and setting it all together in the end. I think we created a great resource for future CRAN package maintainers.”</p>
</section>
<section id="plausible-analytics-and-measuring-success-of-the-cran-cookbook" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plausible-analytics-and-measuring-success-of-the-cran-cookbook">Plausible analytics and measuring success of the CRAN Cookbook</h2>
<p>We’ve implemented <a href="https://plausible.io/contributor.r-project.org%2Fcran-cookbook/">Plausible Analytics</a> to track engagement with the cookbook. By monitoring usage and feedback, we’ll continue refining the resource to better serve the R community.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/user-friendly-technical-cookbook-style-cran-guide-for-new-r-programmers-ready/analytics.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="thank-yous" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thank-yous">Thank yous</h2>
<p>To everyone who supported this project, thank you for helping us bring this vision to life. Whether you’re a new maintainer, a seasoned contributor, or part of the CRAN team, we hope the CRAN Cookbook proves to be an indispensable resource. Here’s to smoother submissions and stronger software in the R ecosystem!</p>
<p>A heartfelt thank you to our community contributors, the steering committee, and the R Repositories Working Group. Your insights and feedback have been invaluable in shaping the CRAN Cookbook. This project would not have been possible without your support and collaboration!</p>
</section>
<section id="community-contributions-process" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="community-contributions-process">Community contributions process</h2>
<p>We can use your help! We also developed a <a href="https://github.com/r-devel/cran-cookbook/wiki/Contributors-Guide">contributors guide</a> to encourage community members to expand and improve the cookbook with their insights and experiences for often seen submission errors.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/user-friendly-technical-cookbook-style-cran-guide-for-new-r-programmers-ready/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/user-friendly-technical-cookbook-style-cran-guide-for-new-r-programmers-ready/analytics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="66" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing R to Malawi: A Community in the Making</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-r-to-malawi-a-community-in-the-making/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>David Mwale, the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-users-malawi/">R Users Malawi</a> group organizer, recently spoke with the R Consortium about his efforts to establish and grow the R community in Malawi. David shared insights into the group’s inaugural meeting, the excitement surrounding R among researchers and students, and his plans to engage academic institutions through online and in-person events. He also discussed the challenges of introducing R in a region where other tools like Stata and SPSS dominate and his vision for fostering a vibrant and supportive R ecosystem in Malawi.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-r-to-malawi-a-community-in-the-making/DavidMwale.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I hold a bachelor’s degree in agricultural economics and a diploma in monitoring and evaluation. I have experience working with various data software, including Stata and SPSS. Last year (2023), I enrolled in a master’s program in data science at the <a href="https://www.ed.ac.uk/">University of Edinburgh</a>, where I was introduced to the R programming language. I’ve used R a few times at work for school assessments and participated in several training sessions on LinkedIn Learning.</p>
<p>Recently, I discovered user groups for R in neighboring countries, such as <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/collaborative-growth-the-botswana-r-user-group-and-regional-partnerships/index.html">Botswana</a>. I contacted the R user group in <a href="https://www.meetup.com/joburg-r-users-group/">Johannesburg</a> and learned about another community group on LinkedIn. I inquired about how they established their groups so we could create our own R user group. Following the steps they provided and the information I found on the R Consortium website, I applied to set up our group. I’m happy to report that we had our first meeting just last month.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Malawi?</strong></p>
<p>The use of R in Malawi is still in its infancy and is not widely adopted. For instance, at one academic institution, master’s students are still being taught Stata and SPSS. While these tools are not wrong, R is a programming language growing in popularity. It has a large community and significant support.</p>
<p>One issue may be that academic institution lecturers themselves still need to become familiar with R. They tend to teach what they already know, which might limit students’ exposure to more modern tools. A colleague of mine, pursuing his studies at an institution in Malawi, mentioned that they still use Stata for their master’s dissertation. Again, while this is acceptable, R offers more advantages.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-r-to-malawi-a-community-in-the-making/RUsersMalawi.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><strong>How was the response to your first event? How did you promote the event?</strong></p>
<p>I created a <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-users-malawi/posts/?feedView=all">LinkedIn</a> account and designed a poster for the event. I posted the poster on LinkedIn, X (formerly Twitter), and my WhatsApp status. Many people registered for the event; however, since this was our first event, I needed to figure out how to manage the registration link. We encountered an issue with the registration link for which platform to use.</p>
<p>I switched from Zoom to Google Meet because Zoom has associated costs. Although many people registered for the meeting, the turnout was significantly lower than expected. There might have been confusion regarding the links I shared. We used one link on the advertising poster, but I sent a different link closer to the meeting time through the R user group. Some people did not notice the latest email I sent.</p>
<p><strong>What are your plans for the group going forward? Do you plan on hosting online or in-person events?</strong></p>
<p>I have two plans. I intend to continue hosting meetings online and in person, particularly at universities, where I can engage with fellow students.</p>
<p>In summary, I aim to organize a meeting around January or February in 2025. I would like to connect with either a student leader or a department head, such as a lecturer interested in data science so that we can hold an R user session for the students on their campus.</p>
<p>Regarding the group’s organization, I am currently looking for co-organizers. I reached out to one person, but they are too busy. I also contacted another individual currently in Germany but originally from Malawi, and he is interested in participating as an organizer.</p>
<p>When I advertised the R User Group, there was a positive response because R is not widely used here in Malawi. Despite its limited usage, there was significant excitement among people working in research, data monitoring, evaluation, and academic students. Although the turnout at our first meeting was lower than expected, the enthusiasm will grow as we continue. Many people are eager to learn how to use R.</p>
<p>Since this is just the beginning, it can be challenging to get started and engage people, but over time, we will likely attract more members and find co-organizers to assist with event planning. We are optimistic about promoting the use of R in Malawi.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-r-to-malawi-a-community-in-the-making/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/introducing-r-to-malawi-a-community-in-the-making/RUsersMalawi-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="109" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Navigating Economic Challenges Through Community: The Journey of R-Ladies Buenos Aires</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/betsabe1984/">Betsabe Cohen</a>, organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-buenos-aires/">R-Ladies Buenos Aires</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the growth and diversity of the R community in Argentina and its role in navigating the country’s economic challenges. Betsy shared insights into the group’s activities, including hosting workshops on tools like Quarto and plans to launch a Shiny-focused reading club. She also highlighted the importance of fostering inclusion and collaboration within the community locally and across Latin America.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/BetsabeCohen.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My background is in sociology. I’m originally from Buenos Aires and have worked in the field for about 15 years. I became involved with the R community through some colleagues and a bit by chance. I discovered R when a friend, who was starting to use it, introduced me to it. She was already connected with the R community, specifically R-Ladies. A few years later, I became an organizer for the group.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Buenos Aires?</strong></p>
<p>R is primarily used in academia but is also prevalent in industry. The R community is very diverse, consisting of people from various backgrounds. We have industry professionals, researchers, and individuals from the government and non-profit sectors. I started using R in a non-profit environment. Our community includes a wide range of skill levels, from beginners to intermediate and advanced users, which adds to its diversity.</p>
<p>Data analysis has become a valuable skill in the job market. Argentina is experiencing a job crisis, making it crucial for people to access information. However, because much of this information is often in English, we aim to generate materials in Spanish and share them with our community, as linguistic barriers can be restrictive.</p>
<p>Communities like our group here in Buenos Aires are essential for people to access this information. However, it can be challenging for us as organizers, especially since we also navigate this crisis ourselves. Many of us juggle multiple jobs, making it challenging to find the time to teach and share information with others.</p>
<p>Balancing these responsibilities can feel like double work, and that’s what we’re currently facing.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/R-LadiesBuenosAiresGroupPhoto1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>You had a Meetup on “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-buenos-aires/events/304386918/?eventOrigin=group_past_events">Turn your data into visual stories with Quarto</a>.” Can you share more about the topic covered? Why this topic?</strong></p>
<p>We chose a topic beneficial for people searching for jobs related to data communication, visualization, and scientific reporting. <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> is an excellent tool for this purpose. The R community and the RUGS have embraced tools that enhance communication, making it more manageable within the scientific community and the business environment. Quarto allows individuals to continue using R while also adapting to various workplaces.</p>
<p>By sharing Quarto with others and demonstrating its capabilities, we aim to help people communicate effectively. Since R is primarily taught in universities but needs a proper communication tool, this was a significant factor in our decision to support and assist others.</p>
<p>Additionally, I have some exciting news: we are planning to start a reading club focused on mastering <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/">Shiny</a> for next year.</p>
<p>We are still preparing it. Shiny is widely used to make data accessible to users, which is part of our decision-making to support people during this challenging time. Reading this book alone is not the same as sharing the experience with others. There is significant value in sharing information and being part of a network, as it fosters community and support among us.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/R-LadiesBuenosAiresGroupPhoto2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Do you host your events in person or online? What kind of response do you get for each type of event?</strong></p>
<p>We host both in-person and online events. Sometimes, we can hold events in both formats, but other times, we can only offer them online because the conditions are not ideal for a physical gathering. We record the live events and upload them to our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RLadiesBuenosAires">YouTube</a> channel.</p>
<p>For example, we organized a large event last year that attracted 80 university students. The venue was so full that no one else could enter, and the event generated significant engagement and views on YouTube afterwards.</p>
<p>Some subjects are particularly appealing. Our goal is to reach as many people as possible, but I think a key point here is that inclusion is tied not only to gender but also to the economic dimensions of the issue.</p>
<p>The demand for the recordings we upload to YouTube and access to our meetings is influenced by the employment and economic crises we face. This challenge concerns the material aspects, such as accessing high-speed internet or owning a computer, and the time required to participate in these events. For instance, many people may work night shifts, making it difficult for them to attend events.</p>
<p>We typically schedule our meetings outside of working hours. The standard work schedule in Argentina runs from 9 AM to 6 PM, so we aim to hold our events around 7 PM to accommodate everyone. However, some individuals still need help to attend because they may have two jobs, leading them to plan to watch the YouTube recordings over the weekend.</p>
<p>This situation illustrates our understanding of inclusion; it is not solely about gender—thankfully, our country is making strides in that area—but also about addressing economic challenges.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>We encourage working in pairs when conducting activities in a live classroom, mainly because only some have a computer. It creates an excellent dynamic for us, especially when participants have different skill levels. In our recent sessions, most people had their computers, but that was only sometimes the case. We use Post-it notes to address problems on individual computers. When everything is running smoothly, we engage in live coding, and participants can simply post their notes when they encounter issues.</p>
<p>We organize our roles carefully to ensure efficiency. One of us may demonstrate the general code while live coding, while other organizers take on different responsibilities. Dividing the roles helps us focus on smaller tasks and work together effectively.</p>
<p>This approach applies not only in-person but also during our Zoom meetings. However, people seem less open to sharing their stories virtually. There’s something unique about face-to-face interactions compared to being online. After COVID-19, many people grew weary of Zoom meetings, but there were still benefits to being connected virtually. I participated in events I would never have had the chance to join otherwise.</p>
<p>There’s something unique about sharing space. I think the Post-it notes work well for us, along with consistently sharing information and being well-prepared for the day.</p>
<p>When someone is going to present live coding, they feel more comfortable knowing that they don’t have to worry about other tasks. We always make it a point to take care of everything by dividing responsibilities and staying organized beforehand.</p>
<p>We prepare everything we need for the day, from coffee and cookies to all the necessary materials. Someone is clearly assigned to each task, and I believe that’s the best approach. At least it works great for us!</p>
<p><strong>Can you share more about the journey of R-Ladies Buenos Aires?</strong></p>
<p>It has been a long journey for us in Buenos Aires. Buenos Aires was Argentina’s first chapter, and many other chapters of our Slack account opened up. We still share the same main Slack, R Ladies Buenos Aires, along with the other provinces that are very important to us.</p>
<p>I had the opportunity to travel to the country’s south to meet some of the organizers of <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/">R Ladies Bariloche</a>, where we have another chapter. I also participated in events like <a href="https://latinr.org/">LatinR</a>, bringing chapters across Latin America together. That experience was amazing!</p>
<p>I went to Uruguay last year, and it was fantastic to see so many R users from diverse backgrounds. It’s very exciting! The R User Groups are a great way to connect, and I always recommend them to others. People tend to respond very positively, and I am so proud to be part of this community.</p>
<p>You can reach out to R-Ladies Buenos Aires through the following:</p>
<p>Instagram:<a href="https://www.instagram.com/rladiesba/?hl=en">https://www.instagram.com/rladiesba/?hl=en</a></p>
<p>Facebook: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/RladiesBA/">https://www.facebook.com/RladiesBA/</a></p>
<p>Website: <a href="https://rladiesba.netlify.app/">https://rladiesba.netlify.app/</a></p>
<p>X: <a href="https://twitter.com/rladiesba?lang=en">https://twitter.com/rladiesba?lang=en</a></p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/navigating-economic-challenges-through-community-the-journey-of-r-ladies-buenos-aires/R-LadiesBuenosAiresGroupPhoto2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Books, Beginners, and Big Ideas: Beatriz Milz on Fostering R-Ladies São Paulo’s Vibrant Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://beamilz.com/about">Beatriz Milz</a>, a co-organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-sao-paulo/?eventOrigin=event_home_page">R-Ladies São Paulo</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the vibrant growth of the R community in São Paulo and its commitment to inclusivity and accessible learning. Beatriz shared insights into the group’s activities, from organizing popular in-person and online events to coordinating a book club focused on the newly translated R for Data Science in Portuguese. She also discussed the unique needs of R users in Brazil and how R-Ladies São Paulo supports beginners and advanced users through collaborative events and community-driven resources.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/BeatrizMilz.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My background includes a bachelor’s degree in environmental management, a master’s in environmental analysis, and a PhD in environmental sciences. During my master’s program, my supervisor mentioned that I needed to learn R to analyze the data we were collecting. However, no one in the lab was familiar with R or able to assist me. I attempted to learn it independently, but that didn’t work well.</p>
<p>Eventually, my supervisor connected me with another professor, and a postdoc in his lab helped me with the analysis for my master’s dissertation. While that assistance was beneficial, I felt uncomfortable relying on others to conduct the analysis. After finishing my master’s and before starting my doctorate, I decided that I wanted to learn how to program so I wouldn’t have to depend so heavily on fellow researchers for data analysis.</p>
<p>I started trying to learn R again after a friend mentioned the R-Ladies group. In 2018, I discovered that a new group was starting in São Paulo. I attended their first event, which was an incredible experience. Around that time, I began to learn R.</p>
<p>In São Paulo, we don’t just organize events; we also have a group on <a href="https://telegram.org/">Telegram</a> where we can communicate between events. It allowed me to ask for recommendations on learning materials, pose questions, and receive help from others in the group. This support was invaluable to my learning process.</p>
<p>Two months after getting involved, I began helping in the group. Initially, the group was relatively new, and one person mainly did most of the organizing tasks: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hsvab/?originalSubdomain=br">Haydee Svab</a>. She expressed a need for assistance, not just with R-related tasks but also with organizing events. So, I started to help, and I am still one of the co-organizers today, while Haydee remains the lead co-organizer.</p>
<p>It’s been six years since I began participating in the group, and I’m currently a postdoc involved in much work with R.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in São Paulo?</strong></p>
<p>Our group consists of researchers from various fields who want to learn R or have already used it. Many journalists started using R a few years ago and joined our group. Now, these journalists often invite other journalists. We have many journalists who need to learn R to analyze public data from the government for their journalistic work in newspapers.</p>
<p>We also have many members with a background in Statistics. Since most university courses typically use R, students joining our group already have experience with it from their undergraduate studies. Additionally, many individuals from the industry use R for consultancy in various fields. I am currently doing a postdoc, but I also worked with consultants for two years, during which time I used R extensively.</p>
<p><strong>In R-Ladies São Paulo, how many events are typically held each year?</strong></p>
<p>It varies. This year, we hosted two in-person and many more online events—11. We held an average of 6.5 events per year. However, this year, we focused more on online events and had fewer in-person ones, mostly because booking venues for in-person events has been more difficult.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/R-LadiesSaoPauloEvents.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Regarding your experience, are people more interested in online or in-person events?</strong></p>
<p>People engage more in in-person events. They look forward to attending these events because we usually have limited seats, which fill up quickly. We often have a waiting list for those who want to attend. If someone cancels, we can soon offer their spot to someone on the waiting list.</p>
<p>On the other hand, online events tend to have a different pattern of participation. Fewer people attend in real-time, but many engage later by watching the recorded sessions and leaving comments. This flexibility allows those who cannot participate live to catch up afterwards.</p>
<p>While online events can have a broader impact on reaching a larger audience, in-person events typically draw more attendees at once. For instance, we have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/RLadiesS%C3%A3oPaulo">YouTube</a> channel where we post recordings of our online events. One particular event we held during the pandemic garnered 13,000 views, demonstrating significant engagement after the event. However, only some online events achieve that level of viewership; the median for recorded events is 330 views. Nevertheless, I see value in these recordings, as they provide material for those who want to engage later. Sometimes, people are simply not available to attend live.</p>
<p><strong>Please provide us with an update on your group’s recent activities.</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/R-LadiesSaoPaulo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I wanted to discuss a series of events related to the book club we’re hosting. In Brazil, we speak Brazilian Portuguese. An editorial group published the highly regarded book <a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/">R for Data Science</a> in Portuguese. The first edition is available only through purchase, but the English version is free online.</p>
<p>Some communities have done volunteer translations; for instance, there is a <a href="https://es.r4ds.hadley.nz/">Spanish</a> version. When I learned that a second edition of the book was being written, I contacted the authors to ask if we could translate it into Portuguese with the community’s help. It took some time because the authors needed approval from O’Reilly, the publishing company producing the book.</p>
<p>We received confirmation that we could begin the translation. The book’s second edition has <a href="https://cienciadedatos.github.io/pt-r4ds/">been translated and is now available in Portuguese</a>! The translation team is not limited to the R Ladies community; it includes contributions from more than 20 people from different backgrounds.</p>
<p>This book club focuses on discussing the translated Portuguese version of the book. Since February, we have held online meetings to discuss the book chapters. Members from the R Ladies community present these discussions, allowing participants to ask questions and engage in dialogue. These events have been working well.</p>
<p>I have been referencing this book whenever someone asks for material. Many people will already be familiar with it as we continue to promote it. We have also been using and sharing this resource extensively.</p>
<p>Now, the book’s second edition is available in Portuguese <a href="https://cienciadedatos.github.io/pt-r4ds/">online</a> and for free, so anyone with an internet connection can access it. It is an excellent way to share knowledge for those who can afford to buy the book and for anyone with internet access, making it a valuable study resource.</p>
<p><strong>What are some trending topics from the group?</strong></p>
<p>Our events with introductory content attract more participants. It is likely because many attendees are either new to the subject or at an intermediate level, where they feel comfortable studying independently. The most popular topics are introductory sessions.</p>
<p>However, when we asked participants about their interests in different topics, many wanted to learn about machine learning and other trending subjects like deep learning and artificial intelligence. The challenge is that we need more experienced individuals to teach these advanced topics. While many people are interested in these areas, organizing events around them can be more difficult due to the complexity involved.</p>
<p><strong>What techniques do you recommend for planning or conducting the event? (e.g., GitHub, Zoom, etc.) Can these techniques help make your group more inclusive for people unable to attend in-person events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>We use <a href="https://streamyard.com/">StreamYard</a> for our online events. The free version has proven helpful. Previously, when we hosted events on Zoom, we needed to edit recordings and upload them afterwards. This process often took a while, mainly because everyone was busy, and it delayed recording the events online. StreamYard has made the process easier for us, although it does offer less space for participant interaction.</p>
<p>We have a chat feature with StreamYard, but participants can also share their screens on Zoom. Therefore, the platform we choose depends on the kind of event we want to conduct. Participants must share their screens for some events, so we opt for Google Meet or Zoom.</p>
<p>One significant improvement has been our use of <a href="https://github.com/R-Ladies-Sao-Paulo">GitHub</a>. We created issue templates as a to-do list for organizing our upcoming events. This system helps us remember everything we need to do.</p>
<p>Additionally, we have a <a href="https://rladies-sp.org/">blog</a> that invites community members to contribute articles. It allows individuals to write about interesting topics regardless of expertise. Some people hesitate to present at events but feel comfortable writing blog posts. It serves as their first contribution or participation in our community, shifting them from just participants to active contributors.</p>
<p>Overall, the blog is an excellent way to encourage people to make their first contributions.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/books-beginners-big-ideas-beatriz-milz-fostering-r-ladies-sao-paulo-community/R-LadiesSaoPaulo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="60" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Moving forward to meet new challenges in 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Terry Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/moving-forward-to-meet-new-challenges-in-2025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It has been a momentous year for the R Consortium, and we are very grateful for the engagement and support we have received from our member sponsors and all the members of the R community.</p>
<section id="members-91-r-user-groups-39-countries-6-continents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="members-91-r-user-groups-39-countries-6-continents">76,048 members, 91 R User Groups, 39 countries, 6 continents</h2>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/moving-forward-to-meet-new-challenges-in-2025/RUGS-nov-2024.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">R User Groups program</a> is better than ever! We helped to support a lot of you out there learning and sharing the R language. It is exciting to see this type of activity and we hope that in 2025, these groups will continue to grow and that we can sponsor new groups, too. We are always looking for more and better ways to support the community. We hope that you will let us know your suggestions for helping to grow the R community in your area.</p>
</section>
<section id="working-groups-and-top-level-projects-delivering-progress-and-access" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="working-groups-and-top-level-projects-delivering-progress-and-access">Working Groups and Top-Level Projects delivering progress and access</h2>
<p>Many of our working groups and projects had solid wins this year in pushing forward on their projects.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Our Submissions working group achieved its <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/">fourth successful submission with the FDA</a> – the first to feature WebAssembly to bundle a Shiny application into a self-contained package.</p></li>
<li><p>We kicked off our <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/">Health Technology Assessment (HTA) working group</a> with two workstreams (1. Stakeholder and landscape mapping and opportunity assessment &amp; 2. R Tools for HTA – Identification, Curation, and Education) addressing issues in health technology evaluation and building a well-documented resource for robust R tools in HTA.</p></li>
<li><p>Multilingual R Documentation has published its first package <a href="https://github.com/eliocamp/rhelpi18n">rhelpi18n</a> adding multilingual documentation support. This effort is a <a href="https://ropensci.org/multilingual-publishing/">co-sponsored project</a> with <a href="https://www.ropensci.org">rOpenSci</a> and the <a href="https://czi.co/OpenScience">Chan-Zuckerberg Initiative’s Open Science Program</a>,</p></li>
<li><p>We have added <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-universe-named-r-consortiums-newest-top-level-project/">R-universe as a new Top-Level Project</a>. R-universe provides a searchable catalog for R software, articles, datasets, anywhere in the ecosystem, and it is an open platform for running CRAN-like package repositories.&nbsp;We are thrilled to be working with rOpenSci on this important infrastructure project for the R community.</p></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="quarto-powered-website" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quarto-powered-website">Quarto powered website</h2>
<p>We must brag about our beautiful new Quarto-based website that we launched this year. Performance was increased by 65% faster overall, with homepage load times going from 2.3 seconds to 0.8 seconds on average in testing. The team did a wonderful job, and we invite the community to <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/rconsortium_website#contributing-to-this-website">join us in contributing to the site.</a> This is a great opportunity for first time contributors and for others to get a chance to work with a Quarto site.</p>
</section>
<section id="expanding-support-for-the-r-language-and-infrastructure" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="expanding-support-for-the-r-language-and-infrastructure">Expanding support for the R language and infrastructure</h2>
<p>The Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC) funds two grant cycles per year for projects that support the development of the R language and the maintenance of its infrastructure. We funded <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/funded-projects.html">13 new projects in 2024</a>. We have dispersed technical grants totaling almost $1.5 million since our founding. Our next grant cycle will re-open March 1, 2025, and now is a great time to <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">contact the ISC to start the process</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="events-irl-and-digital-were-huge-wins-for-all-of-us" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="events-irl-and-digital-were-huge-wins-for-all-of-us">Events IRL and digital were huge wins for all of us!</h2>
<p>Live events are a great way to share new developments and raise awareness of what our community needs or wants. The R Consortium sponsored 12 events this year, and we are looking forward to seeing a lot of you next year at <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/RMedicine_website/">R/Medicine June 10-13</a> and useR! August 8-10. To access all the digital events and webinar content we produce, please <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@RConsortium">subscribe to our YouTube channel</a> so you are sure to get new videos as we post them.</p>
</section>
<section id="new-year-new-opportunities-and-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-year-new-opportunities-and-challenges">New year, new opportunities and challenges</h2>
<p>I encourage you to register for <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/RMedicine_website/">R/Medicine June 10-13</a> and <strong>SAVE THE DATE for useR!</strong> at Duke University August 8-10. We are looking forward to all the great programming in 2025 and <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/contact.html">would love to hear from the community any requests/ideas</a> for content you would like to see.</p>
<p>Finally, <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/">our mission in support of the R language and its community</a> is at the core of everything we do. This means we need to answer new challenges that face both. The recently passed <a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/cyber-resilience-act">Cyber Resilience Act</a> will require CRAN and all community repositories to make changes to meet its requirements for distribution of packages in the EU. We are asking now for financial support to ensure that we, in coordination with the Linux Foundation, can assist all our repository maintainers to plan and work toward compliance by October of 2027.</p>
<p>To our current members, we thank you for your support and ask you to consider renewing your support at the next level.</p>
<p>If you're considering becoming a member-sponsor of the R Consortium, feel free to reach out to me (<a href="mailto:director@r-consrtium.org?subject=R%20Consortium%20Membership">director at r-consortium dot org</a>) or <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/join.html#joining-the-r-consortium-is-easy.">view the materials on our website</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/moving-forward-to-meet-new-challenges-in-2025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/moving-forward-to-meet-new-challenges-in-2025/RUGS-nov-2024.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="76" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empowering Girls in Data Science: The R-Girls-School Network Initiative</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/drghani.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed Dr.&nbsp;Raiza Ghani, Professor Mohamed Amin, and R teacher Anisa Nawaz. Dr.&nbsp;Razia Ghani and her team at <a href="https://greenoak.bham.sch.uk/">Green Oak Academy</a> are leading a two-year project to establish the R-Girls-School (R-GS) network, addressing the underrepresentation of women, particularly from deprived and ethnically diverse backgrounds, in data science. The initiative aims to integrate data science into the UK national curriculum, which is used by schools globally. The project focuses on developing 10 R-based lesson plans in the first year, with the second year dedicated to networking and dissemination. This includes a dedicated website with extensive online resources. Supported by key figures and organizations in the R community, the project aims to provide sustainable, impactful education in data science for girls worldwide​. This project was funded by the R Consortium.</p>
<p><a href="https://rgirls.org.uk/"><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/rgirlswebsite.png" class="img-fluid"></a> <a href="https://rgirls.org.uk/">R-Girls Website</a></p>
<p><strong>What inspired you to initiate the R-Girls-Schools (R-GS) Network project?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> Initially, we thought we would integrate programming into our school curriculum. Using programming to explain mathematical concepts would help the girls visualize and understand them better. Gradually, this idea expanded into a larger vision, where we aimed to create a network of schools using the lessons we developed. Part of the funding requirements was to open up our lessons beyond just our school.</p>
<p>Additionally, being an all-girls school made this initiative particularly appealing to us. We recognized that our students might not have had this exposure otherwise and wanted to provide them with this valuable opportunity. Professor Mohamed worked with us, making it an ideal situation. It was an opportunity that came our way, and we seized it enthusiastically.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/rgirls_logo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Logo design: Anisa Nawaz</em></p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> First, we observed that girls in our school generally didn’t take to computer science; they were often turned off by the subject. Second, Dr.&nbsp;Ghani, with a background in mathematics and statistics, understands the power of software in these fields, both in the classroom and in industry.</p>
<p>I had the pleasure of helping set up the R community for the National Health Service (<a href="https://nhsrcommunity.com/">https://nhsrcommunity.com/</a>) in the UK, which was a very positive experience. One summer, outside of school, Dr.&nbsp;Ghani and I discussed bringing the joy of R to the classroom. This idea seemed readily achievable because of Dr.&nbsp;Ghani’s background in mathematics and statistics. We then considered how to implement this and became aware of a funding opportunity from the R Consortium. As part of that process, we actively sought support from various individuals who replied positively.</p>
<p>I should emphasize that our goal was not to teach computer programming. Dr.&nbsp;Ghani made it clear from the beginning that we see software as a tool to teach other subjects, not just programming. Our aim was to use R as an applied tool to help the girls in various subjects involving data collection, analysis, and visualization.</p>
<p>In summary, we wanted to see if teenage girls could experience the joy of using R. The support from the R consortium allowed us to pursue this idea.</p>
<p><strong>Anisa:</strong> My first experience with R was a request to design a logo. It was exciting to do and it’s great to see the logo has now been adopted. However when I started coding in R, I initially thought it would be very complicated, involving writing a lot of formulas and complex code. However, I’ve learned that coding is actually quite easy. Most resources can be found online, and often it’s just a matter of tweaking things, like replacing numbers or colors. The girls also noticed that while it seemed like a lot of text and difficult concepts at first, they began to understand what everything meant over time, making it much easier for them.</p>
<p>One challenge is that only a few girls are entering fields like data science because they need to understand how it works or what it looks like to work in that field. This lack of understanding makes it seem more complicated and intimidating. But now that they see how it works, I hope that in the future, more girls will be interested in these areas.</p>
<p><strong>Could you explain the significance of using R specifically, as opposed to other programming languages, in the context of this project?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> We were aware that computer science didn’t appeal to the girls, so we avoided using that label and the associated languages. Instead, we opted for R because of its strong worldwide community, numerous user groups, and abundant free resources. The <a href="https://rladies.org/">R-Ladies group</a> is also a significant part of that community, which helps build confidence for both staff and students in their journey with R.</p>
<p>This doesn’t mean we’re against other languages such as Python; we just chose to focus our energy on R. You can go far in your data science career with R, especially if your primary goal is to analyze existing data, look for insights, and create reports and graphics, rather than building data science products.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani used SAS a long time ago when there were fewer choices, but SAS is not something we would consider bringing to the school. It’s a complex programming language that takes many years to master. These were some of the considerations we had when choosing R over other options. For us, it was a clear decision.</p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> From the school finance perspective, choosing R was a no-brainer. It’s freely available, which makes a huge difference compared to having to subscribe to something annually. We did have some annual subscriptions for other things, but R itself is free, and we were already using it in the school. We use R to produce graphs that show student progress and to print out timetables. This project was just a natural extension of what we were already doing.</p>
<p><strong>Can you elaborate on the specific challenges girls from disadvantaged, ethnically diverse backgrounds face in entering the field of data science?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> I think the key issue here is deprivation, particularly among ethnic minority backgrounds. The girls’ backgrounds likely play a significant role. Coming from a deprived family limits their exposure to fields like data science. For example, they might know about engineering but need to be made aware of the different types of engineers. Similarly, they might know about doctors but not the various specializations available.</p>
<p>Deprivation makes it more difficult for them to access these opportunities. If you come from an influential family, you’re exposed to many different fields. In contrast, our community doesn’t offer the girls many readily available opportunities. This project was a chance for us to expose them to something they might not encounter until university.</p>
<p><strong>Anisa:</strong> It might sound more complicated, but we have girls in our class, ages 12-13 years, building websites by themselves. We encourage them and help fix mistakes. Many of these girls are learning on their own, despite lacking prior knowledge. Some don’t have computers at home or know how to use them well. I also teach ICT, and I’ve seen girls who struggle with basic computer skills, like typing quickly.</p>
<p>I know some girls have a harder time because they come from backgrounds with limited financial resources and lack access to technology at home. They often need extra training in basic software like Word or PowerPoint. Without our support, it’s less likely they would be introduced to these topics. I think what we’re doing is very important and beneficial.</p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> Data science is not typically in the mindset of our students because they come from ethnically diverse and deprived backgrounds where traditional roles are more emphasized. Data science is not part of their vocabulary, and their parents wouldn’t know how to encourage them in this field even if they wanted to.</p>
<p>Our school has been able to expand their horizons, showing them new interests and possibilities. They have found joy in R and data science, which was not initially within their bandwidth. We started with pre-made lessons, but with support, the girls’ horizons have expanded. They are now doing amazing projects with R, something we couldn’t have anticipated initially.</p>
<p>If someone had suggested on day one that 11 to 16-year-olds would be building their own websites using R, it would have seemed too ambitious. Yet, today, they are doing just that because they chose to pursue their interest without it being mandated. The girls asked to build websites - we had no such plans! The topics they choose for their websites are engaging and interesting, allowing them to do creative and intellectual work, organize, and debug code. These are sophisticated skills, and they are learning them in a fun way. None of this would have been available to them in the traditional curriculum.</p>
<section id="feedback-on-the-second-r-lesson-using-r-markdown" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="feedback-on-the-second-r-lesson-using-r-markdown">Feedback on the Second R Lesson using R Markdown</h3>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/feedback1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/feedback2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/feedback3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>How did your previous experience as an applied statistician in the pharmaceutical sector influence your approach to integrating R in the school curriculum?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> When you’re doing statistical analysis in any field, you realize how much data is available and how important it is to analyze it efficiently. In teaching, I noticed that many still use old methods of manual calculations and drawing graphs by hand. If software is available, it can make it much easier for students to visualize data quickly instead of creating everything from scratch.</p>
<p>Using R, the visualization of data becomes much quicker and more straightforward; it’s often just a matter of cutting and pasting from the programs, making it easier to reuse graphs without having to redraw them each time. The ability to quickly visualize and analyze data using R has been a game-changer for our students. This ease of use is a significant advantage.</p>
<p>If I hadn’t had a background in statistics and data science, this project wouldn’t have taken off in our school.</p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> Having someone with a background in mathematics and statistics in the industry meant that the idea could germinate in a fertile environment. Otherwise, it might have intimidated people. For context, schools are very congested places, not just with people but with time. There’s wall-to-wall coverage from 9 to 5 with almost no curriculum space. Teachers are working very hard, and students are very busy. You might get five minutes with someone if you’re lucky. It’s a complex environment with constant changes.</p>
<p>So, for anyone to be willing to try something new in that environment deserves a medal. Dr.&nbsp;Ghani’s industry experience meant there was no fear of the idea, which was crucial because lack of confidence is a major issue in change management. This confidence was vital because Dr.&nbsp;Ghani understood the power of data science in the industry.</p>
<p>One of our early design decisions, which is a testament to the development of RStudio and the investment in R, was to make R Markdown central to our work. This allowed the girls to do data analysis, graphics, and report writing all within one document. In the old model, as Dr.&nbsp;Ghani described, you would do your analysis, cut and paste the graph into your report, and retype the numbers. These tasks, which were painful, became smooth and doable within the RStudio environment. The girls could see the convenience of plotting something and having it come out in a ready-made report. The development of these technical tools made it easy to launch this initiative.</p>
<p><strong>How do you envision the R-GS Network impacting the broader educational landscape for girls worldwide?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> We want other girls’ schools to see us as an inspiration. One of our goals is to hold an online conference where girls from any country can join and showcase their projects and work. This would allow us to share information and experiences. An annual conference like this would be great for networking, improving communication skills, and showing that we’re not isolated. There is a global community facing similar challenges. This shared community could also help form long-term friendships among the girls.</p>
<p>Through our connections on <a href="https://twitter.com/r_girls_school">Twitter (now X)</a>, we’ve joined many R-Ladies groups and received numerous follow-backs and visitors, which has been inspiring. Even though we’ve only been active for about two years, seeing how our community is growing is amazing. If the girls can build this community with others around the globe, who knows where we could end up? Our aim is to eventually have a global conference for the girls.</p>
<p>COVID didn’t help; we weren’t allowed to travel or attend in-person conferences, only online. That was a bit of a setback, but we’re coming out of that now. Schools are currently facing challenges with their curriculums, especially at Key Stage 3 (ages 11-13, which is equivalent to middle school in the USA). I believe curriculums need to be broadened because the standard approach is too restrictive. It doesn’t open students’ minds to the idea that subjects like geography, math, and science are interconnected.</p>
<p>We’ve started collaborative lessons where teachers cover the same topic across different subjects at Key Stage 3. This approach might inspire other schools to become more integrated. We need to demonstrate the benefits of this method. I think we will have to be the pioneers if we want to move forward.</p>
<p><strong>Anisa:</strong> I believe that collaboration with girls from different countries and places would be beneficial, even across language barriers. When I was in university, we were encouraged to work on overseas projects to understand how things work in different parts of the world. Similarly, we can provide feedback to each other about our work.</p>
<p>Our lessons are designed to be used by anyone, regardless of gender, though they are particularly beneficial for girls. I hope that our lessons can also help university students because they are so simple to use. We aim for our work to help many people around the world, especially girls. <a href="https://rgirls.org.uk/">https://rgirls.org.uk/</a></p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> We’ve received a lot of interest from people around the world, and we’ve had several visitors come to our school to see R in action in the classroom. This was a great experience for the girls, showing them that people are interested in what they’re doing. We’ve also had visits from R Ladies members. While we have big ambitions and interest from R Ladies and others interested in R for girls globally, we have yet to find a way to get into more schools.</p>
<p>Schools are very congested and under a lot of pressure. Teachers are very busy and under a lot of stress, with many considering leaving the profession. Engaging schools is a challenge. If anyone is trying to bring R into their school, we’d love to partner with them because they already have an open door. Dr.&nbsp;Ghani and Green Oak Academy’s story is special because of our alignment but we believe any school can use R in the classroom with a little bit of support (from us!).</p>
<p>It took us about two and a half to three years to embed R into our school, and it will likely take other schools just as long if they’re starting from scratch. Our ambition is huge because the potential is huge, but we still need to crack how to get into more schools. We’d love to host a R girls’ conference and network with other schools in the future. Dr.&nbsp;Ghani has presented at two conferences, but they were both data science conferences, not education-focused ones. We plan to present more at education conferences, but that’s still a work in progress.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://rss.org.uk/">Royal Statistical Society</a> recognized that we didn’t set out to teach R as a standalone subject; instead, we aimed to support existing subjects in the curriculum using R. This meant that R didn’t need its own space in the timetable. Traditionally, new timetables were created for teaching subjects like R or Python as part of computer science, but we took a different approach. By integrating R into existing subjects, we avoided framing it as a separate computer science topic. As a result, R has organically spread in ways we couldn’t have anticipated, but we’re delighted to see this growth.</p>
<p>This approach highlights a necessary mindset change for schools: it’s not about carving out new timetable space but thinking differently about using tools like R within the existing curriculum.</p>
<p><strong>How do you plan to integrate R into the teaching of non-mathematical subjects like geography and science?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> Our science and geography lessons are data-rich. For example, when experimenting, students collect a lot of data, which is a great starting point. The girls are already programming in some ways. They can use the collected data with a ready-made lesson for that experiment. For science, they simply input their data and work with it. For geography, they can find readily available data online, like rainfall data from different parts of the world, and analyze it.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/geography_lesson.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We started by creating lessons based on our needs and exploring the data to generate charts and insights. Initially, that was our focus. However, we began developing websites with the girls, which was not something we originally planned. If someone had told me at the beginning that we would be doing web design, I wouldn’t have believed it. One of our visitors helped us develop our girls’ website, and during a conversation, the girls expressed their desire to create a website. Now, we have lessons on creating websites step by step.</p>
<p>It’s almost like we’re giving them the skeleton and they build upon it. We provide the structure, and they use it to develop websites or analyze data for different subjects. It really comes down to their imagination. I’ve seen incredible things artists can do, things I never thought were possible. The internet has shown us amazing possibilities once we dove into the R programming side of things.</p>
<p>This initiative has expanded beyond just science and geography to include design technology and website creation. The resources and guidance are there for the girls to use. It’s all about providing the resources and opportunities for the children. They’ll take it forward from there.</p>
<p><strong>Anisa:</strong> Designing a website involves a lot of creativity. The girls engage in video chatting, finding pictures, and defining their designs. Some girls use websites to create their own logos, choosing colors and everything else. For example, the current website project involves themes like street shops and skateboarding outfits. The girls gather all the necessary materials, such as prices and pictures, and design logos and fonts.</p>
<p>This process includes an artistic element, as they create layouts and visual designs. It’s a comprehensive activity that combines art, design, and practical skills.</p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> I see that we were excited about the framework and the shape of our projects, but what’s emerging here is the transformation of the girls. We have some lovely stories about how these projects have impacted students. It’s also transformed some of our teachers, giving them the courage to learn something new and bring it into the classroom. The head of geography, Mrs.&nbsp;Dabhelia, and the head of science, Mrs.&nbsp;Nawaz, have personal stories about how this experience has changed them as teachers.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani and I, who had the initial conversation, can now step back and enjoy seeing how positively this has enriched the students’, staff’s, and school’s experience.</p>
<p><strong>How has it been working with the R Consortium? Would you recommend applying for an ISC grant to other R developers?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/priceless.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Dr.&nbsp;Ghani:</strong> The visitors and opportunities we’ve had are priceless. The initial funding from the R Consortium gave us credibility, showing people we were serious because we had reputable backing.</p>
<p>For anyone else starting out, give it a go. You’ve got nothing to lose. Submit the bid—you never know what might come of it. Even if you don’t get everything you ask for, the help and support you receive can be invaluable. Additionally, we won a prize at the EARL conference, which further validated our efforts.</p>
<p>I have to add that when we submitted our bid, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hadleywickham/">Hadley Wickham</a> responded. At first, I didn’t know who he was. I mentioned to the professor that someone named Hadley got back to me, and they told me he’s the main man in the field. It was impressive to receive his response, and our first conversation was memorable.</p>
<p>Hadley advised us to start small. We planned to create more lessons initially, but he suggested opening up as a network and getting others involved from outside our school. His advice was to expand beyond our school to reach a wider audience. In hindsight, those were words of wisdom. At that time, we were focused on our school’s curriculum, but his advice helped us see the bigger picture and involve more people in the initiative.</p>
<p><strong>Professor Mohamed:</strong> Our interaction with the R Consortium was very positive. We found that people were interested in the technical details of our project as well as in the idea itself. Hadley and other colleagues provided valuable feedback and support. Initially, we considered bidding for long-term funding, but they wisely advised us to break it down into smaller parts and start with seed funding. This approach has been very helpful.</p>
<p>Now, the R Consortium has two separate funding streams: one community-oriented and one technical. This wasn’t clear to us initially, but we plan to apply for community funding in the future. We’d love for the consortium to help us engage its influential members to invest in using R in education, particularly for students aged 11 to 16.</p>
<p>R in education might need a different model than used for university-level R, R-Ladies, or other conferences. We could set up a small working group to explore how to bring R into education globally. Our project has some experience, but there’s still much to learn. We’ve had interest from colleagues in different parts of the world, mainly the Middle East, but there isn’t enough momentum on this topic. It is a neglected area.</p>
<p>The R Consortium could consider a strategic approach to add R in schools and home education environments. Overall, our experience with the R Consortium has been very positive.</p>
</section>
<section id="about-isc-funded-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-isc-funded-projects">About ISC Funded Projects</h2>
<p>A major goal of the R Consortium is to strengthen and improve the infrastructure supporting the R Ecosystem. We seek to accomplish this by funding projects that will improve both technical infrastructure and social infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/call-for-proposals">https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/call-for-proposals</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-girls-in-data-science-the-r-girls-school-network-initiative/drghani-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="69" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R-Universe Named R Consortium’s Newest Top Level Project</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-universe-named-r-consortiums-newest-top-level-project/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://r-universe.dev/search"><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-universe-named-r-consortiums-newest-top-level-project/r-universe-search.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
<p>The R Consortium is proud to announce our newest top level project, <a href="https://r-universe.dev/search">R-Universe</a>. R-universe is a platform for improving publication and discovery of research software in R, developed by rOpenSci.</p>
<p>Critical R community projects that need support over a longer time period are evaluated by the Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC) for long-term status. Being designated Top Level gives a project guaranteed funding for 3 years, along with a voting seat on the ISC.</p>
<p>“The ability to find and evaluate high quality R packages is important to the R community, and the R Consortium is pleased to support the R-Universe project with a long-term commitment to help strengthen the foundation of the R package ecosystem,” said Terry Christiani, R Consortium executive director. “We are pleased to be working more closely together with rOpenSci on this effort.”</p>
<p>R-Universe will be joining R Consortium’s three current Top Level Projects:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://r-dbi.org/">DBI</a> - R’s interface to databases</li>
<li><a href="https://rladies.org/">R-Ladies</a> - Promoting diversity in the R community with 200+ groups worldwide</li>
<li><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">R User Group Support Program (RUGS)</a> - facilitating person-to-person exchange of knowledge in small group settings on a global scale</li>
</ul>
<p>“R-universe provides a searchable catalog for R software, articles, datasets, anywhere in the ecosystem, and it is an open platform for running CRAN-like package repositories ranging from personal to lab to industry-scale production to make your work visible and accessible to a big audience, with or without CRAN,” said Noam Ross, rOpenSci executive director. “We are very excited to continue to strengthen R infrastructure and work closely with the R Consortium.”</p>
<p>R-universe allows users and developers of R packages to:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Discover:</strong> R-universe provides a searchable catalog for R software, articles, datasets, anywhere in the ecosystem. It is indexed and ranked using R specific features.</li>
<li><strong>Learn:</strong> R-universe serves rendered material and extensive background information to learn about a package and get started using it.</li>
<li><strong>Publish:</strong> R-universe is an open platform for running personal CRAN-like package repositories to make work public and accessible to a big audience, with or without CRAN.</li>
<li><strong>Develop:</strong> R-universe provides a zero-config development environment for continuous integration (identify upcoming breakage before release), experimental R features, new platforms such as WebAssembly, and more.</li>
</ul>
<p>For more information about the R Consortium’s Top Level Projects, please visit: <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-universe-named-r-consortiums-newest-top-level-project/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empowering Data Science in Mexico: R-Ladies Querétaro on Inclusivity and Growth</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/DriseldaSánchez-Aguirre.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<p>Driselda Sánchez-Aguirre, co-founder and organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/es/rladies-queretaro/">R-Ladies Querétaro</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about her journey in building a welcoming, diverse R community in Querétaro, Mexico. She shared insights on the chapter’s hybrid events, collaborative partnerships with other R-Ladies chapters, and upcoming workshops focused on accessible R training. Driselda highlighted the challenges and rewards of growing a supportive space for women in data science in Querétaro and beyond. Querétaro is located in central Mexico, about 4 hours north of Mexico City.</p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I co-founded the R-Ladies Querétaro chapter as a PhD student in economics. It was fascinating to connect with women from various disciplines who shared an interest in creating the group together. One of the members was also a PhD student, but she specialized in genomics, while another was a postdoctoral researcher in psychology. We all shared a passion for using R, although I initially found it challenging because economics primarily focuses on business-related disciplines.</p>
<p>We have access to many software options for statistics that are easier to use but are often proprietary. Initially, I was just looking for a simple button to click to find results. However, I discovered that R offers much more, including beautiful graphs and visuals. Each time you use it for a new task, it presents a challenge, but it is incredibly rewarding to uncover the answers. Since 2019, we have organized sessions and workshops to continue developing this chapter.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Mexico?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/RLadiesQueretarologo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>From my experience, R is primarily used in academia and the industry. Specifically, the R-Ladies Querétaro chapter is quite diverse, with a mix of professionals. For instance, I am an economist, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/azalea-reyes-aguilar-5a328b70/">Azalea</a> works in psychology, <a href="https://comunidadbioinfo.github.io/authors/anabva/">Ana Betty</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/karen-nu%C3%B1ez-reza">Karen</a> study genomics, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elizabeth-valles-053b4815a/?originalSubdomain=mx">Elizabeth</a> is in neuroscience. One of our main focuses is inclusivity, ensuring that individuals from all backgrounds and skill levels feel welcome. All genders are welcome, but meetings and workshops are always organized and hosted by women.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/RladiesQueretaroMeeting.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I remember our first meeting in 2019; it was a truly memorable occasion. We discovered that women from various industries attended the workshop, marking the inaugural chapter meeting in Querétaro. It was inspiring to see women working as programmers in the pharmaceutical industry and as engineers coming together. It was an incredible experience to have such a variety of backgrounds represented.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/RladiesQueretaroGroupPhoto1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>When the pandemic began, managing the various profiles we maintained became challenging. Since then, the focus has shifted towards academic users, particularly women interested in workshops. While we still connect with women from industry through social networks and email, our primary target group is academia in Querétaro.</p>
<p>Since last year, we have collaborated with <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/">R-Ladies Morelia</a>, another chapter in Mexico. We discovered that a significant group of women use R for bioinformatics, a fascinating area of interest. I enjoy discussing social and economic topics, especially those related to tourism, political stories, and inclusivity. However, most discussions focus more on bioinformatics and similar subjects.</p>
<p><strong>Please tell us about upcoming events from your group.</strong></p>
<p>During the COVID pandemic, we transitioned to online events, and since 2022, we have been working towards a hybrid format. Now, we’re excited to return to in-person gatherings.</p>
<p>I would like to highlight a recent event from our group. On September 28th, we participated in the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ql9pXSPPQOU">R-Ladies Mexico Annual Meeting</a>, which brings together all R ladies’ chapters nationwide. The event is open to everyone who speaks Spanish, making it a fantastic opportunity to connect, share knowledge, and foster collaborative partnerships.</p>
<p>Additionally, thanks to a grant from the R Consortium, we plan to host four more workshops yearly. The first one was face-to-face on <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-queretaro/events/304128867/?utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=share-btn_savedevents_share_modal&amp;utm_source=link">how to make maps with R</a>, open to the general public but emphasizing students and researchers in earth sciences and geography. It was on November 21st, 2024, we had about 20 attendees, there was pizza and popcorn to share with each other.</p>
<p>The other three workshops will cover basic R concepts using <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot</a> and open science practices incorporating R. While we don’t have exact dates for all the workshops, we have already begun planning and are excited to offer these opportunities to our community.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/RladiesQueretaroGroupPhoto2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We use a variety of tools to ensure smooth planning for our events. <a href="https://github.com/">GitHub</a> is essential for sharing our resources. For example, when we’re hosting a workshop, it’s easier to share the GitHub link so that participants can access the materials we’ll be using.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.zoom.com/">Zoom</a> also enables remote participation, making our events accessible to a wider audience. It includes reaction features that help gauge participant engagement. For instance, attendees can click a green button if they understand the task or a red button if they feel lost. This feedback allows us to tailor the learning experience to meet their needs better.</p>
<p>We use social media to promote our events, primarily <a href="https://x.com/RLadies_Qro">X</a> and Facebook. Additionally, we believe that collaborating with other R Ladies chapters enhances our outreach. We have partnered with chapters in <a href="https://x.com/RLadiesBquilla">Colombia</a> and other locations in Mexico, which allows us to expand the topics we cover, as they also use their media channels to promote our events.</p>
<p>We have also found WhatsApp to be a useful communication tool. WhatsApp provides a real-time platform for organizers to communicate and coordinate. These tools help make the group more inclusive, accessible, and efficient, ensuring that tasks are completed on time.</p>
<p><strong>What challenges have you faced in organizing the R Ladies Querétaro Chapter? How have you overcome these challenges?</strong></p>
<p>I believe it’s crucial to emphasize the importance of collaboration and community support. As a nonprofit group, we often face challenges, especially when managing time due to other responsibilities, such as family obligations. To maintain consistent participation, we need to balance our personal and professional lives while continuing to advance our chapter.</p>
<p>Maintaining the chapter is rewarding, but finding the time is also a constant challenge. We love what we do because we want to share all the good things it offers to different disciplines and areas of focus. However, this challenge to find time can be overwhelming. I believe we can overcome it through collaboration and community support. It’s important to emphasize the role of the community in helping us achieve our goals.</p>
<p><strong>How do I Join?</strong></p>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 75,492 members in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-in-mexico-r-ladies-queretaro-on-inclusivity-and-growth/RladiesQueretaroGroupPhoto2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="71" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bridging the Real-Time Gap: How INWT is Bringing Apache Kafka to the R Ecosystem</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/bridging-the-real-time-gap-how-inwt-is-bringing-apache-kafka-to-the-r-ecosystem/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/bridging-the-real-time-gap-how-inwt-is-bringing-apache-kafka-to-the-r-ecosystem/Andreas.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>In a recent interview with the R Consortium, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreas-neudecker-457946208/">Andreas Neudecker</a>, solution architect at INWT, a data and analytics company located in Berlin, Germany, shared insights into the motivation behind developing an Apache Kafka client for R and the challenges it aims to address within the R ecosystem. His company frequently builds models in both R and Python, often encountering the need for real-time data analytics from Kafka clusters. When a real-time fraud detection project required connecting to a Kafka cluster, the lack of a stable Kafka client for R forced them to switch to Python despite having an R-based model ready to go. This experience highlighted the gap in R’s real-time data processing capabilities. It inspired Andreas to develop a Kafka client for R, making it easier to access real-time data sources and potentially leveling the playing field with Python.</p>
<p>To get started using kafka right away, please reference this article by Andreas titled “<a href="https://www.inwt-statistics.com/blog/r-package-kafka">Introducing the kafka R Package</a>,” which covers an example to demonstrate how kafka works.</p>
<p>GitHub repository: <a href="https://github.com/INWTlab/r-kafka">https://github.com/INWTlab/r-kafka</a></p>
<p>Installation from GitHub:</p>
<pre><code>remotes::install_github("inwtlab/r-kafka")</code></pre>
<p>This ISC project was funded by the R Consortium.</p>
<p><strong>What motivated you to develop a Kafka client for R, and what specific challenges in the R ecosystem are you aiming to address with this project?</strong></p>
<p>We typically build models in both R and Python, depending on our customers’ needs and preferences. Each language has different types of models available, so the choice between R and Python depends on the specific requirements. We handle both traditional batch processing and real-time analytics for our clients.</p>
<p>Many of our customers use Kafka clusters for their real-time data. At one point, we faced a challenge where we needed to perform real-time analytics, but the data was stored in a Kafka cluster. The question became: how do we connect to the Kafka cluster?</p>
<p>To be more specific, we had a real-time fraud detection project where we needed to identify fraudulent patterns in a stream of transactions. We already had a model in R, and our initial plan was to continue using it to keep costs down. However, we realized there was no stable Kafka client available for R at the time. So, we were essentially forced to switch to Python to consume the data from Kafka, which wasn’t our preferred choice.</p>
<p>In the end, we developed a solution by having a Python consumer write data into an in-memory cache database, which allowed us to continue using our existing R model. The R process accessed the data from this cache database. This experience made it clear to us that having a Kafka client for R would have made the process much smoother. We’ve also heard from other companies who made the same choice—they opted for Python over R simply because Python had a Kafka client, and R didn’t.</p>
<p><strong>Could you explain how the R Kafka client will enhance real-time data analysis and processing capabilities within the R environment?</strong></p>
<p>In many cases, there are solid reasons to train models in R. For example, some specific models are available in R that haven’t been developed in Python yet. Personally, I also find that I can develop much faster in R—it typically takes me less time to get a running prototype compared to Python.</p>
<p>What I’ve noticed is that R is often used more for traditional batch processing or modeling, but there’s no real reason why it shouldn’t also be used for real-time applications. I believe that having a Kafka client for R could be a missing piece of the puzzle, making it easier to access real-time data sources.</p>
<p><strong>How does the proposed solution compare to existing alternatives, such as using Python for Kafka communication in data pipelines?</strong></p>
<p>It should essentially work the same way as it does in Python, since we’re using the same underlying C library. While we’re still in the early stages and don’t have all the capabilities of the Python client yet, the experience should feel pretty similar because of this shared foundation.</p>
<p><strong>What were the key insights from your initial benchmarking of the prototype, and how do they inform the project’s development goals?</strong></p>
<p>First, we created a proof of concept (PoC), which showed us that it’s definitely possible to write a proper Kafka client for R using the C library. As we moved on to building the first minimum viable product (MVP), we also did some basic benchmarking. The results showed that we were a bit slower than the Python client. To give you some numbers, we could consume or produce 1 million messages in about 20 seconds, while Python handled it in 10 seconds, so Python was faster in this case.</p>
<p>However, I believe we could improve this with a better interface or some optimizations. That said, even with these numbers, the speed difference shouldn’t have a major impact in most real-world applications, because it’s not just about reading the data—it also involves processing, which takes additional time. So, even though the client isn’t quite as fast as Python’s, it’s still sufficient for most use cases.</p>
<p><strong>What is the significance of the Admin Client functionalities in managing Kafka infrastructure, and how do you plan to implement these within the R package?</strong></p>
<p>Right now, our client can handle the essential tasks of sending and receiving data. However, it would be great to add the ability to create and delete topics directly within R, as well as manage consumer group offsets. These are likely the most important additional features we need.</p>
<p>We plan to implement this in a way similar to how the Python Confluent package does it—by creating a separate class for admin tasks. Since the underlying functionality already exists in the C++ package, the process should be straightforward. We just need to create wrapper functions using <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/Rcpp/index.html">Rcpp</a>, write the documentation, and run the necessary tests, and then it should work as expected.</p>
<p><strong>How has it been working with the R Consortium? Would you recommend applying for an ISC grant to other R developers?</strong></p>
<p>It was a very straightforward and smooth process, with no unnecessary bureaucracy. Overall, it was a great experience, and we had a friendly and helpful contact person throughout. I would definitely recommend it if you have an idea—it’s a really good way to secure funding.</p>
<section id="about-isc-funded-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-isc-funded-projects">About ISC Funded Projects</h2>
<p>A major goal of the R Consortium is to strengthen and improve the infrastructure supporting the R Ecosystem. We seek to accomplish this by funding projects that will improve both technical infrastructure and social infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/bridging-the-real-time-gap-how-inwt-is-bringing-apache-kafka-to-the-r-ecosystem/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/bridging-the-real-time-gap-how-inwt-is-bringing-apache-kafka-to-the-r-ecosystem/Andreas.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Health Technology Assessment (HTA) Working Group Kickoff: Building a Collaborative Vision in R for HTA</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On October 31, 2024, the Health Technology Assessment (HTA) Working Group convened for its first general meeting, marking the beginning of an exciting industry-wide initiative to elevate the role of R within the HTA community. The gathering featured 35 members, including co-chairs and founding members Gregory Chen, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/anders-gorst-rasmussen-50bb732/?originalSubdomain=dk">Anders Gorst-Rasmussen</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dominic-muston-a897517/">Dominic Muston</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-rickert-a45a96?miniProfileUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_miniProfile%3AACoAAAAo_1UB1mlPH37Q6CKV1o0BVHibrVBgYsA&amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_search_srp_all%3B9Qho7amVQtCu8OfJFebhwA%3D%3D">Joseph Rickert</a>, with participants bringing varied expertise from across the HTA landscape. Hosted on video, the kickoff set the stage for collaboration, innovation, and tangible impacts on the development and application of R tools in health technology assessments. You can watch the recording <a href="https://zoom.us/rec/play/IGEvwwmmIZ_BVHB5wqMkdDpTcjC1VsEcEU4RcBJPkpZSR_zMOow3nCQH7FMTbiQk27bq0MBPABOgpHMe.LH2M4thN5AqgI3sY?canPlayFromShare=true&amp;from=share_recording_detail&amp;continueMode=true&amp;componentName=rec-play&amp;originRequestUrl=https%3A%2F%2Fzoom.us%2Frec%2Fshare%2F9NTj9ZtSKBFz3Ij0rf0x3gTSoOcx99MCdvJCzUEUz3XEboB-EhilI4mMQ-Bw8bYe.0IKFWabamQjvIRdS">here.</a></p>
<section id="opening-remarks-and-vision" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="opening-remarks-and-vision">Opening Remarks and Vision</h2>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/OpeningRemarksandVision.png" class="img-fluid"> Gregory Chen and Anders Gorst-Rasmussen opened the meeting with a vision of collaboration, emphasizing the importance of a shared, flexible structure within the HTA Working Group. The co-chairs highlighted two initial workstreams designed to channel the group’s efforts without restricting the scope of potential projects. This framework underscores the group’s commitment to evolve in response to member feedback and industry needs.</p>
</section>
<section id="workstream-1-building-connections-across-the-hta-ecosystem" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workstream-1-building-connections-across-the-hta-ecosystem">Workstream 1: Building Connections Across the HTA Ecosystem</h2>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/Workstream1.png" class="img-fluid"> Anders Gorst-Rasmussen and Dominic Muston introduced the first workstream, focusing on building connections across diverse stakeholders within HTA. This foundational effort aims to foster a common perspective and identify relevant challenges and opportunities. By bridging gaps between different sectors within HTA, Workstream 1 seeks to create a solid framework for addressing complex issues in health technology evaluation and supporting innovation across the industry.</p>
</section>
<section id="workstream-2-r-tools-for-hta-identification-curation-and-education" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workstream-2-r-tools-for-hta-identification-curation-and-education">Workstream 2: R Tools for HTA – Identification, Curation, and Education</h2>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/MappingofHTA.png" class="img-fluid"> Gregory Chen and Joseph Rickert presented Workstream 2, which takes a hands-on approach toward bolstering R’s role in HTA. Key goals include identifying relevant R packages, curating high-quality, production-ready tools, and proactively enhancing documentation and user resources. The working group will also promote these tools through blogs, webinars, and other educational efforts to foster a culture of learning and improvement around R for HTA. The ultimate aim is to ensure that the HTA community has access to well-documented, robust R tools and resources that meet industry needs.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps-how-members-can-contribute" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps-how-members-can-contribute">Next Steps: How Members Can Contribute</h2>
<p>The HTA Working Group’s GitHub repository serves as the central hub for collaboration, providing access to meeting materials, discussion threads, and project updates. Members are encouraged to engage actively by commenting on<a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/HTA-wg">Issue #1</a> with a brief statement about their backgrounds, opening new issues to propose ideas, and suggesting solutions to emerging challenges. This repository promises to be a lively and evolving resource as the working group’s projects advance.</p>
</section>
<section id="group-discussion-setting-the-foundation-for-future-initiatives" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="group-discussion-setting-the-foundation-for-future-initiatives">Group Discussion: Setting the Foundation for Future Initiatives</h2>
<p>The group discussion allowed members to share insights, generate new ideas, and identify priorities for the working group’s next steps. The discussion was lively and constructive, underscoring the potential of this initiative to drive meaningful contributions to the HTA field.</p>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-meeting">Upcoming Meeting</h2>
<p>The next meeting of the HTA Working Group is scheduled for Wednesday, November 27, 2024, from 17:00 to 18:00 CET. Members are encouraged to join, contribute to ongoing discussions, and help shape the next steps of this impactful initiative. If you have not received an invitation, please reach out to <a href="mailto:joseph.rickert@gmail.com">Joseph Rickert via email</a>.</p>
<p>The HTA Working Group has set forth on a promising path, and this first meeting demonstrated the collaborative spirit and commitment to progress that will drive its success. Stay tuned for more updates as the group’s efforts take shape and begin to impact the HTA community.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/health-technology-assessment-hta-working-group-kickoff-meeting/OpeningRemarksandVision.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="68" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reviving Sheffield R User Group and Building Tools for Thyroid Cancer Prediction</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://blog.nshephard.dev/about.html">Neil Shephard</a>, co-organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/">Sheffield R User Group</a> in Sheffield, United Kingdom (also on <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@sheffieldr">fosstodon</a>), recently spoke to the R Consortium about his journey from Genetic Epidemiology to Research Software Engineering with R. He also discussed the revival of the Sheffield R User group and the challenges of organizing inclusive and hybrid events. Neil also highlighted the group’s successful participation in Hacktoberfest and shared insights into his current R projects, including developing tools for thyroid cancer prediction and deploying Shiny applications.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/NeilShephard.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I have a background in biology. I studied zoology and genetics at the undergraduate level and then pursued a master’s degree in genetic epidemiology, focusing on identifying genes involved in human diseases. Specifically, I worked on complex diseases such as rheumatoid arthritis and related autoimmune diseases initially and breast cancer. During my master’s program, I was taught programming and learned some C, although that was quite a long time ago, around 25 years ago. While I never really took to C programming, I was also introduced to the statistical package <a href="https://www.stata.com/">Stata</a>, which I found very user-friendly and appreciated its strong community support.</p>
<p>As time passed, I began to hear more and more about R. This was around 2000, a few years after R was first released. One of the things I had started doing was writing literate documents in <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a>. I would write a LaTeX document, and Stata could output tables to LaTeX, which I could then include in my document and render to PDF. I found this a much more efficient way to work reproducibly than traditional word processors and spreadsheets.</p>
<p>I was exploring R and discovered Friedrich Liesch’s package <a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/utils/doc/Sweave.pdf">Sweave</a>, which interweaved LaTeX and R code. It was really the precursor to RMarkdown. I also started using Linux as my operating system and became interested in the free open source software movement.</p>
<p>Around 2004 I made a conscious choice to switch from Stata to R because of its open source licensing and extensibility. While Stata allowed me to write my functions and modules, I found R more open as it isn’t owned by a company, and I didn’t need a license, which I typically relied on my employers to provide.</p>
<p>I decided to invest my time learning R for all my work because it would benefit me in the long run, as I could take the knowledge and skills and use them anywhere. When I switched careers from genetic statistician to medical statistician in a clinical trials unit at the University of Sheffield, I continued using R, although I was in a minority, as most colleagues at the time used Stata or SPSS.</p>
<p>I continued using R and convinced a few others to join me. We supported each other, and around 2015 the SheffieldR user group was initiated by <a href="https://annakrystalli.me/about/">Anna Krystalli</a>. I attended the meetings and found them really useful as they brought together people from the university and beyond who shared a passion for using R in their research, showing each other how they used R in their work. It was a great way to discover new features. I attended those meetings until around 2019, when I switched jobs to work for a startup tech company and switched to using Python and Java for work. Soon after, SheffieldR fizzled out due to lockdown in 2020.</p>
<p>After working for a tech company for a few years, I returned to the University of Sheffield as a Research Software Engineer, where I’m currently employed. This role has given me more opportunities to use R. I have been involved in a Python project from the beginning, but recently, I’ve also had the chance to work on a few R projects. I’ve missed the enjoyable and exciting R user group meetings that I used to attend.</p>
<p>I was asked to improve Sheffield’s RSE (Research Software Engineering) community. As part of this, I joined the <a href="https://osc-international.com/">open science community movement</a>, an international initiative that began in the Netherlands. They had an incubator program to establish open science communities in local areas, and I enrolled in that program to start an open science community in Sheffield. I’m quite a practical person and like to take action and help others, so I resolved to revive the Sheffield R user group as I had found it so useful in helping me learn what could be done with R earlier in my career.</p>
<p>I briefly worked with Anna, who had started the SheffieldR group, but unfortunately, soon after I started to work with the RSE Team, she <a href="https://www.r-rse.eu/">moved on</a> and became an R consultant. Still, we had some overlap, and she was happy to share all the materials and the <a href="https://github.com/SheffieldR">GitHub</a> repository for the website with me. So, I took on the responsibility of organizing the group. I rewrote the <a href="https://sheffieldr.github.io/">website</a> and switched it from <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a> to <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> to learn more about using Quarto, which had just been released. It wasn’t too difficult since the languages are pretty similar.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/SheffieldRUGs.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>Sheffield R User Group <a href="https://sheffieldr.github.io/posts/2024-04-22-april-meetup/">April 2024</a> Meetup “Profiling and Optimising your R code,” Speaker: Dan Brady, Research Software Engineer, University of Sheffield.</em></p>
<p>I was joined by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/grace-accad-9776b22b9/">Grace Accad</a> from the Data Analytics Service at the University of Sheffield to organize SheffieldR. She had been involved in R ladies and attended other R user groups, and I’ve been very grateful to her for her support and help in sharing the workload.</p>
<p>We have been hosting Sheffield R user group events for over a year, and they have been quite successful. We aim to hold the events every month during term time. I presented at our initial reboot session showing how to use <a href="https://ns-rse.github.io/SheffieldR-quarto-for-slides/#/title-slide">Quarto and GitHub pages to put slides online</a>, but we have been fortunate to find other speakers since then. However, Grace and I are primarily responsible for organizing and setting up the website and booking rooms. It’s not too demanding, but that’s my primary role in the group.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Sheffield? </strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/SheffieldJanuary2024.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>Sheffield R User Group January 2024 Meetup “<a href="https://sheffieldr.github.io/posts/2024-01-18-jan-meetup/">Automating Health Economic Evaluation with R</a>,” Speaker: Robert Smith, <a href="https://darkpeakanalytics.com/">Dark Peak Analytics</a>.</em></p>
<p>I only have a little industry experience, having only worked for one company. However, I think R is more academic, although that is changing. In Sheffield, the company I worked for had a research department with only two people. So, at least in Sheffield, R is used in the industry. The Sheffield R user group aims to bring together people who use R in the area to create a community where they can ask questions and help each other. A <a href="https://shef-ai.github.io/">data science learning community</a> in Sheffield used to be more R-oriented but now includes people using pandas. I like that community as well.</p>
<p>I strongly believe in the importance of connecting with people in person. The networking effect is natural and very beneficial. Building these connections and networks online while possible is more challenging, so I am focused on creating a local group to foster this. Most participants are from the University of Sheffield. However, there are also individuals from Sheffield Hallam University and outside academia, such as Simon Rolph from the UK Centre for Ecology and Hydrology, who gave an excellent talk on the <a href="https://sheffieldr.github.io/posts/2024-02-15/">targets package</a>. We’ve also had talks with <a href="https://sheffieldr.github.io/posts/2024-01-18-jan-meetup/">Robert Smith and Wael Mohammed</a> of Dark Peak Analytics.</p>
<p>One of my challenges is that I have a daughter, so I usually need to be home in the afternoons to take care of her. I appreciate that attending events in the evenings isn’t possible for everyone. Finding a suitable time for everyone is difficult. If we have meetings at lunchtime, we get a lot of university attendees, but only a few from farther away because they would have to travel. You can please some of the people sometimes, but you can’t please all the people all the time.</p>
<p><strong>Your group recently hosted <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sheffieldr-sheffield-r-users-group/events/?type=past">Hacktoberfest events.</a> Can you share more about the topic covered? Why this topic? </strong></p>
<p>Hacktoberfest celebrates open source software and encourages people to find their favorite open source project to contribute to. Our first meeting was on October 4th, and then we had one every other Friday throughout October.</p>
<p>The main objective was to help people get comfortable contributing to open source software, especially those who use R but may not be familiar with version control using Git and GitHub. In the first session, I used material from my job as a research software engineer, where I’ve been teaching a course Anna developed on using Git and GitHub for the past year or two. This course covers the basics of version control and includes a collaborative exercise using a GitHub repository.</p>
<p>Participants learned how to fork the repository, make changes locally, push their changes, and create pull requests. The following three weeks were dedicated to providing support, where others and I with experience in version control and using R were available to assist others. The goal was for people to help each other during this time and not rely solely on me or my colleagues as organizers, as some individuals may have more knowledge than others. It was great to see everyone coming together to support one another, as some people may have more expertise in specific areas than I do.</p>
<p><strong>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future? </strong></p>
<p>I have a GitHub issue template in place to help organize our meetings. I use GitHub to plan events because my memory is terrible. I’d likely forget something important if I didn’t have everything written down. Whenever we plan an event, we create a GitHub issue and assign it to me or Grace. It’s a checklist of tasks such as booking a room, setting dates and times, confirming speakers, obtaining consent for photography during the event, and listing places to advertise the event. This checklist helps us keep track of everything that needs to be done for each event.</p>
<p>The Sheffield R user group used to meet in a local pub. However, when we restarted the events, we decided that using more neutral spaces would be more inclusive, so we use university buildings now. We want to ensure everyone feels welcome, so we choose accessible venues for people with disabilities. It’s important to me that everyone can attend without any barriers.</p>
<p>We also run hybrid meetings, which I find challenging. When I have a group of people in the room, I naturally tend to speak to them. I have to remind myself to pay constant attention to the online participants. It’s helpful to have another organizer keeping an eye on the online side of things when people raise their hands. Despite the challenges, we continue with hybrid meetings because they’re a good way of allowing people to attend if they can’t make it in person.</p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</strong></p>
<p>I’m working on a project with a PhD student trying to improve thyroid cancer prediction. When he approached me, he used SPSS for his analysis because that’s what one of my old colleagues had taught him. From now on, I encouraged him to switch to using R for all his work, and I’ve helped him set up version control for it.</p>
<p>He has learned to write Quarto documents with embedded R code to write the manuscript he wants to create. This has been very useful. He has also learned how to use a multiple imputation package that he hadn’t used before to summarize the results and check their consistency with the observed data. At one point, the PhD student and his supervisor wanted to create a website where people could enter various characteristics about a patient and receive a risk profile indicating whether the lumps in their thyroids were likely to be malignant. To achieve this, he revisited his knowledge of <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/">Shiny</a> to get the website up and running. However, he was aware that it might be something they wanted to put into production. Consequently, he discovered the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/golem/index.html">Golem</a> package, which appears to be a handy tool for taking Shiny and developing it more rigorously for deployment to production. This has been the main focus of his recent work with R.</p>
<p>I’ve been using Quarto and R for my <a href="https://ns-rse.github.io/">blog</a> and some small tasks lately. I’ve written several posts about <a href="https://pre-commit.com">pre-commit</a> for linting code, which is really useful. I’m overdue writing one on how to use the <a href="https://lintr.r-lib.org/">lintr</a> package and should find time to investigate the newer <a href="https://flint.etiennebacher.com/">flint</a> package too.</p>
<p>I also had a project where the researchers used R and had a lot of code. I convinced them to organize their code into a more structured package format. I found <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/devtools/index.html">DevTools</a> and the <a href="https://usethis.r-lib.org/">usethis</a> package to be very helpful for that. At the same time, I set up the package repository to use <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/lintr/index.html">linter</a> to ensure that all coding standards were followed in case they ever decided to release it to <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/">CRAN</a>.</p>
<p>I feel like a jack of all trades because I use Python, R, and a bit of Bash. I know a little about everything, but I’m not an expert at any one thing!</p>
<p><strong>How do I Join?</strong></p>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 75,492 members in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reviving-sheffield-r-user-group-and-building-tools-for-thyroid-cancer-prediction/SheffieldRUGs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="98" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Streamlining API Integration: Jon Harmon’s Journey with the api2r Package</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/streamlining-api-integration-jon-harmons-journey-with-the-api2r-package/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonthegeek/">Jon Harmon</a>, Principal Data Solutions Engineer at Atorus, about his ISC-funded project, <em>api2r</em>. Jon’s extensive experience working with APIs from platforms like Slack, YouTube, and LinkedIn, along with his leadership of the Data Science Learning Community (DSLC.io), inspired him to develop <em>api2r</em> to simplify the process of wrapping APIs in R. The package streamlines the creation of R packages for various APIs by leveraging the OpenAPI standard, making it easier for developers to integrate external services into their R workflows.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/streamlining-api-integration-jon-harmons-journey-with-the-api2r-package/JonHarmon.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>Jon discusses the challenges he faced during the package’s development, particularly around authentication and endpoint setup, and how <em>api2r</em> differs from other tools like {httr2} and {paws}.</p>
<p>The R Consortium funded this project.</p>
<p><strong>What inspired you to create the api2r package, and how do you envision benefiting the R community?</strong></p>
<p>I run the <a href="dslc.io">Data Science Learning Community (DSLC) at dslc.io</a>, and through that, as well as some paid work, I frequently work with various APIs like Slack, YouTube, Zoom, LinkedIn, and different task management systems. I noticed that most of these are documented using the <a href="https://www.openapis.org/">OpenAPI Specification</a> or an older variant, which made it easier for me to read and write R code for them.</p>
<p>However, I found myself repeatedly looking up how I had done similar tasks before, which made me realize it would be much easier if I created a tool to streamline this process. Since I love writing R packages, it felt natural to pursue this idea.</p>
<p>In terms of how the R community could benefit, I want to make it easier for others to wrap APIs in R so people can create packages for whatever tasks they might need.</p>
<p><strong>Can you elaborate on the challenges you foresee in implementing authentication and endpoint calls in the initial milestone (version 0.1.0)?</strong></p>
<p>I’ve actually moved past the initial milestone of setting up authentication, but it definitely presented—and continues to present—challenges. First, I ended up splitting the package into three parts. There’s <em><a href="https://rapid.api2r.org/">rapid</a></em>, which parses API descriptions into a standard object, <em><a href="https://nectar.api2r.org/">nectar</a></em>, which wraps the <code>httr2</code> package to handle common tasks, and <em><a href="https://beekeeper.api2r.org/">beekeeper</a></em>, which is the main package. <em>Nectar</em> was particularly helpful because I was able to abstract the standard types of authentication into just a few simple wrappers. While <code>httr2</code> handles much of the heavy lifting, it doesn’t guide you through what you need to find in the documentation. That’s where <em>Nectar</em> steps in, helping streamline the setup process.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/streamlining-api-integration-jon-harmons-journey-with-the-api2r-package/beekeeperlogo.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>That said, there are still ongoing challenges. Many sites don’t fully or correctly implement the OpenAPI Specification, making it difficult to find the necessary information. Even when they do, details on how to obtain an API key can be tricky to track down. I spent a lot of time trying to address this issue, although there’s no perfect solution. Fortunately, after I wrote my grant application, a new version of <code>httr2</code> was released that simplifies a lot of these processes, which has been a big help.</p>
<p><strong>How does the api2r package aim to address the inconsistencies and inefficiencies in the current process of wrapping APIs into R packages?</strong></p>
<p>One thing I really wanted to focus on is the challenge of testing packages that wrap APIs. I’ve helped many people navigate this issue, as it’s easy for your package to get rejected from CRAN if the tests are not set up correctly or if they require an internet connection. To address this, I made sure that part of the automatic package building process includes generating a test suite that follows best practices for API testing.</p>
<p>With the <em>Nectar</em> package I mentioned earlier, it simplifies things by abstracting common setups—normally done with something like <code>httr2</code>—down to just what’s necessary, based on the API documentation. This creates a straightforward, one-to-one correspondence between what the API specifies and what you need to do, automatically generating a version of the package that handles this process smoothly.</p>
<p><strong>What are the key differences between the api2r package and other API-related tools like {httr}, {httr2}, and {paws}?</strong></p>
<p><em>Paws</em> is actually a family of packages designed specifically for working with Amazon Web Services (AWS) APIs, which is just one use case. The goal of the <em>API to R</em> family of packages I created is to make it easier to write packages like <em>Paws</em>. Essentially, <em>Paws</em> could be a package you’d create using my tools.</p>
<p>I extensively use <code><em>httr2</em></code> (the updated version of <code><em>httr</em></code>), which helps simplify writing API calls.</p>
<p>However, with <code><em>httr2</em></code>, you still have to manually piece everything together. The idea behind <em>API to R</em> is to take the API documentation and automatically build the <code><em>httr2</em></code> calls for you, eliminating the need to manually complete all the intermediate steps.</p>
<p><strong>How do you plan to engage the R community in the development and testing of the api2r package, and what role do you see for collaboration?</strong></p>
<p>I engage with many members of the R community on social media, primarily through <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@jonthegeek">Mastodon</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonthegeek/">LinkedIn</a>, where I share updates about the packages I’m working on, like <em>API to R</em>. I also maintain websites for these packages, and you can visit <a href="beekeeper.api2r.org">beekeeper.api2r.org</a> to find links to all of them. I keep everything up to date there.</p>
<p>As I mentioned earlier, I run the Data Science Learning Community at dslc.io, which now has over 19,000 members, with 400-500 active weekly. Most of our members are R users, and I regularly keep the group updated. We also host a monthly project club where members present their work, and I’ve presented about this project a few times. I’m also active on other R platforms like the ROpenSci Slack team and various Discord channels.</p>
<p>That being said, I’ve reached a point where I could use some help. I’d love for people to check out the GitHub repositories for these packages and share how they’re using them. If you encounter any bugs or have feedback, let me know. Just last week, I had an interaction on Mastodon where someone was working with a new API and asked if I could help. While we haven’t fully connected yet, I was able to send them the documentation to get started on creating the package and exploring what works and what doesn’t. It’s exciting to see where this could lead!</p>
<p><strong>What are your long-term goals for maintaining and expanding api2r, and how do you plan to ensure its sustainability in the R ecosystem?</strong></p>
<p>I strongly believe in developing everything openly, so the project is available on <a href="https://github.com/jonthegeek/beekeeper/tree/main">GitHub</a> for anyone to explore. You can access it from the website. Since it’s public, people are free to use it however they like. If I don’t take the project in the direction they prefer, they can fork it and work on their own version.</p>
<p>I also work closely with <a href="https://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</a> and other package developers to ensure that there’s a supportive community to keep things running. That said, if anyone is particularly interested in this package and its goals, I would really welcome an active collaborator or two to help manage and advance it. The standard we’re using—like the object version of the OpenAPI Specification—does evolve, and as APIs update, the package will need to adapt as well. My aim is to keep this project going long-term, and I don’t want it to rely entirely on me. Collaboration would be key to ensuring it grows and stays up to date.</p>
<p><strong>How has it been working with the R Consortium? Would you recommend applying for an ISC grant to other R developers?</strong></p>
<p>The R Consortium has been fantastic to work with—completely reasonable, transparent, and supportive at every step. The challenge for me, however, was that I seriously underestimated how much work this project would require. It wasn’t just about the difficulty; I also ended up going off on tangents that weren’t part of the original plan. Since the grant was milestone-based, there are still some milestones I haven’t reached, and that’s been tough to manage.</p>
<p>I definitely recommend applying for an ISC grant if you’re working on something, but I would advise being very careful with how you structure your proposal. I got a bit stuck in my details, and now I’m at a point where I have to find extra time to work on it. There’s still some grant money left, but not enough to fully cover the remaining work. So, I tend to work on the project when I have a specific use for it and can justify the time.</p>
<p>Overall, having the grant was incredibly helpful in giving me the time and space to explore this package, but it’s something to approach with caution regarding planning and execution.</p>
<section id="about-isc-funded-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-isc-funded-projects">About ISC Funded Projects</h2>
<p>A major goal of the R Consortium is to strengthen and improve the infrastructure supporting the R Ecosystem. We seek to accomplish this by funding projects that will improve both technical infrastructure and social infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/streamlining-api-integration-jon-harmons-journey-with-the-api2r-package/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/streamlining-api-integration-jon-harmons-journey-with-the-api2r-package/api2r-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="55" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>ConectaR, Podcasts, and Datathons: How the San Carlos R User Group in Costa Rica is Connecting Latin America’s Data Lovers</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/fransvandunne/">Frans van Dunné</a>, the organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/san-carlos-r-user-group/">San Carlos R User Group</a>, recently discussed with the R Consortium the development of the R community in Costa Rica and the broader Latin American (LATAM) region. He also talked about the growth of events such as the ConectaR conference and the success of the <a href="https://www.datalatam.com/">Data Latam podcast</a>, which he co-hosts to delve into data science in Latin America. Additionally, Frans highlighted the challenges of building a data-driven community in a rural area and the creative methods they’ve employed to connect people through R.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/FransvanDunne.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I have a background in biology, and during my PhD in tropical ecology, I encountered some statistical questions that I needed to solve through programming. That’s when I started learning to program, initially with Perl. Eventually, I discovered that I enjoyed solving data-related problems through programming, and that led me to R. It was around 2001 when I first started programming in R.</p>
<p>Eventually, I married and emigrated to Costa Rica (my wife is Tica). Knowing no one in the area, I started an R User Group to connect with people and navigate the area.</p>
<p>Very soon after arriving in Costa Rica, I established my town’s San Carlos R user group. Initially, we held our meetings in-person, but I soon discovered that some attendees traveled for hours by bus to reach San Carlos. Realizing the impracticality, I decided to move our meetings online, and to my surprise, it worked out well. This change occurred even before the pandemic, and we began to see people from Peru and other distant locations joining our group. San Carlos is a small rural area with a population of around 50,000, so having individuals from different parts of Latin America join us was truly amazing.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/SanCarlosRUGsmeeting.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>One of the first San Carlos R User Group meetings - February 2016, Ciudad Quesada, Costa Rica</em></p>
<p>We had to stop our online meetings because Meetup informed us that, according to their policy before the pandemic, we wouldn’t be able to use their platform if we didn’t hold physical meetings. The world is different now, but that was the situation back then.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the local R community is like in San Carlos? </strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/ConectaR2019.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants of ConectaR 2019 - January 2019, San José Costa Rica</em></p>
<p>We collaborated with the University of Costa Rica to organize an event that brought together industry, academia, and citizen science professionals for a conference focused on R. The event is called <a href="https://journal.r-project.org/news/RJ-2019-2-conectaR/">Conecta R</a>. We started in 2019 and held the latest edition this year, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/san-carlos-r-user-group/events/299265414/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Conecta R 2024</a>. When we started, we wanted to understand R’s current status and usage in the LATAM region. It only confirmed that R is widely used in academia. Most statistics courses have transitioned from licensed software to R. R is also used widely in industry.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/ConectaR2024.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants of the Tidymodels workshop during ConectaR 2024, March 2024, San José, Costa Rica</em></p>
<p>At <a href="https://www.ixpantia.com/en/">ixpantia</a>, the company I co-founded, we work with clients in various industries, such as consumer packaged goods, retail, oil and gas, and energy production. Additionally, a significant number of clients utilize our financial services.</p>
<p><strong>Would you like to tell us about your recent events?</strong></p>
<p>We’ve resumed our monthly online meetings for the San Carlos R user group. The meetings now take place on the first Saturday of the month in the morning, and anyone is welcome to join through Meetup.com. Our last meeting was held recently, and it was great to see familiar faces returning.</p>
<p>Additionally, we have a podcast called <a href="https://www.datalatam.com/">Data Latam</a>, which covers topics related to data science, not just R. We aim to release a new episode every month. We run this podcast in parallel with meetings, serving a similar purpose. It’s about providing examples and even role models of professionals working with data to show that you don’t need to be an IT professional or a programmer to work with data.</p>
<p><strong>Please share more about the Data Latam podcast. How did you come up with the idea of starting it? Would you like to highlight a few of your favorite podcasts from this series?</strong></p>
<p>The story behind the Data Latam podcast is funny. The co-host, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/diegohmay/">Diego May</a>, and I met through an R Package I wrote to access data from an open-data platform he had developed. We shared an interest in using data and data science to help the development of LATAM and agreed to start a podcast to get to know each other better. Within two months, we had the first opportunity to start a project, and that is when we founded ixpantia, which brings best practices in data science, data engineering, and data strategy to LATAM.</p>
<p>We have done 110 podcasts to date! It seems like a lot, but we learn so much from every conversation that it hardly feels like an effort. Some of my personal favorites that are related to R include Episode 109 with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/noamross/">Noam Ross</a>, where we talked about <a href="https://ropensci.org/">rOpenSci</a>, episode 98 with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sherlytarazonatocto/?originalSubdomain=pe">Sherly Tarazona</a> about her work and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/es/rladies-lima/">R-Ladies Lima</a>, episode 85 with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tareefk/">Tareef Kawaf</a> from Posit and episode 75 with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jaahumada/">Jorge Ahumada</a> about the work they do at <a href="https://www.wildlifeinsights.org/">Wildlife Insights</a>. I could go on, but pointing to the complete list at <a href="http://www.datalatam.com">www.datalatam.com</a> makes more sense. I’m sure there is something for everyone interested in data there.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future? </strong></p>
<p>Online events are great. I live in a rural area, and attending a physical event, even here in Costa Rica, requires a long three-hour drive to the capital. We have done that and will do it again, but having the option to go online is much more practical and has a broader reach.</p>
<p>When we started our first online meetings, we used Google Hangouts, which would fry my laptop after one hour. These tools have improved so much over the last few years, largely pushed by the boom in remote work during the pandemic. We still like <a href="https://www.zoom.com/">Zoom</a> and its functionality for setting up and executing events, including registration.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/ConectaR2024.png" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants of the Datathon 2019 in San Carlos, August 2019, Santa Clara, Costa Rica</em></p>
<p>We have organized two datathons (similar to a hackathon but focused on data) that were incredibly enjoyable and well-attended. The key to their success was our partnerships. One datathon was organized in collaboration with the Costa Rican government, and the other involved two local universities: The University of Costa Rica (UCR) and the Costa Rica Institute of Technology (TEC). I still meet people who attended these events and have fond memories of them.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 75,492 members in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/conectaR-podcasts-and-datathons-san-carlos-r-user-group-in-costa-rica/ConectaR2024.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="61" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
