<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Consortium</title>
<link>https://r-consortium.org/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://r-consortium.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.57</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Endophytes, Oaks, and R: How R-Ladies Morelia is Cultivating Science and Community in Morelia, Mexico</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/goretty-mendoza-785004322/">Goretty Mendoza</a>, the organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/es-ES/rladies-morelia/">R-Ladies Morelia</a>, recently spoke to the R Consortium about her experience with the group and her work using R in molecular biology. Under her guidance, the group has grown into a supportive space for women from diverse fields, focusing on building R skills, sharing knowledge, and fostering collaboration. Goretty is committed to empowering the local R community through online and physical events that encourage learning and networking.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/Goretty.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><strong><em>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</em></strong></p>
<p>I am a PhD student specializing in molecular biology, focusing on endophytic fungi. My work involves high-throughput sequencing, particularly amplicon sequencing, to study microbiomes.</p>
<p>I started using R during my PhD. Initially, I practiced independently through online courses, but then I discovered an R-Ladies community. The group was just starting in my city, so I took the opportunity to join. Attending the meetings helped me overcome my fear of working with R and allowed me to improve my skills. Gradually, I became more involved, and a few months ago, we had the opportunity to hold a face-to-face meeting with some members of our R-Ladies community who live in other cities, thanks to the R Consortium’s grant. I’m sure we returned home more motivated, knowing we all aim to improve our R skills.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/RLadiesMorelia.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the local R community is like? </strong></p>
<p>Our local R community is a group of enthusiastic women from various fields. Most of us come from science, mainly mathematics or biology, but we also have members from areas like finance or economics interested in learning R. At the start of each semester, we meet to share our interests and goals for the upcoming months. During our face-to-face meetings, we enjoy coffee and cookies, which create a welcoming atmosphere. A key focus of our group is ensuring that those with more experience in R share their knowledge with new members who are just starting. It creates an environment where everyone can learn and grow together. Our R-community is a great opportunity to get involved, collaborate with other women, and make new friends as we learn.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/r-ladies-morelia-zoom.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting related to your industry?</strong></p>
<p>I’m pursuing my PhD, and R is a tool I use almost daily. For example, I use R for a project involving the study of endophytic associations in different temperate oak species of Mexico. To this end, we initially explored the functional leaf traits of these oak species, and I had to learn different R packages for this project, such as data manipulation and visualization (e.g., <a href="https://dplyr.tidyverse.org/">dplyr</a> and <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot2</a>). Additionally, I used specialized packages like ‘<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/TPD/index.html">TPD</a>’ to calculate metrics related to functional diversity studies and ‘hypervolume’ to calculate climatic niches.</p>
<p>Our study aimed to determine if a functional niche partitioning between two evolutionary groups of oaks allowed them to coexist. We conducted a functional niche analysis and graphical visualization using R and the packages above. An interesting finding was that the analysis suggested differences in functional similarity among the groups, indicating evidence of functional niche partitioning and resource gradients.</p>
<p>These studies are crucial for conservation efforts and guide the development of management practices supporting temperate forests’ long-term health and resilience.</p>
<p><strong>What resources/techniques do/did you use? (Posit (RStudio), Github, Tidyverse, etc.)</strong></p>
<p><strong>Is this an ongoing project? Please share any details or CTA for who should get involved!</strong></p>
<p>Among the various R packages I used, some are for data manipulation and visualization, such as dplyr and ggplot2, and others more specialized, like TPD for calculating metrics used in functional diversity studies, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/hypervolume/index.html">hypervolume</a> for constructing functional niches, and <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ecospat/index.html">ecospat</a> to calculate climatic niche overlap indices.</p>
<p>We extensively utilized GitHub repositories, ensuring that all the scripts were well-documented to allow others to reproduce the analyses easily. Our ongoing project on endophytic fungi associated with oaks is crucial as a first approximation for understanding the complex interactions between fungi and their host plants.</p>
<p>The concept of hidden diversity is a novel and intriguing area that we are just beginning to explore. For those interested in diving deeper into this field, there are several ways to get involved. You can join professional networks in microbial ecology or engage with the field of computational biology through organizations and online communities. Additionally, participating in conferences, workshops, and collaborations with researchers and professionals in the field offers valuable opportunities to contribute to current research.</p>
<p><strong>What trends do you currently see in R language and your industry? Are there any trends you see developing in the near future?</strong></p>
<p>In metagenomics, one of the key trends is the development of massive datasets generated by next-generation sequencing (NGS). It has enabled a deeper and more detailed analysis of microbial communities and their diversity and functions. In this context, R remains an essential tool for statistical analysis and data visualization with specialized libraries like <a href="https://joey711.github.io/phyloseq/">phyloseq</a> and <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/vegan/index.html">vegan</a>.</p>
<p>However, given the complexity of metagenomic data, other programming languages like Python and <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/">Bash</a> are becoming indispensable. In the near future, the use of interdisciplinary workflows that combine R, Python and Bash will continue to grow, along with the development of more integrated tools to manage large datasets. Additionally, we can expect an increased use of artificial intelligence and machine learning to analyze these data.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/endophytes-oaks-and-r-how-r-ladies-morelia-is-cultivating-science-and-community-in-morelia-mexico/RLadiesMorelia-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="62" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The U.S. Federal Reserve quarterly model in R</title>
  <dc:creator>Guest Blog Post</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Guest Post contributed by Andrea Luciani, Bank of Italy, Directorate General for Economics, Statistics and Research, maintainer of the <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bimets">bimets</a> package (Time Series and Econometric Modeling) in CRAN</em></p>
<p>The US Federal Reserve’s econometric model for the US economy (i.e., FRB/US) is publicly available at <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/econres/us-models-about.htm">federalreserve.gov</a>. The website states, <em>“FRB/US is a large-scale estimated general equilibrium model of the US economy that was developed at the Federal Reserve Board, where it has been in use since 1996 for forecasting, analysis of policy options, and research projects.”</em></p>
<p>FRB/US is a quarterly model with hundreds of equations and variables. The model definition and time series data are available for download on the Federal Reserve website, as is the source code, which allows users to perform several econometric exercises. However, the Federal Reserve publicly distributes source codes only for EViews™ and python.</p>
<p>In this post, we show how to load the FRB/US model, and perform in R the same econometric exercises provided by the Federal Reserve.</p>
<section id="the-frbus-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-frbus-model">The FRB/US model</h2>
<p>The Federal Reserve website also states, <em>“Compared with DSGE models, however, FRB/US applies optimization theory more flexibly, which permits its equations to better capture patterns in historical data and facilitates modeling the economy in greater detail… A distinctive feature of FRB/US is its ability to switch between alternative assumptions about how economic agents form expectations. Under the VAR-based option, expectations are derived from the average historical dynamics of the economy as manifested in the predictions of estimated VAR models. Under model-consistent (MC), agents are assumed to form accurate expectations of future outcomes as generated by simulations of FRB/US itself.”</em></p>
<p>FRB/US is a quarterly model, and counts 284 equations and 365 variables (Feb.&nbsp;2024 version). The XML model definition is available for download on the Federal Reserve website, and contains, for each endogenous variable, the following information: the variable name, the variable definition with a short description, the economic sector the variable belongs to, the related equation in both EViews™ and python format, coefficients and exogenous variables involved in the equation.</p>
<p>64 endogenous variables are marked as stochastic and, during the stochastic simulation exercise, will be transformed by applying sequences of shocks as drawn randomly from their historical residuals.</p>
<p>14 endogenous variables belong to the MCE group (i.e., Model-Consistent Expectations) and have an alternative equation that contains forward-looking references.</p>
<p>Finally, at the end of the XML model definition, users can find additional information on economic sectors and exogenous variables involved in the model definition.</p>
</section>
<section id="moving-towards-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="moving-towards-r">Moving towards R</h2>
<p>FRB/US model definition is available to R users in the <code>FRB__MODEL</code> dataset of the <a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=bimets">bimets</a> package (bimets ver. 4.0.2, a software framework for time series analysis and econometric modeling):</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#load bimets</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(bimets)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#load FRB/US MDL definition</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data</span>(FRB__MODEL)</span>
<span id="cb2-3"></span>
<span id="cb2-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#print first 4 equations in model definition</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">cat</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">substring</span>(FRB__MODEL,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1615</span>))</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>MODEL

$DOWNLOADED FROM federalreserve.gov AND CONVERTED TO BIMETS MDL IN Feb, 2024

$FRB/US is a large-scale estimated general equilibrium model of the U.S. economy 
$that was developed at the Federal Reserve Board, where it has been in use since 1996 
$for forecasting, analysis of policy options, and research projects. 

$--------------------------------------------------------------------------

$ ENDOGENOUS SECTION

$-----------------------------------------------
$Financial Sector
$Monetary policy indicator for both thresholds
$DMPTMAX equals one when either the unemployment threshold or
$the inflation threshold is breached.
IDENTITY&gt; dmptmax
IF&gt; dmptlur&gt;=dmptpi
EQ&gt; dmptmax=
dmptlur
IDENTITY&gt; dmptmax
IF&gt; dmptlur&lt;dmptpi
EQ&gt; dmptmax=
dmptpi

$-----------------------------------------------
$Federal funds rate, first diff
IDENTITY&gt; delrff
EQ&gt; delrff=
TSDELTA(rff)

$-----------------------------------------------
$Financial Sector
$Monetary policy indicator for unemployment threshold
$DMPTLUR equals zero when the unemployment rate is above its
$threshold (LURTRSH) one when it is below. A logistic function
$smoothes the transition, improving solution convergence properties.
IDENTITY&gt; dmptlur
EQ&gt; dmptlur=
1/(1+EXP(25*(lur-lurtrsh)))

$-----------------------------------------------
$Financial Sector
$Monetary policy indicator for inflation threshold
$DMPTPI equals zero when expected inflation is below its threshold
$and one when it is above. A logistic function smoothes the
$transition, improving solution convergence properties.
IDENTITY&gt; dmptpi
EQ&gt; dmptpi=
1/(1+EXP(-25*(zpic58-pitrsh)))</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="dynamic-simulation-in-a-monetary-policy-shock" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dynamic-simulation-in-a-monetary-policy-shock">Dynamic simulation in a monetary policy shock</h2>
<p>The first econometric exercise proposed by the Federal Reserve is a dynamic simulation of the FRB/US model under a monetary policy shock. The simulation is operated from 2040-Q1 to 2045-Q4, after the <code>rffintay</code> time series, defined as <em>“Value of eff. federal funds rate given by the inertial Taylor rule”</em>, is shocked by 100 base points in 2040-Q1.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Load data</span></span>
<span id="cb4-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data</span>(LONGBASE)</span>
<span id="cb4-3"></span>
<span id="cb4-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Load model</span></span>
<span id="cb4-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">data</span>(FRB__MODEL)</span>
<span id="cb4-6">model <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">LOAD_MODEL</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">modelText =</span> FRB__MODEL)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>Analyzing behaviorals...
Analyzing identities...
Optimizing...
Loaded model "FRB__MODEL":
    0 behaviorals
  284 identities
    0 coefficients
...LOAD MODEL OK</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Load data into model</span></span>
<span id="cb6-2">model <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">LOAD_MODEL_DATA</span>(model, LONGBASE, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">quietly=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span>)</span>
<span id="cb6-3"></span>
<span id="cb6-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Specify dates</span></span>
<span id="cb6-5">start <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2040</span>,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>)</span>
<span id="cb6-6">end <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">normalizeYP</span>(start<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">23</span>),<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4</span>)</span>
<span id="cb6-7"></span>
<span id="cb6-8"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Standard configuration, use surplus ratio targeting</span></span>
<span id="cb6-9">model<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>modelData<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>dfpdbt[[start,end]] <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb6-10">model<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>modelData<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>dfpsrp[[start,end]] <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb6-11"></span>
<span id="cb6-12"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Solve to baseline with adds</span></span>
<span id="cb6-13">model <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">SIMULATE</span>(model,</span>
<span id="cb6-14">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">simType=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'RESCHECK'</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-15">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TSRANGE=</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(start,end),</span>
<span id="cb6-16">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ZeroErrorAC =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-17">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">quietly=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span>)</span>
<span id="cb6-18"></span>
<span id="cb6-19"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># 100 bp monetary policy shock</span></span>
<span id="cb6-20">trac <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> model<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>ConstantAdjustmentRESCHECK</span>
<span id="cb6-21">trac<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>rffintay[[start]] <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> trac<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>rffintay[[start]]<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb6-22"></span>
<span id="cb6-23"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Solve</span></span>
<span id="cb6-24">model <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">SIMULATE</span>(model,</span>
<span id="cb6-25">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">simAlgo =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'NEWTON'</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-26">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TSRANGE =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">c</span>(start,end),</span>
<span id="cb6-27">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ConstantAdjustment =</span> trac,</span>
<span id="cb6-28">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">BackFill =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">12</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-29">                  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">quietly=</span><span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>R code produces the following charts:</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/FRB_R_1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On the other hand, the python code provided by the US Federal Reserve produces very similar results:</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/FRB_python_1.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="stochastic-simulation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stochastic-simulation">Stochastic simulation</h2>
<p>Another econometric exercise proposed by the Federal Reserve is a stochastic simulation of the FRB/US model. The <code>stochsim</code> procedure in the <code>pyfrbus</code> python package (available on the Federal Reserve web site) performs a stochastic simulation by applying sequences of shocks to 64 endogneous variables of the model, as drawn randomly from historical residuals. In a similar way in R, the <code>STOCHSIMULATE</code> procedure allows users to shock the same endogenous variables with randomly sampled historical residuals.</p>
<p>R code, omitted for brevity, produces the following charts:</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/FRB_R_5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>On the other hand, the python code provided by the US Federal Reserve produces very similar results, despite the random numbers generator being different between R and python:</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/FRB_python_5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="section" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="section">________________</h2>
<p>Additional exercises, e.g., rational expectations, endogenous targeting, etc., and computational details are available in the package vignette <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=bimets/vignettes/frb2bimets.pdf">The U.S. Federal Reserve quarterly model in R with bimets</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/us-federal-reserve-quarterly-model-in-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empowering Dengue Research Through the Dengue Data Hub: R Consortium Funded Initiative</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-dengue-research-through-the-dengue-data-hub/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-dengue-research-through-the-dengue-data-hub/DengueDataHub.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/thiyangt/denguedatahub">Dengue Data Hub</a>, an ambitious initiative funded by the R Consortium ISC, transforms how researchers access and utilize dengue-related data. At its core, the Dengue Data Hub aims to provide a centralized repository for dengue incidence, mortality, and risk-related data, streamlining the research process and empowering scientific inquiry into this global health issue. The platform offers easy access through the denguedatahub R package, a Shiny app, and an informative website, making data analysis more efficient and accessible.</p>
<p>Please note: <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/denguedatahub/index.html">denguedatahub version 2.1.1</a> was published on CRAN on Sep 22, 2024.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thiyanga-talagala-24bb63134/">Dr.&nbsp;Thiyanga Talagala</a>, a Senior Lecturer at the University of Sri Jayewardenepura in Sri Lanka, spearheads this initiative. With a PhD from Monash University, where she honed her skills in R programming and data science, Dr.&nbsp;Talagala is deeply passionate about leveraging her expertise to address Sri Lanka’s public health challenges, particularly dengue. Together with her sister, Dr.&nbsp;Priyanga Talagala, she co-founded the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-colombo/">R-Ladies Colombo group</a> and has been instrumental in bringing innovative solutions to the scientific community. Dr.&nbsp;Talagala’s commitment to enhancing dengue research through accessible data resources is central to her ongoing work, making the Dengue Data Hub a vital tool for researchers worldwide.</p>
<p><strong>Tell us about your background and how it connects to the Dengue Data Hub project</strong></p>
<p>Currently, I am working as a Senior Lecturer, Department of Statistics, Faculty of Applied Sciences, University of Sri Jayewardenepura, Sri Lanka. I earned my PhD from Monash University, Australia. During my time at Monash University in Australia, I was part of the NUMBAT research group, where I developed a deep interest in the R programming language and discovered its incredible potential for data analysis and research. I also had the opportunity to meet and collaborate with leading experts in the field, which further fueled my passion for R and data science. I also got to know about the R Ladies community, and I attended events organized by R-Ladies Melbourne.</p>
<p>Once I returned to Sri Lanka after completing my PhD, I felt a strong desire to contribute to my country using the knowledge I had gained. I, along with my Sister, Dr Priyanga Dilini Talagala (we both did our PhDs together at Monash University), established the R Ladies Colombo meetup group.</p>
<p>Dengue is a major public health issue in Sri Lanka. As a data scientist, I can contribute to its mitigation by establishing a centralized repository for dengue data for data analysis and modeling, which empowers dengue research. This project was funded by <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/2022-group-1.html#dengue-data-hub">R Consortium ISC 2022 - 1 Grant</a> and I have been working on it since 2022.</p>
<p><strong>What is the Dengue Data Hub?</strong></p>
<p>The Dengue Data Hub is a centralized repository that provides access to a variety of data sets related to dengue incidence and other relevant factors. This includes data on dengue deaths, reported cases, indigenous cases, local cases, dengue serotypes, breeding sites, and country-wise levels of risk. I have data related to annual dengue incidence for 195 countries around the world.</p>
<p><strong>Why is this project important for the research community?</strong></p>
<p>Dengue researchers often spend their valuable time searching for datasets, web scraping and cleaning data. The publication of data in a centralized repository helps to prevent duplicate efforts. The dengue data hub enables the community to focus on analysis and modeling rather than data collection and cleaning. Additionally, it enhances research sustainability by allowing researchers to utilize data for their studies while preserving it for future researchers.</p>
<p><strong>How do researchers use the Dengue Data Hub?</strong></p>
<p>There are three straightforward ways for anyone to participate. Use the denguedatahub R software package, use the Dengue Data Hub Shiny app (for non-programmers), or use our website which provides tutorials and examples.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Use the denguedatahub R software package.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-dengue-research-through-the-dengue-data-hub/denguedatahub-package.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The denguedatahub R package allows researchers to download dengue-related data easily. For Sri Lanka, it includes web scraping functions that directly retrieve weekly epidemiological reports published by the Epidemiology Unit, Ministry of Health, Sri Lanka. This functionality also cleans the data into a tidy format. Additionally, the package offers various data manipulation functions tailored for dengue data visualization and modeling. You can find the package on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/thiyangt/denguedatahub">https://github.com/thiyangt/denguedatahub</a>.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Dengue Data Hub Shiny app</li>
</ol>
<p>The Shiny app provides an interface for non-programmers to access dengue data. It is available at: <a href="https://denguedatahub.shinyapps.io/denguedatahub/">https://denguedatahub.shinyapps.io/denguedatahub/</a></p>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Website (<a href="https://denguedatahub.netlify.app/">https://denguedatahub.netlify.app/</a>)</li>
</ol>
<p>This website is the home for the projects. It provides tutorials and examples. The site was developed using Quarto.</p>
<p><strong>What impact do you hope the Dengue Data Hub will have?</strong></p>
<p>My hope is that the Dengue Data Hub will become a go-to resource for dengue researchers globally. I believe the hub will accelerate dengue research and discoveries which will help in developing effective strategies to combat dengue. The dengue data hub also serves as a</p>
<p>teaching tool for data science and statistics, as it includes comprehensive data sets.</p>
<p><strong>Do you have any final thoughts or messages you’d like to share with the research community?</strong></p>
<p>I invite dengue researchers worldwide to collaborate on this project. I do not have access to clinical trial data, so contributions in that area would be especially valuable. We are looking to expand the datasets available, as comprehensive data sharing is essential for advancing our collective understanding of dengue epidemiology. Additionally, we welcome contributions of data, analytical tools, and insights that can help strengthen the hub’s capacity to serve as a central resource for researchers globally.</p>
<p>You can learn more about how to collaborate <a href="https://denguedatahub.netlify.app/collaborate.html">here.</a> We can build a stronger network to enhance dengue research and response efforts worldwide.</p>
<section id="about-isc-funded-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-isc-funded-projects">About ISC Funded Projects</h2>
<p>A major goal of the R Consortium is to strengthen and improve the infrastructure supporting the R Ecosystem. We seek to accomplish this by funding projects that will improve both technical infrastructure and social infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-dengue-research-through-the-dengue-data-hub/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-dengue-research-through-the-dengue-data-hub/DengueDataHub.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R/Pharma 2024, Virtual, October 29-November 1, Includes New Dedicated Asia-Pacific (APAC) Track</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/rpharma-apac-main-image.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>R/Pharma 2024 is coming up Oct 29-Nov 1, 2024. This is a free event, fully virtual. R users in Pharma around the world are encouraged to attend, ask questions, and contribute their opinions!</p>
<section id="register-now-for-free" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="register-now-for-free"><a href="https://events.zoom.us/ev/AvobJEOTVwkUnH6_TgLZDZJauk4dxfm5jCG8JFNN9zukOcsVLvTN~AmO5XY5HRBcxkKG6Hga1aXZaYtpBSER6jHms1seP-NNOA0dhcQZUGJ2NWg">Register now for free!</a></h2>
<p>For the first time, R/Pharma will be including a dedicated Asia-Pacific (APAC) track which better aligns with Asian time zones and includes 2 pre-conference workshops, 3 keynotes that will be recorded from the global track and then streamed with live discussion sessions thereafter, and 2 live panels, one focusing on Japan, and one on China. In addition, there are 20 contributed talks.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/rpharma-china-panel.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/rpharma-japan-panel.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium talked with Daniel Sabanés Bové, R/Pharma organizer, co-chair of openstatsware.org, co-founder of RCONIS, a biostatistics consulting and software engineering firm, (co-)author of multiple R packages published on CRAN and Bioconductor, and author of the book “Likelihood and Bayesian Inference: With Applications in Biology and Medicine.” Daniel is giving a 3-hour workshop on October 27 with Joe Zhu (Roche) on “Good Software Engineering Practice for R Packages,” and introducing openstatsware in a talk on 31 October.</p>
<p>We talked to Daniel to find out more about the new APAC track.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/daniel.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="why-is-rpharma-adding-an-apac-track-now" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-is-rpharma-adding-an-apac-track-now">Why is R/Pharma adding an APAC track now?</h3>
<p>Last year, I was on an extended business trip for Roche for 6 weeks in Shanghai. I was fortunate to attend the first China Pharma R User Group (RUG) Meeting in March 2023, so I have seen how active the community is. I also found out how tough it can be to be based in Asia - you just don’t get enough sleep working with colleagues in Europe and North America!</p>
<p>So when the R/Pharma program committee reported that they have been approached by colleagues in Asia about organizing events in their time zone or region, I used the opportunity of my upcoming move to Taipei mid 2024 to propose organizing a dedicated track in the Asia-Pacific timezones.</p>
<p>The R/Pharma APAC track is designed specifically to help avoid time zone burnout, as well as to foster the APAC regional community.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-does-adoption-of-r-in-pharma-in-apac-differ-from-other-parts-of-the-world" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-does-adoption-of-r-in-pharma-in-apac-differ-from-other-parts-of-the-world">How does adoption of R in Pharma in APAC differ from other parts of the world?</h3>
<p>This is not based on robust data, but from a personal perspective I have noticed one key feature is that biotech and Pharma companies in Asia are concentrated in a few hubs, there is Shanghai, Tokyo, and not too many more. Having said that, I have noticed the rise of Contract Research Organizations (CROs) e.g.&nbsp;in India that are starting to use R - the CROs are catching up. Compare that to Europe and the United States, with a wide range of Pharma companies and organizations spread around many different locations. This also influences the adoption of R and open source technologies in general.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-some-of-the-key-topics-being-covered-in-the-apac-track" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-some-of-the-key-topics-being-covered-in-the-apac-track">What are some of the key topics being covered in the APAC track?</h3>
<p>I was pleasantly surprised at the amount and variety of proposals submitted. We have organized the APAC track’s topics into 6 types of sessions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Change management (moving from proprietary software to R)</li>
<li>Sessional clinical reporting (producing tables and reports)</li>
<li>Shiny</li>
<li>Best practices</li>
<li>AI/ML</li>
<li>High dimensional data</li>
</ul>
<p>We have quite an exciting APAC Track program that includes:</p>
<ul>
<li>2 pre conference workshops</li>
<li>3 keynote streams, which are recorded keynotes that are slightly delayed to stream during convenient APAC times, plus we have added some discussion after</li>
<li>2 live panel discussion (China, Japan)</li>
<li>20 contributed talks in total</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="full-agenda" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-agenda">Full Agenda</h3>
<p>A full list of workshops, keynotes, talks and panels is available <a href="https://events.zoom.us/ev/AvobJEOTVwkUnH6_TgLZDZJauk4dxfm5jCG8JFNN9zukOcsVLvTN~AmO5XY5HRBcxkKG6Hga1aXZaYtpBSER6jHms1seP-NNOA0dhcQZUGJ2NWg">here</a>.</p>
<p>If you use the filter button you can get just the APAC Track information.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/filter.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/filter-apac.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="register-now-for-free-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="register-now-for-free-1"><a href="https://events.zoom.us/ev/AvobJEOTVwkUnH6_TgLZDZJauk4dxfm5jCG8JFNN9zukOcsVLvTN~AmO5XY5HRBcxkKG6Hga1aXZaYtpBSER6jHms1seP-NNOA0dhcQZUGJ2NWg">Register now for free!</a></h2>
<p>If you, or your organization, would like to support R/Pharma you can do so following <a href="https://www.pledge.to/r-pharma">this link</a>. Be sure to follow the R/Pharma <a href="https://rinpharma.com/post/">blog</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/open-source-in-pharma">LinkedIn</a> and <a href="https://x.com/rinpharma">Twitter/X</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rpharma-2024-virtual-oct29-nov1-apac-track/rpharma-apac-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="71" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using R to Submit Research to the FDA: Pilot 4 Successfully Submitted to FDA Center for Drug Evaluation and Research</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/webR-shiny.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium is excited to announce that, on September 20, 2024, the R Submissions Working Group successfully submitted its latest test submission package—featuring a WebAssembly component—through the FDA’s Electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD) gateway! This marks a significant milestone as the FDA Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER) staff has officially received the submission package.</p>
<p>Statistician Eric Nantz at pharmaceuticals company Eli Lilly in Indianapolis, Indiana, says that using WebAssembly “will minimize, from the reviewer’s perspective, many of the steps that they had to take to get the application running on their machines.”</p>
<p>The complete set of submission materials is available publicly on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot4-webR-to-fda">R Consortium Submissions Pilot 4.</a></p>
<section id="about-the-pilot-4-project" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-the-pilot-4-project">About the Pilot 4 Project</h2>
<p>The objective of the R Consortium R submission <em>Pilot 4 </em>Project is to explore the use of novel technologies such as Linux containers and WebAssembly to bundle a Shiny application into a self-contained package, facilitating a smoother process of both transferring and executing the application. The application was built using the source data sets and analyses contained in the R submission <em>Pilot 1-3</em>. To our knowledge, this is the first publicly available submission package that includes a WebAssembly component. We hope this submission package and what we have learned can serve as a good reference for future regulatory submission efforts. The WebAssembly technology compiles applications into a portable, consistent environment driven by a web browser, allowing agency reviewers to easily run and evaluate software without complex setups. The second half of the Pilot 4 Project (leveraging container technology to package a Shiny application) will be submitted as an additional package later this year. Additional agency feedback will be shared in future communications.</p>
</section>
<section id="about-the-r-submissions-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-the-r-submissions-working-group">About the R Submissions Working Group</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">R Consortium R Submissions Working Group</a> is focused on improving practices for R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions.</p>
<p>Health authority agencies from different countries require electronic submission of data, computer programs, and relevant documentation to bring an experimental clinical product to market. In the past, submissions have mainly been based on the SAS language.</p>
<p>In recent years, the use of open source languages, especially the R language, has become very popular in the pharmaceutical industry and research institutions. Although the health authorities accept submissions based on open source programming languages, sponsors may be hesitant to conduct submissions using open source languages due to a lack of working examples.</p>
<p>Therefore, the R Submissions Working Group aims to provide R-based submission examples and identify potential gaps while submitting these example packages. All materials, including submission examples and communications, are publicly available on the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium">R consortium GitHub page.</a></p>
</section>
<section id="join-the-r-submissions-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="join-the-r-submissions-working-group">Join the R Submissions Working Group</h2>
<p>The R Submissions Working Group comprises members from over 10 pharmaceutical companies, as well as regulatory agencies. We are a collaborative community open to anyone interested in contributing to this important work. For more information, or to get involved, visit<a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg">our website</a> or contact us directly at director@r-consortium.org.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/webR-shiny.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="96" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Cakes, Code, and Community: Rasmus Bååth’s Secret to Reviving the CopenhagenR UseR Group</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rasmus-baath/">Rasmus Bååth</a>, the organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/copenhagenr-user-group/">CopenhagenR UseR Group</a>, recently spoke to the R Consortium about his experience in organizing the group. After joining the Copenhagen R User Group in 2013, he took the lead in reviving the group in 2023 after a period of inactivity. Under his guidance, the group now focuses on industry-related topics, personal projects, and emerging tools like Quarto. Rasmus is dedicated to fostering a vibrant local R community through in-person meetups that encourage learning and collaboration.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/rasmus-baath.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The CopenhagenR UseR Group is hosting an exciting “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/copenhagenr-user-group/events/303309816/">Two Tools for Report Generation in R</a>” event on October 3, 2024. The event will feature two presentations on using Sweave and Quarto for report generation, followed by discussions and networking at <a href="https://www.prosa.dk/">PROSA</a>, København, Denmark.</p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I currently work as a Data Science Manager at Normative.io. I’ve used R on and off for about 15 or 16 years. It all started when I was doing my bachelor’s in academia and needed to plot a histogram. At that time, plotting a histogram in Excel wasn’t easy, so my supervisor suggested trying out R. I gave it a shot and got hooked. After that, I pursued a PhD in cognitive science, where I used R extensively for statistical analysis.</p>
<p>I used R for a lot of graphing during my academic years. After academia, I became a data scientist in the industry, and R was my preferred tool. I work with R and Python, depending on the job’s requirements. In 2013, there were no R meetups in the south of Sweden where I live. I found out about an R meetup in Copenhagen and decided to attend. There, I met <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kennethrose82/">Kenneth Rose</a>, the organizer, who was full of energy and charisma. It was a fun group, so I started attending regularly despite the commute from Sweden to Copenhagen. Kenneth was very active and enthusiastic in running the meetup group.</p>
<p>After a couple of years, the group’s activity declined. A new organizer revived the group, but COVID hit, ending the meetups. The group had been around for ten years by 2023, and I felt it was a shame to let it die. I decided to restart it, and now we have a small but active group. We enjoy discussing industry-related topics and personal projects.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/copenhangenr-meetup.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the local R community is like?</strong></p>
<p>It is the Copenhagen meetup group located in Denmark. However, I can speak for Denmark and Sweden since I live in Sweden. R is widely used in academia and is considered the language of choice for statistics. Python is more prevalent in the industry due to the large number of programmers who are familiar with the language. In Denmark, the pharmaceutical industry is significant. R is still widely used there due to its close ties to academia and the specific requirements for reporting, statistics, and visualization, in which R excels.</p>
<p><strong>Do you guys host online or in-person events?</strong></p>
<p>During the COVID-19 pandemic, we tried some online events, but creating a sense of community online with so much content is challenging. I believe online events are great, and people should consider them. However, we also recognize the need for in-person events. For those unable to attend, there is plenty of valuable content online. We don’t have the setup to record events, but we would consider doing so if feasible.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/copenhangenr-meetup2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>You have a Meetup titled “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/copenhagenr-user-group/events/303309816/">Two tools for report generation in R</a>.” Can you share more on the topic covered? Why this topic?</strong></p>
<p>Our next meetup will focus on automatic reporting in R. We’ll have two speakers: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dperepolkin/">Dmytro Perepolkin</a> and an anonymous speaker. The anonymous speaker will present on <a href="https://rpubs.com/YaRrr/SweaveIntro">Sweave</a>, an older tool used to generate reports in R, while Dmytro will present on <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, a more recent and popular tool for combining R code and text. This meetup will depart from the usual topics, focusing on automatic reporting rather than visualization.</p>
<p>I’m looking forward to our upcoming event. It will be a history lesson and a great opportunity to learn about a useful minimalistic tool (Sweave). I’m also excited about Quarto and the potential for new developments. We could have a Quarto meetup every year to stay updated with the latest advancements. The meetup will feature different presentations, including introductions to new tools and discussions about projects and code. It will be a great way to learn and connect with others in the field.</p>
<p><strong>What are some of the popular R-related topics in the group?</strong></p>
<p>The topics we typically cover are where R is at its strongest. We often discuss personal projects, and although I wonder if they receive a great response, I love them. Additionally, we frequently explore new tools and libraries, particularly those related to dashboarding, Shiny, and visualization. Presentations are highly technical, and I’ve noticed that our audience may not be accustomed to text-heavy or math-intensive presentations. Therefore, topics such as statistics and statistics packages might not receive as much attention despite my interest in them. Surprisingly, machine learning is not a common focus at our meetups, as most speakers are more inclined towards visualization, reporting, and statistics rather than machine learning.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/copenhangenr-meetup3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (GitHub, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>There are three key components needed to get started with organizing an event. First, you need people who are interested in attending your event. It can be challenging if you’re in a small town or a location where it’s difficult to attract attendees. Second, you need to secure speakers who are willing to participate. Lastly, finding a suitable venue is crucial. Having a reliable and cost-free location for your event is essential. We were fortunate to secure a free venue through a union for IT workers in Copenhagen, which aligns with our goal of offering free courses without being tied to a specific company.</p>
<p>Finding speakers can be challenging, but constantly contacting and asking for volunteers is the best approach. To make it easier for potential speakers, consider organizing events where multiple speakers can do shorter presentations, which may be less intimidating than a full-hour presentation. However, attracting speakers and attendees remains the most difficult aspect of organizing events. Nevertheless, securing a dependable venue is a great starting point.</p>
<p>And then there are some small things. Make sure to make nice announcements. They need a nice picture. They need friendly text so that people feel welcome. That’s the minimal thing. And the other thing is, if it’s allowed in the meetup space, bring some cakes or cookies and have some snacks. If people know there will be a little bit of snacks, they’re more likely to show up. So it’s a small thing, but I think that helps. This meetup is in Copenhagen, and I’m from Sweden. However, Denmark and Copenhagen have a special relationship with beer. I distinctly remember my first Copenhagen meetup when Kenneth Rose was the organizer. Back then, he brought a big case of beer cans to each meetup, and everyone was having a nice time. I don’t say you need a beer at your meetup, but bringing drinks and snacks is always nice.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">Learn More!</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/cakes-code-and-community-reviving-the-copenhagenr-user-group/copenhangenr-meetup3.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="99" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Announcing the Health Technology Assessment (HTA) Working Group</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/announcing-health-technology-assessment-HTA-working-group/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The R Consortium is pleased to announce a new Working Group (WG) focused on Health Technology Assessment (HTA). The HTA WG has a mission of promoting the use of R in all aspects of HTA analytics, including both clinical assessment and economic evaluation. It aims to build on the success of other R Consortium working groups in bringing together and promoting dialogue between the broadest range of stakeholders from the HTA ecosystem (industry, HTA bodies, academics and others) to identify needs and address challenges through practical tools and pilot exercises. Health Technology Assessment (HTA) helps decision-makers determine which medical technologies and treatments are effective and worth paying for. It can help ensure that the right treatments reach the right patients at the right time by assessing clinical evidence and economic evaluations to inform policy-making about reimbursement and market access.</p>
<p>Recent policy changes, such as the EU HTA Regulation, require pharmaceutical companies to face stricter standards and shorter deadlines for submitting evidence. At the same time, HTA authorities must review an increasing number of complex analyses under the pressure for timely evidence-based decisions. Lastly, there is pressure on academia to provide easy-to-use HTA software and tools.</p>
<p>Initially, the WG will focus on the following objectives.</p>
<ul>
<li>Foster Collaboration and Knowledge Sharing:
<ul>
<li>Understanding the needs of all stakeholders for HTA analytics, and where the use of R may best fit.</li>
<li>Promote the common goal of delivering HTA analytics work that meets those needs and efficiently utilizes R.</li>
<li>Become a central hub for connecting existing and new R initiatives in the HTA space, ensuring efficient and unified efforts.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Develop and Document Best Practices:
<ul>
<li>Develop and disseminate best practices for using R in HTA analytics work for clinical and economic evaluation.</li>
<li>Promote transparency and reproducibility in HTA analytics work.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Explore Pilot Studies with HTA authorities
<ul>
<li>Explore pilot studies to test and refine open source R-based tools and frameworks for clinical and economic evaluation.</li>
<li>Pursue collaborative efforts with HTA authorities to validate these tools, demonstrating their value in real-world HTA scenarios.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>If you think any of this is exciting and would like to become involved, please leave your name and email in <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/HTA-wg/issues/1">issue number 1</a> at the HTA GitHub repository.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/announcing-health-technology-assessment-HTA-working-group/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/announcing-health-technology-assessment-HTA-working-group/hta-main-page.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="50" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Unlocking Chemical Volatility: How the volcalc R Package is Streamlining Scientific Research</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/unlocking-chemical-volatility-how-the-volcalc-r-package-is-streamlining-scientific-research/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unlocking-chemical-volatility-how-the-volcalc-r-package-is-streamlining-scientific-research/volcalc.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed <a href="https://datascience.cct.arizona.edu/person/kristina-riemer">Kristina Riemer</a>, director of <a href="https://datascience.cct.arizona.edu/">the CCT Data Science Team</a> at the University of Arizona, and <a href="https://datascience.cct.arizona.edu/person/eric-scott">Eric Scott</a>, Scientific Programmer and Educator in the CCT Data Science Team, the developers behind the <a href="https://github.com/Meredith-Lab/volcalc">volcalc package</a>, to discuss the motivation and development of this innovative tool designed to automate the calculation of chemical compound volatilities. volcalc streamlines the process by allowing users to input a compound and quickly receive its volatility information, eliminating the need for time-consuming manual calculations. Initially created to assist <a href="https://has.arizona.edu/person/laura-meredith">Dr.&nbsp;Laura Meredith</a> in managing a large database of volatile compounds, volcalc has since grown into a more versatile tool under Eric’s leadership, now supporting a wider range of researchers.</p>
<p>Kristina and Eric share insights into the challenges they faced, including managing dependencies, integrating with CRAN and Bioconductor, and refining complex molecular identification methods. They also discuss future enhancements, such as incorporating temperature-specific volatility calculations and expanding the package’s functionality to estimate other compound characteristics. This project was funded by the R Consortium.</p>
<p><strong>Could you share what motivated the development of the volcalc package and how it aligns with the broader goals of the R ecosystem, particularly in scientific computing?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Kristina</strong>: I was heavily involved in the initial development of volcalc, and later on, Eric took over the project. We developed volcalc because we began collaborating with Dr.&nbsp;Laura Meredith, who was compiling a database of volatile chemical compounds. At the time, she had around 300 compounds, and her students manually gathered details for each one by examining their representations and calculating various associated values. This process was tedious and prone to errors, so we thought there must be a more efficient and automated way to handle it.</p>
<p>That’s when we came up with the idea of creating a pipeline where someone could input a compound and quickly receive its volatility information, eliminating the need for all the manual labor. The purpose of volcalc was to transform the process from taking months to gather details for 300 compounds to obtaining information for thousands in a much shorter time.</p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: volcalc was initially developed specifically for a project where the researchers were mainly interested in chemical compounds from the <a href="https://www.genome.jp/kegg/">KEGG database (Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes)</a>. When I joined the team and learned about the project, I was thrilled because, as a chemical ecologist, I saw its potential. However, I also recognized a limitation: the tool only worked with the KEGG database. This was a drawback because many researchers, including food scientists and others who work with similar compounds, might not find their compounds in that specific database.</p>
<p>This realization inspired me to apply for the R Consortium grant. We saw a significant opportunity to expand volcalc, making it more flexible and applicable to a wider range of researchers. We also wanted to improve its integration within the R ecosystem by adding features like returning the file path of a molecule representation after downloading it, so it could be easily piped into subsequent steps. These enhancements aimed to make the tool more versatile and user-friendly for a broader audience.</p>
<p><strong>What were the most significant challenges you faced during the development of the initial version of volcalc, and how did you overcome them?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Kristina</strong>: One of the most challenging aspects of developing volcalc, which continues to be an issue, is managing dependencies. Specifically, we rely heavily on a command-line program to handle much of the processing. Early on, we struggled with how to enable users to run volcalc without needing to install this program on their own computers, as many of our users aren’t familiar with that kind of setup. I spent a lot of time trying to create a reproducible environment using <a href="https://mybinder.org/">Binder</a>, but I was never able to get it fully working. Even today, there are still issues related to managing these dependencies, which Eric can elaborate on further.</p>
<p>It was incredibly important to have Eric on this project because I don’t have a strong background in chemistry. His ability to come in and figure out some of the intricate details that would have taken me much longer to grasp was a huge advantage. The more we can collaborate with domain experts, the better our results will be.</p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: One thing that has helped with the dependency challenges is that we’ve started building volcalc on <a href="https://r-universe.dev/search">R-Universe</a>, which means binaries are available there. While it’s not on CRAN yet, having these binaries on R-Universe makes installation a bit easier. However, we’ve faced some challenges with dependencies, particularly because two of them are from Bioconductor. We didn’t originally aim to develop this package for Bioconductor, which uses S4 objects and has different standards than CRAN. Our goal was to get it on CRAN, but our first submission was rejected because the license field for the Bioconductor package wasn’t formatted to CRAN’s liking. These differences between Bioconductor and CRAN have created barriers, even though the authors of the Bioconductor package have been very responsive. Their package works fine on Bioconductor, but it doesn’t meet CRAN’s criteria, which has been a frustrating challenge.</p>
<p>Another major challenge in developing volcalc relates to the method we use for estimating volatility. This method involves counting the numbers of different functional groups on molecules—such as hydroxyl groups or sulfur atoms—and assigning coefficients to them. To do this programmatically, we use something called SMARTS, which is essentially like regular expressions but for molecular structures. Regular expressions for text are already challenging, but SMARTS is even more complex because it deals with three-dimensional molecules.</p>
<p>Before I joined the group, the first version of volcalc had most of these functional groups figured out, but not all. I spent a significant amount of time trying to develop SMARTS strings to match additional molecules. Moving forward, I hope that if we implement new versions, we can get help from the community to refine these SMARTS strings, as there are likely people out there who are more skilled at it than I am.</p>
<p><strong>The original project proposal mentions expanding volcalc to work with any chemical compound with a known structure. What are the key technical challenges you anticipate in achieving this goal?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: This task turned out to be less difficult than I initially expected, but let me explain. In the original version of volcalc, before we received the R Consortium funding, the main function started with a KEGG ID—an identifier specific to the KEGG database. The function would download a MOL file, which is a text representation of a molecule corresponding to that ID. It would then identify and count the functional groups in the molecule, and finally, calculate the volatility based on those counts.</p>
<p>The major change we needed to implement to make volcalc more versatile was to decouple these steps. In the current version of volcalc, the functionality to download a MOL file from KEGG is still available, but it’s now separate from the main function that calculates volatility. This means that the inputs for calculating volatility can now be any MOL file, not just ones from KEGG. The file can come from any database, be exported from other software, or even be downloaded manually. Additionally, the tool now supports SMILES, which is another, simpler text-based representation of molecules.</p>
<p>There are various ways to represent chemicals in text, including another format called <a href="https://www.inchi-trust.org/">InChI.</a> The Bioconductor packages we use, ChemmineR and ChemmineOB, have the ability to translate from InChI and other types of chemical representations. However, that feature isn’t available on Windows. So, I decided to keep volcalc focused on SMILES and MOL files. I believe that chemists and other researchers should be able to obtain data in one of these two formats, or use another tool to translate their data into these formats. I didn’t want to overload volcalc with the responsibility of being a chemical representation translator, as that didn’t seem like its primary purpose.</p>
<p><strong>Can you walk us through the process of implementing the SIMPOL algorithm within the volcalcc package?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Kristina</strong>: The algorithm itself is fairly simple; it’s just basic math. You need to input some constants, the mass of the compound, and the counts of the functional groups we discussed earlier. Writing the code for this was straightforward and not particularly challenging.</p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: Each functional group has a coefficient associated with it, which is multiplied by the number of times that group appears in the molecule. These values are then summed up, and the mass of the molecule is factored in as well. The challenging part wasn’t the algorithm itself, which is straightforward—just multiplying by coefficients and adding them up. The real difficulty was interpreting what the authors of the algorithm meant by each of the functional groups. Some were oddly specific, like how the hydroxyl group that is part of a nitrophenol group isn’t supposed to count toward the total number of hydroxyl groups. I spent a lot of time poring over the paper, particularly one table, to fully understand how they defined each group. That interpretation was the hardest part.</p>
<p><strong>What future functionalities or expansions do you see as crucial for volcalc, especially in the context of evolving research needs in chemoinformatics?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: Right now, we’re working on allowing users to specify different temperatures. The paper that describes the SIMPOL.1 method includes equations for how the coefficients of each functional group change with temperature. These changes aren’t always linear, and the contributions of functional groups can shift in importance as the temperature varies. This is an important feature to include because the version of volcalc we currently have uses coefficients calculated at 20°C, based on a table from the original paper. To accommodate other temperatures, we need to integrate another table that provides equations for calculating these coefficients based on temperature, and that’s what we’re working on.</p>
<p>Another key feature we want to leave room for in the future is the ability to add other methods for estimating volatility. SIMPOL.1 is just one type of group contribution method, but there are other approaches described in various papers that use different functional groups, equations, and coefficients. The basic idea remains the same: count the functional groups in a molecule, apply an equation, and estimate volatility. We’re trying to structure the code in a way that makes it easy to incorporate additional methods later, even if we don’t add them right away. I think these are the most important features we’re focusing on right now.</p>
<p><strong>Kristina</strong>: We’re focused on the features I mentioned in the near future, but looking further ahead, I could see volcalc expanding to estimate other characteristics of compounds beyond just volatility. While I’m not a chemistry expert or a chemical ecologist, I imagine that those interested in volatility might also be interested in other compound characteristics that currently lack automated tools for estimation. So, it’s possible the package could evolve to include those features.</p>
<p>That said, one of the things I appreciate about the R package ecosystem is that it allows for specialized tools. Since anyone can build what they need, we don’t end up with massive, overly complex packages that try to do everything and become difficult to maintain. It might be better to keep volcalc focused and leave room for separate packages to handle additional functionality. This way, the tools remain manageable and easier to maintain in the long run.</p>
<p><strong>How has it been working with the R Consortium? Would you recommend applying for an ISC grant to other R developers?</strong></p>
<p><strong>Kristina</strong>: The application process was straightforward, and I found the grant format to be very practical. It was focused on milestones and product development, which is refreshing compared to many academic research grants that tend to avoid specific deliverables. I highly recommend considering this grant. I believe people often overlook smaller funding sources, but even small amounts can make a big impact on the work you’re doing.</p>
<p><strong>Eric</strong>: The first time I applied for an R Consortium grant was as a grad student, and I strongly encourage trainees to apply as well. It was a great experience for me because I could do it independently—my advisor wasn’t involved as one of the authors, and it wasn’t a complex process like applying for an NSF grant. It was straightforward and really rewarding. The only tricky part was figuring out the payment process, but that’s something people can work out.</p>
<p>I’ve noticed there seem to be fewer projects in recent years, and I don’t think it’s due to a lack of funding. It seems like fewer people are applying, which is why I especially encourage others to give it a shot. From what I’ve seen, there’s a very good chance of getting funded if you apply right now.</p>
<p>People should be creative and think broadly about how their project can benefit the broader R community. This doesn’t mean you need to develop the next big thing like R-Universe or CRAN. It can be something smaller, like a package that other R users will find helpful. For example, with our project, volcalc, our main goal was to encourage chemists—who usually use point-and-click software—to start using R. That was enough of a contribution to the R community to get funded. So, I really encourage people to think creatively about what “benefiting the R community” can mean.</p>
<section id="about-isc-funded-projects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-isc-funded-projects">About ISC Funded Projects</h2>
<p>A major goal of the R Consortium is to strengthen and improve the infrastructure supporting the R Ecosystem. We seek to accomplish this by funding projects that will improve both technical infrastructure and social infrastructure.</p>
<p><a href="../../all-projects/">Learn More!</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/unlocking-chemical-volatility-how-the-volcalc-r-package-is-streamlining-scientific-research/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unlocking-chemical-volatility-how-the-volcalc-r-package-is-streamlining-scientific-research/volcalc.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Free Boba Tea and Technical R Topics Lure Young Learners to New Brunei R User Group</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/haziqjamil/">Haziq Jamil</a>, the founder and organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/bruneir/">Brunei R User Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium. Haziq established the first R User Group in Brunei to promote R programming and create collaborative learning environments. Under his leadership, the group hosts monthly meetups and events to advance R skills across various sectors in Brunei. Through these efforts, Haziq aims to build a supportive and inclusive R community, encouraging both personal growth and data-driven innovation in the region.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/haziq-jamil.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My name is Haziq Jamil, and I am an Assistant Professor in Statistics at Universiti Brunei Darussalam, the leading higher education institution in Brunei. I have used R for almost ten years during my studies and on many personal and professional projects.</p>
<p>The Brunei R User Group was founded in February 2024, and I serve as its chair and founder. My role is to lead the group’s administration, oversee its overall direction and strategy, and ensure that its initiatives align with its mission of promoting R programming and fostering a supportive learning environment, focusing on community engagement and collaboration.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/smiles.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Brunei? </strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/brunei-rugs-logo.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>The R community in Brunei may be small, but it is growing thanks to the efforts of the Brunei R User Group. The group organizes monthly meetups and events to promote learning and development in R programming and advance its use across various fields in Brunei. These gatherings provide opportunities to expand the community by enhancing participants’ skills, offering a platform for networking with like-minded individuals, and engaging in practical applications such as data analysis, visualization, and spatial data techniques. By creating an inclusive R community, the group aims to support individual growth in Brunei and foster collaboration on data-driven R projects. Whether for students, professionals, or hobbyists, the group strives to provide a supportive space for learning, sharing insights, and driving innovation within the local R community.</p>
<p><strong>You hosted a Meetup, “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/bruneir/events/300000854/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">R&gt;aya with R</a>,” in April. Can you share more about the topic? Why this topic? </strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/brunei-raya-meetup.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R User Group’s “<a href="https://bruneir.github.io/posts/bru-2/">R&gt;aya with R</a>” Meetup in Brunei was a lively event that combined Hari Raya Aidilfitri’s (Eid-ul-Fitr) festive spirit with the exploration of R programming. To engage younger audiences, we offered free boba tea as a beverage during the session. The event featured informative sessions led by expert community members, each focusing on advanced topics relevant to different fields.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/boba.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>One of the critical presentations was on “Survival Analysis” by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elvynna-leong-84b449190/?originalSubdomain=bn">Dr.&nbsp;Elvynna Leong</a>. She explained statistical techniques to predict the time until an event of interest, such as guests’ arrival at a Hari Raya open house. This topic is directly related to fields that depend on time-to-event data, such as healthcare or actuarial science.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/presentation.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>One of the highlights was <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/wafid-sophian-6b8073141/?originalSubdomain=bn">Wafid Sophian</a>’s session on “Simulation Methods for Economic Analysis.” In this presentation, Wafid demonstrated how R can be used to simulate and analyze complex economic scenarios. The topic focused on modeling outcomes and making data-driven predictions. It was chosen due to its significance in finance and business analytics.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/eden-ng-737504177/">Dr.&nbsp;Eden Ng</a> presented on “Mathematical Modeling of Evolutionary Biology,” showcasing how R can be used to model biological evolutionary processes. This session visualized the intersection of R programming and biology, thus emphasizing R’s utility in research areas such as genetics and evolutionary studies.</p>
<p>The event covered three topics in the areas of mathematics, economics, and biology. It was open to all individuals interested in learning about the capabilities and usage of the R language, regardless of whether they were beginners or experts.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future? </strong></p>
<p>For planning and executing events like the “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/bruneir/events/299246264/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Analysing Spatial Data with R</a>” event, the R&gt;aya Meetup, and the “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/bruneir/events/301146476/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Introduction to R</a>” sessions, we utilized <a href="https://github.com/bruneir">Github</a>. To host R scripts, datasets, and event materials. Our participants can access and review the code before and after the event. It also provides a platform for issue tracking and version control to facilitate feedback and group collaboration. It helps those who can’t attend in person to engage and contribute to our <a href="https://bruneir.github.io/">Quarto Blog</a>. To publish event summaries, key takeaways, and additional resources on the official Brunei R User Group blog. We hope to provide a centralized location for information and help remote participants catch up.</p>
<p><strong>Please share any additional details you would like to include in the blog. </strong></p>
<p>As the first R user group in Brunei, we are excited to promote the adoption and growth of R across various industries. Our mission goes beyond just hosting events—we are dedicated to creating and nurturing an inclusive R community and showcasing the power of R in numerous fields.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><strong><a href="../../all-projects/rugsprogram.html">Learn more</a>!!</strong></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/free-boba-tea-and-technical-r-topics-lure-young-learners-to-new-brunei-r-user-group/smiles.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Empowering Data Science: How R is Transforming Research in Cameroon</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nyavoratovo/?originalSubdomain=cm">NyAvo RATOVO-ANDRIANARISOA</a>, the co-founder of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-community-cameroon/">R Community Cameroon</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the rapid growth of the R community in Cameroon and the impact of R on local research and data analysis. NyAvo provided insights into the community’s activities, such as developing an R community website using Shiny and implementing innovative projects like a custom search application. He also discussed the challenges and strategies in building a robust R ecosystem in Central Africa.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/nyavo.jpg" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I am a statistical engineer from the Institute of Statistics of Central Africa in Cameroon, originally from Madagascar. Currently, I serve in a monitoring and evaluation role with the United Nations. My journey with R began about five years ago as a student. I started learning R during my studies and expanded my expertise by freelancing as a <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/">Shiny</a> developer. Over time, I’ve also gained experience with OCR technology, working with Tesseract and utilizing Google Cloud Colab’s API Amazon Web services for R and artificial intelligence models.</p>
<p>With a solid statistical background, I specialize in data mining. In 2020, before learning about the R Consortium campaign, I had already envisioned creating an R community in Cameroon. After discussing the idea with some colleagues and discovering the potential support, it became the perfect opportunity to bring this vision to life. My colleagues and I officially launched the R Community Cameroon at the beginning of this year.</p>
<p>I would like to mention my colleagues who have co-founded the group with me: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/romain-tchakoute-916126170/">Romain TCHAKOUTE</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/idrissa-dabo-72a199118/">Idrissa DABO</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aboubacar-sa%C3%AFdou-boureima-0aa918203/">Saidou BOUREIMA</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mianala-anaelle-manambiravaka-8291aa260/">Mianala MANAMBIRAVAKA</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ndjiya-djeumen-luc-ronald-franck-8a5968221/">Ronald DJEUMEN.</a></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/community.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Cameroon?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Cameroon is home to one of Central Africa’s largest science schools. I am part of a vibrant academic community of 30 members from several nationalities. This environment brings together some of the brightest minds, and R is an integral part of our curriculum. However, our use of R goes beyond basic statistics and plotting; we focus on more sophisticated applications, such as Monte Carlo estimation, model development, and advanced R programming.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/school.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Several professors in our school possess strong statistical backgrounds and rely on R for their research. Additionally, our alums who have transitioned into the industry continue to leverage R for data analysis. While Cameroon has a limited amount of data, we conduct numerous surveys. The initial step most of us take is data cleaning, predominantly using R. Once the data is clean, we employ Quarto to generate automatic reports, allowing us to summarize survey results quickly. Some of my colleagues also explore other functionalities of R, like creating applications with R Shiny.</p>
<p>Another significant group is comprised of economics students or those working on their theses. They often seek our assistance to learn R for tasks such as descriptive statistics and building logistic models.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>Currently, we rely on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/powerpoint">PowerPoint</a> to create posters for our events and <a href="https://meet.google.com/landing">Google Meet</a> for online meetings before having the Meetup Pro account provided by R Consortium. Many of us, the co-founders of the community, are technicians, so we also use Word for various tasks. However, leadership skills have been crucial in convincing people to join our vision. To engage others, we often organize dinner or lunchtime meetings. We’ve invested significant effort into these initiatives, and through them, we’ve successfully negotiated several partnerships. Initially, I contacted colleagues at the National Institute of Statistics to rally support for our cause.</p>
<p>Our community now includes students and academics, and some PhD doctors are still in the learning phase. I discussed creating a community in Cameroon, asking what value we could offer to encourage their participation. I proposed that they become co-founders of the community, a role they could highlight on their resumes. Seven people have already stepped up as leaders within our group.</p>
<p>We’re active both online and in person. It’s important to note that we organize two types of meetings. The first is an internal meeting with our community leaders, typically attended by around seven people. We use a WhatsApp group for communication and usually meet monthly for lunch at a restaurant for these meetings. The second activity involves larger groups. For these, we first coordinate with the administration, such as the school mentioned earlier, who then communicate with the students. We also document and share these activities online to inform others, though most of our communication is direct and specific.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/meeting.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>For example, after explaining our vision to a university contact, they were interested and agreed to offer a course at their institution. We then coordinated with the student body leader, planned a session, and shared the event online. We even hired a professional photographer to capture the event, sharing the photos with the school for further distribution. However, we haven’t yet posted about this activity on LinkedIn.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, we’re planning a session with another school—the statistical school where I studied. We’re currently in discussions with their management. Once we’ve had our conversation, possibly next week, we’ll talk with the student leaders. After the session, we plan to share our activities online, including photos, to highlight what we’re accomplishing in Cameroon.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/students.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Do you have any upcoming events planned for the group?</strong></p>
<p>We have an upcoming event that I consider one of the most important we’ve planned. It is our group’s quarterly meeting. The main objective of this meeting is to develop our R community website using Shiny. It will be a workshop where we’ll gather in one place and form small groups comprising beginners and experienced members. During the workshop, we’ll collaborate to code and discuss ideas, and ideally, by the end of the session, we will have the code for our community website ready for deployment.</p>
<p>We’re currently facing some logistical challenges to organize this event. In Cameroon, when we organize events, we strive for perfection, ensuring everything from photography to visibility is top-notch. We’re searching for a suitable hotel venue to host our event.</p>
<p><strong>What trends do you currently see in R language and your industry?</strong></p>
<p>In Cameroon, <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> is one of the most popular packages we promote during our R community sessions. Another widely used package is R Markdown. While I primarily use <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a> to produce outputs for my job, I am also working on becoming more proficient with Quarto, as it is the future of reporting and documentation.</p>
<p>I frequently use the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/">tidyverse</a>, <a href="https://tidyr.tidyverse.org/">tidyr</a>, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/labelled/index.html">labelled</a>, and <a href="https://haven.tidyverse.org/">haven</a> suite of packages for data cleaning and reporting. A significant part of my job involves data cleaning, and I rely on tidyverse in conjunction with Quarto for these tasks.</p>
<p>We also utilize R for machine learning, though there is still potential for improvement in this area. We are focused on leveraging Shiny, Quarto, and tidyverse for our work.</p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting, primarily related to your industry?</strong></p>
<p>We are currently working on an exciting project that is still in progress. The aim is to develop an application inspired by the functionality seen in the movie Fast and Furious, where users can search for information on the Internet. We are utilizing the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/httr/index.html">httr</a> package to collect data from online sources.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The application will enable users to input a search term, such as “lion in Cameroon,” and receive a dataset with all relevant information. Our goal is to provide high-quality data for researchers and other users, which involves considerable effort to ensure the accuracy and usefulness of the data.&nbsp;</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/r-user-group-support-program">Learn more</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/empowering-data-science-how-r-is-transforming-research-in-cameroon/school.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Thank You, Joseph Rickert: A Legacy of Leadership and Innovation in the R Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/thank-you-joseph-rickert-a-legacy-of-leadership/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As we announce the end of Joseph (Joe) Rickert’s tenure as the Executive Director of the R Consortium, we reflect on his remarkable contributions that have significantly contributed to the R community. Joe’s leadership has been instrumental in fostering growth, innovation, and collaboration within the R ecosystem.</p>
<p><strong>Founding the R Consortium</strong></p>
<p>Joe has been with the R Consortium since its inception in 2014. He was initially appointed to be Microsoft’s representative to the Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC) and was soon tasked with creating the R User Groups (RUGS) grants program. Joe also pioneered the formation of ISC working groups to foster industry-wide collaborative projects. In 2016, Joe was appointed to be RStudio’s representative to the Board of Directors. In 2018, he took on the role of Secretary, and by 2019, he was elected Chair of the Board. In 2023, Joe took on the role of Executive Director. Under his guidance, the R Consortium has grown into an inclusive organization supporting the R programming language and its community. Our new executive director, Terry Christiani, was affirmed by the board of directors in our August 2024 board meeting after a selection committee interviewed candidates and made recommendations.</p>
<p><strong>Advancing User Groups</strong></p>
<p>One of Joe’s notable achievements is his unwavering support for R user groups worldwide. He recognized the importance of grassroots movements in spreading the use of R and provided essential resources and funding to these groups. He was instrumental in funding the R-Ladies as a top-level ISC project that operates worldwide to provide safe places for women to come together and learn from each other in an otherwise male-dominated space. Joe was also directly involved with the Bay Area useR Group (BARUG), organizing events, speaking, or contributing to discussions around the R programming language, especially in the context of data science and statistical computing. This support has enabled countless R enthusiasts to connect, share knowledge, and collaborate on projects, thereby strengthening the global R community.</p>
<p><strong>Industry Collaboration and Working Groups</strong></p>
<p>Joe actively reached out to industry leaders to create unique working groups aimed at solving industry-wide problems. These collaborations have led to the development of working groups focused on R programming solutions that benefit not only the community but also industries that rely on data science and statistical computing.</p>
<p><strong>A Legacy of Innovation</strong></p>
<p>Throughout his tenure, Joe has been a driving force behind numerous initiatives that have propelled the R community forward. His efforts have ensured that the R Consortium remains a dynamic and inclusive organization, fostering a spirit of collaboration and innovation. His leadership has left an indelible mark on the R community, and his legacy will continue to inspire future generations of R users and developers.</p>
<p>As we welcome new leadership, we extend our heartfelt gratitude to Joe Rickert for his dedication, vision, and tireless efforts in advancing the R community. Thank you, Joe, for your invaluable contributions and for paving the way for a brighter future for the R ecosystem.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/thank-you-joseph-rickert-a-legacy-of-leadership/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/thank-you-joseph-rickert-a-legacy-of-leadership/thank-you-main-page.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="50" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R-Ladies Bariloche in Argentina: Fostering a Different Approach to Leadership</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/lina.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lina-moreno-azocar-81a5aa276/?originalSubdomain=ar">Lina Moreno</a>, founder and organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/es/rladies-bariloche/">R-Ladies Bariloche</a> chapter in Argentina, recently shared her journey with the R Consortium. A biologist focusing on evolutionary ecology, she discussed her experience building a local R community, the challenges of maintaining engagement post-pandemic, and her efforts to foster discussions on leadership and gender equity within academia. Through her work, she aims to create an inclusive space for women in data science and strengthen the R community in Bariloche.</p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I am a biologist working on evolutionary ecology, I did a bachelor in Sciences in another Argentinian province and then moved to Bariloche to start my PhD. (That was 16 years ago!) I spent a couple of years working in the field (I study reptiles, mainly lizards, and their adaptations to cold environments), and then I had to analyze the data. When I started my main analysis, I could only do it in R. At that time, my boss told me to start with R immediately, so I started searching online. I am doing this kind of work in my home country, so finding resources was complex. I had to work on a comparative analysis and phylogenies, which was difficult initially. However, I started studying and meeting people who taught me, which was awesome.&nbsp;</p>
<p>After several years, I encountered a problem I couldn’t resolve. I turned to Google and found a helpful community of ladies. They assisted me a lot and saved me from a tight spot. After some communication, they suggested starting an R-Ladies community in Bariloche. I met with them in person when I traveled to Buenos Aires. They convinced me to start a Bariloche chapter, and by the end of 2019, a few of my colleagues and I, mainly biologists working in the same area, created the Bariloche chapter.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/chapter.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>What are some challenges you have faced in organizing this group?</strong></p>
<p>We are currently facing some difficulties as people seem unwilling to get involved. As a result, we are exploring new strategies such as combined meetups (online and in person), and together with other R-Ladies groups. We also plan to organize three or four meetups this year. Despite our efforts, we are getting discouraged by the lack of response, but we will see how it goes.</p>
<p>During the pandemic, there were five organizers, three of us with young children, so it was pretty difficult. We started a study group for the <a href="https://r4ds.hadley.nz/">R for Data Science</a> book, which had recently been translated into <a href="https://es.r4ds.hadley.nz/">Spanish</a>. We also organized meetups, mainly led by us. Surprisingly, there was good attendance during the pandemic, with around 40 people each time, similar to before the pandemic. However, after returning to in-person meetups, the attendance dropped significantly. The most crowded meetup had only 15 people, whereas before, we used to have two meetups on the same subject, both with 40 attendees.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/meetup.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We are attempting to integrate virtual and in-person components, which has proven challenging. We aim to introduce a beginner’s course in R through a meetup to help attendees gain confidence for future meetups. Our meetups typically have a good turnout, but there is a lack of interest in specific topics, particularly those related to gender bias and women’s issues. Despite this, we are putting in a significant effort. Last year, we participated in a round table during a conference in Bariloche, focusing on gender bias and the difficulties of being a woman in Academia, and it received a lot of support, especially from women. The rest of the group is currently working on documenting our experience at that round table. I am not participating as I have been busy with other responsibilities.</p>
<p>Last year we surveyed people on how they feel R-Ladies is contributing to their careers, its influence on leadership abilities, their reasons for abandoning our events, or why they were too busy to attend. We have received some responses, but not as many as we expected.</p>
<p>However, we have enough data to write a paper about it. We’re also looking into the topic of leadership. We are opening our minds and exploring the possibilities of supporting the R community here in Bariloche, but it’s quite challenging at the moment.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Argentina?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The field of artificial intelligence and machine learning is rapidly evolving, which greatly helps incorporate knowledge in R. The leading software used for this purpose is R and Python. R is more popular than Python, as it has been around longer and is more user-friendly. Many people from academia with expertise in machine learning are transitioning to private industries. Regarding statistical analysis in biology, tools such as the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/vegan/vegan.pdf">Vegan</a> package and those incorporating <a href="https://m-clark.github.io/generalized-additive-models/application.html">GAM (Generalized Additive Models)</a> are commonly used. Tools that can handle multiple effects simultaneously are in high demand in ecology.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/community.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Would you like to talk about any recent activity from the group?</strong></p>
<p>It was exciting what happened after the conference we participated in. As women, we are trying to maintain an open community. Initially, the organizers needed to learn how to manage an open group without a leader or a head, where everyone is considered equal. The participants ranged from students to established researchers, which ignited discussions about leadership and how women and minority groups navigate the world. We are accustomed to a robust and assertive leadership style, often associated with being at the top. However, as women, we wanted a different kind of leadership. This led to discussions on creating a new type of leadership that doesn’t adhere to the traditional patriarchal model. The manuscript the group is working on currently revolves around creating a new style of leadership that focuses on nurturing individuals to become better persons, researchers, or workers.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The topics discussed in the manuscript revolve around how we can lead differently. These discussions were not limited to our group; we engaged with several groups from Argentina and Spain who also expressed a similar desire for a different kind of leadership. It is interesting to note that as women and minority groups, we want to be in positions to make meaningful decisions, especially given that our work as biologists primarily tackles environmental issues. Despite historically shying away from more traditional forms of leadership, we are now advocating for different styles. This shared sentiment has brought us closer to other minority groups, and we believe it’s an important topic that needs further discussion. It’s important to recognize that women have a different approach, and it doesn’t make us weaker than men; it simply signifies that we have a unique way of contributing.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="../../all-projects/rugsprogram.html">Learn more</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-bariloche-in-argentina-fostering-a-different-approach/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The 2024 ISC Grant Program will begin Accepting Applications Soon!</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/the-2024-isc-grant-program-will-begin/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/the-2024-isc-grant-program-will-begin/isc-program.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium is excited to announce the second cycle of the 2024 Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC) Grants Program. The <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/call-for-proposals">Call for Proposals will open soon</a>. This initiative aims to support projects that strengthen the R ecosystem’s technical and social infrastructure.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Here is a <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/awarded-projects/2024-group-1">list of projects that received grants from the R Consortium in the First Cycle in 2024</a>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>From the Call for Proposals page:</p>
<p>The ISC is interested in projects that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Are likely to have a broad impact on the R community.</li>
<li>Have a focused scope (a good example is the <a href="https://github.com/r-spatial/sf">Simple Features for R project</a>). If you have a larger project, consider breaking it up into smaller chunks (a good example of this done is with the <a href="http://dbi.r-dbi.org/">DBI/DBItest project</a> submission, where multiple proposals came in over time to address the various needs).</li>
<li>Have a low-to-medium risk with a low-to-medium reward. The ISC tends not fund high-risk, high-reward projects.</li>
</ul>
<p>Whether you’re working on groundbreaking tools or organizing community-driven events, this is your chance to secure funding and make a significant impact on the R community!</p>
<p><strong>Key Dates:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>September 1, 2024:</strong> Grant Application Period Opens</li>
<li><strong>October 1, 2024:</strong> Grant Application Period Closes</li>
<li><strong>November 1, 2024:</strong> Notification of Accepted Grantees</li>
<li><strong>December 1:</strong>&nbsp; Deadline for acceptance of grant and contract. Public notification of grantees occurs shortly thereafter.</li>
</ul>
<p>Submit your proposal by October 1, 2024, and contribute to the ongoing growth of the R ecosystem. Visit the <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/call-for-proposals">R Consortium website</a> for detailed guidelines and submission instructions. Don’t miss this opportunity to bring your innovative ideas to life!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/the-2024-isc-grant-program-will-begin/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R4SocialScience: Empowering Social Science Research with R in India</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/drmohitgarg9/?trk=public_profile_browsemap&amp;originalSubdomain=in">Dr.&nbsp;Mohit Garg</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r4socialscience/">R4SocialScience</a> group in Delhi, India recently talked to the R Consortium about his experience of starting an R user group. The R4SocialScience group aims to bridge the gap between social science research and data analysis, offering support and training to academics, researchers, and industry professionals. Dr.&nbsp;Garg shares his experiences, the growth of the R community in India, and his plans for expanding R’s reach.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/drGarg.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I’m currently working as an assistant librarian at the <a href="https://home.iitd.ac.in/">Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi</a>, one of the premier institutions in India.&nbsp; My academic background includes a BTech in Information Technology from Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University followed by an MS in Librarian Information Science from the <a href="https://www.isical.ac.in/">Indian Statistical Institute</a>, an institution dedicated to statistics in India started by the late Professor P.C. Mahanobis. After that, I completed my PhD in Library and Information Science from IGNOU, New Delhi.</p>
<p>My interest in R began in 2013 when I started my MS at the Indian Statistical Institute.&nbsp; Since then, I have taken various courses as part of my MS program and some online courses. I became interested in R due to its open source nature and the free availability of packages for all kinds of analysis. Then, I started promoting R in the academic community. However, in 2013, there was little interest in R because the prevalent approach in India was more focused on using commercial software for data analysis.&nbsp; However, in the past few years, there has been an increasing interest in R, with many workshops and government-funded events dedicated to it.</p>
<p>I have been providing R training to professors, teachers, and research scholars, and I have also worked on web-based development using <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/">Shiny</a> packages. Furthermore, we have developed a web dashboard to visualize real-time research productivity data obtained from sources like <a href="https://www.elsevier.com/products/scopus">Scopus</a> through API. Recently, we completed a 12-week MOOC course on <a href="https://swayam.gov.in/nc_details/NPTEL">NPTEL SWAYAM</a> platform with a focus solely on R. The course was quite popular, with 2584 learners from India joining, and 515 learners registering for the final examination. Although the course was free, participants had the option to pay for certification.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in India?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I have been involved in the academic profession since 2016 and have been giving lectures and providing resource points at various institutions. I believe that there is a need to build a community focused on social sciences, especially for those who may have a limited understanding of mathematics, and statistics. The idea is to create a specific community related to social science, not just in India, but also in collaboration with other institutions. The community will cater to three main groups: those who are proficient in coding and development of R packages, those who are familiar with basic R but need further guidance, and those who are completely new to R.</p>
<p>The community aims to provide support for those interested in social science and to make R more accessible by offering packages related to social science, basic R tutorials. One specific package gaining popularity in academia is “<a href="https://www.bibliometrix.org/home/">biblo shiny bibliometrics</a>,” which facilitates scientific productivity mapping using R.&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/rSocialScience.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We want to emphasize that R is not just a programming language, but a software for data analysis, to encourage more people to explore its potential. While both R and Python are interpreted languages, we aim to dispel the fear of programming and demonstrate how these languages can be used effectively. Although Python appears to be more widely used in the industry, there is still a growing interest in R.</p>
<p><strong>What are your plans for the group going forward?</strong></p>
<p>I have been teaching R for more than 10 years, and I found that researchers are interested in using R. I have identified three potential co-organizers from different regions in India to make a team of four people. We have already received a grant, and we plan to conduct training sessions in different locations across India.</p>
<p>I am focusing on a “train the trainer” model, where I aim to train individuals who can then carry out training sessions in their respective regions. India has over 50,000 colleges and around 1,200 universities, all involved in significant research and analysis activities. We also aim to have dedicated R trainers in all districts in India by 2026.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/teaching.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our approach involves dividing the country into five zones, followed by state-wise and district-wise planning. We are not heavily reliant on industry support, as our activities are primarily related to academia and research.&nbsp;</p>
<p>We plan to charge a nominal registration fee, which would cover expenses such as food and refreshment. We are hoping to minimize travel expenses, as they can be quite costly. But we will explore some way to fund the travel and accommodation expenses. We have hosted a one day workshop on “<a href="https://x.com/RConsortium/status/1808219594232156479">Doing Research using R</a>” at Galgotias University.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/trainingSession.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>I am currently focusing on building a community and providing training sessions. I have noticed that online sessions may not be as effective as I had hoped, as participants seem to encounter many problems. Therefore, I am considering conducting more in-person workshops, which I believe will help popularize the training sessions. Additionally, I aim to develop specialized packages for social science and build a dedicated team. I am optimistic about these plans. During a recent workshop, I noticed that many participants preferred simple tools for data analysis. I intend to introduce such tools to make the training more accessible and user-friendly for participants. This is my vision for the community.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/community.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</strong></p>
<p>We have developed a platform utilizing the shiny and other text mining packages. This platform is still in the testing phase. The platform allows real-time data fetching from the Scopus API.</p>
<p>For example, if I search for a faculty member, it will display the publication data such as the number of publications, H-index, citations, types of publications, sources of publication, and annual publication distribution. We can also download this data.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/platform.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have also developed a word cloud based on the titles of the publications for each faculty member, processed using the TM package. This helps to infer the expertise of the professors. Furthermore, we have included a feature for identifying the H-classic, which is related to the H-index.&nbsp; This platform is quite useful and efficient, especially for academic institutions. We now have the capability to download data from a specific date range as an Excel file. The data includes publication dates and the number of citations.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/wordcloud.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We’re in the process of creating a full dashboard for universities or institutions. We’ve also conducted a pilot study for other institutions. We are also considering publishing this work as a research paper to increase its visibility.&nbsp;</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="../../all-projects/rugsprogram.html">Learn more</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r4socialscience-empowering-social-science-research/trainingSession.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>News from R Submissions Working Group – Pilot 3 Successfully Reviewed by FDA</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/news-from-r-submissions-working-group-pilot-3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Blog contributed by Ning Leng, People and Product Leader, Roche-Genentech and Joel Laxamana, Principal Data Scientist, Roche-Genentech</em></p>
<p>The R Consortium is pleased to announce the successful completion of the Pilot 3 Submission which extended the work done in Pilots 1 and 2 by generating the ADaM datasets. The complete <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-wg/blob/main/_Documents/Summary_R_Pilot3_Submission.pdf">FDA response letter</a> is available.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>The objective of the R Consortium R Submission Pilot 3 Project is to test the concept that an R-language based submission package for ADaMs and TLFs can meet the needs and the expectations of the FDA reviewers, including assessing code review and analyzing reproducibility. All submission materials and communications from this pilot are publicly available, with the aim of providing a working example for future R-language based FDA submissions. This is an FDA-industry collaboration through the non-profit organization R Consortium.</p>
<p>All submission materials can be found at: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam-to-fda">submissions-pilot3-adam-to-fda</a>. This is the first publicly available R-based FDA submission package including R scripts to generate Analysis Data Models (ADaM) and Tables, Listings &amp; Figures (TLFs).</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/news-from-r-submissions-working-group-pilot-3/collaboration.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Open-Source Collaboration in standardizing Clinical Trial analyses and Submissions. Broadening ways to bring treatments to Patients.</em></p>
<section id="pilot-3-timeline" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-timeline">Pilot 3 Timeline</h2>
<p>The initial submission was submitted through the eCTD gateway on Aug 28, 2023. FDA verbal responses were received from Jan-July 2024 during R submission working group meetings. Documentation of this initial feedback and response can be found at <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam-to-fda/blob/main/m1/us/response-FDA-IR-pilot3.pdf">response-FDA-IR-pilot3.pdf</a>. The updated submission package addressed reported issues and was re-submitted on Apr 19, 2024. The final response letter from FDA was received on Aug 8, 2024.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-scope" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-scope">Pilot 3 Scope</h2>
<p>The Pilot 3 test submission exemplifies an all-R submission package for ADaMs and TLFs, adhering to electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD) specifications. This comprehensive package not only includes ADaMs and TLGs, but it emulates a full study submission package including the source Study Data Tabulation Models (SDTMs) used to generate the Pilot 3 ADaMs. It also encompasses the installation and loading of the proprietary {pilot3utils} R package, various open-source R packages, R scripts for the Analysis Data Model (ADaM) datasets derived from Pilot 3, and Tables, Listings, and Figures (TLFs) from Pilot 1. In addition to other requisite eCTD components, the Pilot 3 package also includes the Analysis Data Reviewer’s Guide (ADRG) providing detailed steps leading to the execution of the analysis R scripts to re-produce the ADaMs and TLFs from a FDA reviewers perspective. These Pilot 3 submission materials are linked above.</p>
<p>Pilot 3 serves as a complement to Pilots <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot1-to-fda">1</a> and <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot2-to-fda">2</a>, which demonstrated the feasibility of submitting TLF R scripts and R Shiny code, respectively. Furthermore, Pilot 3 successfully validated the submission of proprietary R packages in compressed file formats, serving as another alternative to {pkglite} or installation directly from github.</p>
<p>If you have any questions about this Pilot 3 submission, we would love to hear from you. Feel free to submit any questions you may have as a <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam-to-fda/issues/new/choose">new issue</a> in our Pilot 3 github repository or you may find any of the Pilot 3 team members in <a href="https://pharmaverse.slack.com/archives/C030EB2M4GM">Pharmaverse slack</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="learnings-from-pilots-1-through-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learnings-from-pilots-1-through-3">Learnings from Pilots 1 through 3</h2>
<p>In the three pilots, for various TLFs, the working group members intentionally created different tables in different formats using various open-source R packages. The FDA staff successfully accepted and reproduced the results generated from these different open-source packages. However, though not in scope of these Pilots, we want to share awareness that sponsors are responsible for selecting open-source packages that demonstrate sufficient reliability. Further information on this can be found in the <a href="https://www.pharmar.org/">R Validation Hub</a>, formed in 2018 by the PSI AIMS Special Interest Group and supported by the R Consortium. It offers tools like <a href="https://www.pharmar.org/posts/news/updates-aug-2024/">{riskmetric}</a> to quantify the “risk” of R packages and a user-friendly R Shiny app, <a href="https://www.pharmar.org/riskassessment/">{riskassessment}</a>, to evaluate package reliability.</p>
<p>The majority of FDA staff feedback falls under the following themes :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Clear ADRG documentation on computing environment, package dependencies, and expected warnings</li>
<li>Clear documentation on data processing rules and statistical method implementation</li>
<li>Good statistical practice in confirmatory trials, such as avoiding the possibility of “p-hacking”&nbsp;</li>
</ol>
<p>For future submissions using open-source languages, it is recommended to give special attention to recommendation theme 1. Recommendation themes 2 and 3 are language-agnostic and should always be followed, regardless of the programming language used. All of these themes fall in line with the FDA’s <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot3-adam/main/articles/statistical-software-clarifying-statement.html">Statistical Software Clarifying Statement</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="upcoming-pilots" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upcoming-pilots">Upcoming Pilots</h2>
<p>As a next step, the R Consortium R Submission Working Group initiated <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-pilot4/">submission pilot 4</a>, to explore the use of novel technologies such as Linux containers and web assembly to bundle a Shiny application into a self-contained package, facilitating a smoother process of both transferring and executing the application.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-r-consortium-r-submission-working-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-r-consortium-r-submission-working-group">The R Consortium R Submission Working Group</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">R Consortium R Submissions Working Group</a> is focused on improving practices for R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions.</p>
<p>To bring an experimental clinical product to market, electronic submission of data, computer programs, and relevant documentation is required by health authority agencies from different countries. In the past, submissions have been mainly based on the SAS language.&nbsp;</p>
<p>In recent years, the use of open source languages, especially the R language, has become very popular in the pharmaceutical industry and research institutions. Although the health authorities accept submissions based on open source programming languages, sponsors may be hesitant to conduct submissions using open source languages due to a lack of working examples.</p>
<p>Therefore, the R Submissions Working Group aims at providing R-based submission examples and identifying potential gaps during submission of these example packages. All materials, including submission examples and communications, are publicly available on the R consortium Github page: <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium">https://github.com/RConsortium</a> .</p>
<p>The R consortium R submission working group includes members from more than 10 pharmaceutical companies, as well as regulatory agencies. More details of the working group can be found at: <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/</a> .</p>
<p>The R consortium R submission working group is open to anyone who is interested in joining. If interested, please contact Joseph Rickert at director@r-consortium.org.&nbsp;</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-fda-reviewers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-fda-reviewers">Pilot 3 FDA Reviewers</h2>
<p>FDA reviewers included&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hye-soo-cho/">Hye Soo Cho</a>,&nbsp; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/paul-schuette-40aa838/">Paul Schuette</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/youn-kyeong-chang-885785159/">Youn Kyeong Chang</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="pilot-3-developers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-3-developers">Pilot 3 Developers</h2>
<p>The Pilot 3 development team included <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jlaxamana/">Joel Laxamana</a> (Project Lead, Roche), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/robert-devine-50b0b931/">Robert Devine</a> (J&amp;J) , <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ben-straub/">Benjamin Straub</a> (GSK) , <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kaz462/">Kangjie Zhang</a> (Bayer) , <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thomas-neitmann/">Thomas Neitmann</a> (Roche), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tataphani/">Phanikumar Tata</a> (Syneos), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/stevenhaesendonckx/">Steven Haesendonckx</a> (J&amp;J), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yutong-liu-a25b68a8/">Yutong Liu</a> (Moderna), Lei Zhao (Roche), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nicolekjonesmph/">Nicole Jones (Merck)</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bingjun-wang-2b9783147/">Benjamin Wang (Merck),</a> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dadong-zhang-48b937201/">Dadong Zhang (Illumina)</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/declan-hodges/">Declan Hodges (GSK)</a>.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/news-from-r-submissions-working-group-pilot-3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Building Bridges in Haifa, Israel: How the New R User Group in Haifa is Establishing a Diverse R Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/unnamed.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elieydlin/?originalSubdomain=il">Eli Eydlin</a>, a dedicated member of the R community who has been instrumental in establishing an <a href="https://www.meetup.com/haifa-r-user-group/">R User Group in Haifa, Israel</a>. With a background in physics and a recent shift into the biotech industry, Eli was motivated to create the group after noticing the absence of a local R community in his new city. Despite Haifa’s relatively small size, it boasts a diverse R community, including professionals from high-tech companies, academia, and startups. Eli shared his experience organizing their first Meetup, which featured speakers from vastly different backgrounds, and his plans to make future events more inclusive. His story highlights the importance of community building and the impact of taking the initiative, offering inspiration for others looking to contribute to their local R communities.</p>
<p><strong>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I’ve been working in a biotech startup for nearly two years. My background is more on the pharma side, but I decided to dive into this new field. When I moved, I noticed that there wasn’t an R User Group in the area, even though I knew of other groups in different cities and countries that were doing great things. I didn’t like the idea of not having one here, so I decided to start one myself. We just had our first event, and I’m really excited to be a part of this initiative.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Haifa?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/unnamed2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>One of the reasons I started this was to meet new people who are also R programmers or users. I already know that the community is really diverse. My city isn’t huge—around 300,000 people—but has much to offer. There are big high-tech companies like Microsoft and Amazon here that support their R&amp;D departments, and I’m certain that some of our members are involved. Like in many places in Israel, there are hundreds of small startups. What I find interesting is that people come from all sorts of backgrounds—mostly from academia, as usual, but now also from government, traditional companies, and small businesses. I’m excited to see where this leads.</p>
<p><strong>You had a</strong> <a href="https://www.meetup.com/haifa-r-user-group/events/302199640/"><strong>Meetup on August 6th, 2024</strong></a><strong>. Can you share more about the topic covered? Why this topic</strong>?&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/unnamed3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have two completely different topics and two amazing speakers. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/snazarova/?trk=public_profile_browsemap_mini-profile_title&amp;originalSubdomain=ru">Sofia Nazarova</a> is a marine biologist at <a href="https://www.ocean.org.il/en/">Israel Oceanographic &amp; Limnological</a>, who also organizes private guided tours. She teaches people about plants and animals, so she’s not a programmer. However, she co-authored the first-ever R textbook published in Russian, which makes her experience unique. Typically, I work with people who are programmers or data scientists, but she’s out there in the field, literally working with marine life.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/unnamed4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our second speaker was <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adi-sarid/?originalSubdomain=il">Adi Sarid</a>, the CEO of <a href="https://sarid-ins.com/">Sarid Institute LTD</a>, a data science company focusing on production and consumption. He’s also writing a book on R, this time in Hebrew. It’s a completely different experience—he’s a business leader working with governments and large firms, and he showcased some fantastic examples of practical applications in his talk.</p>
<p>I deliberately chose speakers with very different backgrounds because that interests me. While organizing the group, I thought about what I wanted to learn and the connections I wanted to make.</p>
<p><strong>Who was the target audience for attending this event?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>To be honest, there wasn’t a specific target audience for this event because I didn’t know anyone. I just tried to reach out to whoever might be interested in participating. After the first event, I noticed a big jump in interest, but only one woman attended. So, for the next event, I want to specifically target women and try to figure out what went wrong. It seems like many women are using R, but for some reason, they didn’t show up. We’ll address that and improve things moving forward.</p>
<p><strong>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong>&nbsp; &nbsp;</p>
<p>We didn’t use anything for the first event, which we may do with the future in mind. We wanted to stay connected, especially since we’re in Israel, and it’s important to support each other under pressure. The event went well, but after it was over, I started receiving messages from people saying they couldn’t attend because they needed to spend time with their kids or were afraid of potential security issues.</p>
<p>I realize how important it is to offer in-person meetings, but I now acknowledge that it’s not feasible for everyone. So, for the next event, we’ll make it easier for people to join remotely, perhaps through Zoom or a similar platform. We’ll also hold events in more secure locations. It’s clear that while in-person events are valuable, they aren’t always possible or suitable for everyone.</p>
<p><strong>We would like to get to know you more personally. Can you please tell me about yourself? For example, hobbies/interests or anything you want to share about yourself.</strong></p>
<p>First of all, I have a physics background and a master’s degree in it. I recently transitioned into the pharma and biotech industry, which has been a new and exciting challenge for me. My interests have always been diverse, and I’m particularly fascinated by this field, as well as by the natural beauty of Israel, especially its trees. On a different note, I’m also a harmonica player, which is another passion of mine.&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Please share any additional details you would like included in the blog.</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I want to take the initiative with the R Consortium and contribute to its efforts. I see how cool and relatively easy it is to organize such a group. Focusing on developing countries is important, but it’s also relevant here in Israel, even though we’re relatively wealthy. What motivated me was seeing others take action, and I realized that I needed to step up and organize a group as well. The tools and support provided by the R Consortium are incredibly helpful for bringing people together. So, I just wanted to say thank you for that.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/building-bridges-in-haifa-israel/unnamed4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A New R Community in Ahmedabad, India, focused on Clinical Research and Pharmaceutical Industries</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ssinojia/?originalSubdomain=in">Sanket Sinojia</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/ahmedabad-r-users-group/">Ahmedabad R User Group (ARUG).</a> With over 14 years of experience in statistical programming and data sciences in the clinical research industry, Sanket spearheaded the formation of ARUG to create a dedicated community focused on applying R in clinical research and pharmaceutical industries.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Since its official setup in 2023, ARUG has rapidly grown into a vibrant group with over 100 active members. The community fosters collaboration, knowledge-sharing, and mentorship, contributing significantly to the broader R ecosystem. Sanket’s dedication to data science and community building is evident in his efforts to organize impactful events, mentor new members, and drive the group’s growth.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I’ve been working in statistical programming and data sciences in the clinical research industry for more than 14 years, which naturally led me to explore tools that enhance data analysis and visualization. My journey with the Ahmedabad R Users Group (ARUG) began when I recognized the growing need for a dedicated community focused on applying R in our field. I was sitting with my industry friends <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/paresh-parekh-16734817">Paresh Parekh</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/paresh-p-a2352825">Paresh Paghdar</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/parin-shah-98886928">Parin Shah</a>, and <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/rapandya">Rahul Pandya</a>, discussing what we could do to bring the Ahmedabad R community together. After a few days, when we met again, I proposed setting up the ARUG. They welcomed and fully supported the vision.&nbsp;</p>
<p>While the group was initially formed in 2021, its formal setup was completed in 2023 with collaboration from the R Consortium. Since then, I’ve been organizing events, facilitating discussions, and contributing to the group’s growth. My passion for data science and community building drives my commitment to ARUG. Beyond organizing, I also mentor new members, helping them navigate the complexities of R. It’s incredibly rewarding to see the community thrive and to witness the impact of our collective efforts on advancing the field. ARUG is the first city-based group in India associated with R Consortium and the only R user group focused on Clinical Research &amp; Pharmaceutical Industries.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Ahmedabad?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Ahmedabad, a world heritage city known for its rich history and vibrant culture, is also known for its Pharma Industry. Ahmedabad is now emerging as a significant hub for clinical research, data sciences, and pharmaceutical innovation. The R community in Ahmedabad is vibrant and rapidly growing, especially within these sectors. With over 100 active members, our community is a diverse mix of seasoned professionals and enthusiastic newcomers. This diversity fosters a collaborative environment where knowledge-sharing and mentorship flourish. The enthusiasm and engagement at our events reflect the community’s dedication to advancing their skills and contributing to the broader R ecosystem. We’ve seen a significant increase in participation and interest, indicating the strong potential for R to drive innovation and efficiency in our industry. The city’s dynamic and innovative spirit resonates through our community, making it an exciting place for anyone passionate about data science and clinical research.</p>
<p><strong>You had a</strong> <a href="https://www.meetup.com/ahmedabad-r-users-group/events/302239112/"><strong>meetup on July 21st, 2024</strong></a><strong>. Can you share more about the topic covered? Why this topic?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The meetup was a highly anticipated event entitled ‘R Evolution: Shaping the Future of Clinical Trials.’ We chose this topic because it aligns perfectly with the emerging demand for R in our industry and aims to make our attendees aware of the transformative potential R brings to clinical research. Here’s a quick recap:</p>
<p>I started the event by taking attendees through the inspiring journey of the Ahmedabad R Users Group (ARUG). I shared key updates, our association with the R Consortium, and outlined ARUG’s long-term goals. The overwhelming response, with event registration filling up within 24 hours, highlighted the high expectations and enthusiasm of our attendees!</p>
<p><a href="http://linkedin.com/in/sassavvy">Sunil Gupta</a>, a renowned industry expert, delivered an incredible presentation on ‘R Made Easier for SAS Programmers.’ His insights, tips, and tricks on transitioning to R were invaluable, offering a comprehensive learning experience.</p>
<p>Following his session, we enjoyed a vibrant networking session, making new connections and reconnecting with old friends.</p>
<p><a href="http://linkedin.com/in/chintan-patel-291a3553">Chintan Patel</a> captivated us with a simplified demonstration of creating Kaplan Meier Plots using R. His comprehensive topic coverage inspired many to delve deeper into graphing with R.</p>
<p><a href="http://linkedin.com/in/miteshpatel5056">Mitesh Patel</a> then presented ‘R Shiny in Action,’ explaining the fundamentals and applications of R Shiny, complete with a live demonstration of three case studies. His session highlighted R Shiny’s potential as a game-changer in data visualization.</p>
<p>I then hosted a dynamic round table discussion on conferences, joined by <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/parin-shah-98886928">Parin Shah</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/purvi-kalra-csm%C2%AE-8b506a14/?originalSubdomain=in">Purvi Kalra</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/saumil-tripathi-40a90b65/">Saumil Tripathi</a>. They shared invaluable tips on conference preparation, R trends, and enhancing presentation confidence.</p>
<p>Finally, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/krupa-trivedi-a2517515a">Krupa Trivedi</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/nidhi-shah-73815715a">Nidhi Shah</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nikunj-kothari/?originalSubdomain=in">Nikunj Kothari</a> organized a thrilling ‘Test Your R Skills’ quiz. The live, time-bound quiz with an instant leaderboard brought a fun and competitive spirit to the hall.</p>
<p>The event wrapped up with <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/rapandya">Rahul Pandya</a>’s vote of thanks, where we celebrated our presenters, the ARUG event team, and quiz winners.</p>
<p>The ARUG Event Team – <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/ankit-vadodaria-b775a961">Ankit Vadodariya</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/dishant-parikh-6b893954">Dishant Parikh</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/krupali-prashant-0b94232a">Krupali Ladani</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/krupa-trivedi-a2517515a">Krupa Trivedi</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/nidhi-shah-73815715a">Nidhi Shah</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/nikunj-kothari">Nikunj Kothari</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/paresh-p-a2352825">Paresh Paghdar</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/paresh-parekh-16734817">Paresh Parekh</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/parin-shah-98886928">Parin Shah</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/purvi-kalra-csm%C2%AE-8b506a14">Purvi Kalra</a>, <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/rapandya">Rahul Pandya</a>, and <a href="http://linkedin.com/in/ssinojia">Sanket Sinojia</a> – successfully organized the entire event. Their hard work and dedication ensured a seamless and impactful experience for all attendees.</p>
<p><strong>Who was the target audience for attending this event?</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed4.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our target audience primarily includes professionals and researchers from the clinical and pharmaceutical industries. This encompasses data scientists, statistical programmers, biostatisticians, clinical trial analysts, and anyone interested in leveraging R for data analysis and visualization in these fields. We also welcome newcomers who are eager to learn and contribute to this dynamic industry. By targeting this specific audience, we ensure our content is highly relevant and impactful, addressing real-world challenges and opportunities our members face. Additionally, our events offer networking opportunities that can lead to collaborations.</p>
<p><strong>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed6.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>For planning and executing our events, we rely on a combination of tools such as <a href="https://github.com/ssinojia/ARUG/tree/main">GitHub</a> for collaborative project management and repositories, Zoom for virtual sessions, and <a href="https://www.meetup.com/ahmedabad-r-users-group/">Meetup</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/arug/about/">LinkedIn ARUG</a> pages for continuous engagement and communication. These tools not only streamline our processes but also enhance accessibility. By utilizing these technologies, we can include members who cannot attend physical events, making our group more inclusive. We share our event summaries and slides on GitHub, ensuring that valuable information is accessible to all members. Additionally, we are considering recording sessions and sharing them on platforms like YouTube to further extend the reach of our events. Using these tools also allows us to gather feedback and improve future events, ensuring we meet the evolving needs of our community. This approach helps us maintain a vibrant and connected community, regardless of geographical limitations.</p>
<p><strong>We would like to get to know you more personally. Can you please tell me about yourself? For example, hobbies/interests or anything you want to share about yourself.</strong></p>
<p>Outside of my professional life, I have several passions that I pursue with great enthusiasm. I enjoy blogging and sharing my thoughts on data science, industry trends, and personal reflections. The mountains always call me, and I find peace and inspiration in hiking and exploring nature. Additionally, I write poetry in my local language, allowing me to express my creativity and connect with my cultural roots. These hobbies provide a balanced and enriching life, complementing my professional endeavors.</p>
<p>Apart from ARUG, I volunteer with organizations like <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/">CDISC</a>, <a href="https://phuse.global/">PHUSE</a>, <a href="https://pharmaverse.org/">Pharmaverse</a>, and <a href="https://rinpharma.com/">RinPharma</a>, contributing to various projects such as <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/standards/foundational/sdtmig/sdtmig-v3-4">SDTM IG v3.4 development</a>, <a href="https://www.cdisc.org/primer">CDISC Primer development</a>, and <a href="https://learn.rinpharma.com/shiny4submissions.html">Shiny for Submission</a>. These experiences offer me a unique perspective and a sense of tranquility that I bring into my work, enhancing my creativity and problem-solving abilities. Engaging in these activities helps me maintain a holistic approach to my professional and personal life.</p>
<p>I cherish spending time with my family, especially with my adorable daughter Saanvi. My better half, Niza, always supports and encourages me in all aspects of life. She is dedicated to taking care of our family and provides unwavering support that allows me to pursue my passions and professional goals.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join">How do I Join?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/a-new-r-community-in-ahmedabad/unnamed.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R Consortium Grants Committee Announces New Chair</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rconsortium-grants-comittee-announces-new-chair/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rconsortium-grants-comittee-announces-new-chair/images/Katherine.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The R Consortium is pleased to announce that Katherine Jeschke has been appointed Chair of the Grants Committee.</p>
<p>She will oversee day-to-day grant processes for both pre- and post-awards, ensuring grants meet the R Consortium’s strategic objectives. Katherine will report to the Executive Director and work closely with the Infrastructure Steering Committee and the RUGS program to track grants and help improve the effectiveness of R Consortium grants in supporting the R Community.</p>
<p>Katherine’s non-profit grants and administration skills were honed over more than 25 years of experience in marketing communications, and staff, budget, development, and grants management for non-profits and trade organizations, as well as corporate and public sector consulting organizations.</p>
<p>She holds an MA degree in American History and Museum Administration from George Washington University and a BA degree in Fine Arts and Art History from the University of Maryland.</p>
<p>“Getting acquainted with our various grants and procedures while evaluating the strategic effectiveness of R Consortium grants is a big undertaking, but her background and years of experience should ease her way,” said Joseph Rickert, Executive Director of the R Consortium.</p>
<p>She may be reached at kj.jeschke@posit.co</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/rconsortium-grants-comittee-announces-new-chair/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/rconsortium-grants-comittee-announces-new-chair/images/Katherine-blog2.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="58" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pharma RUG: The Rise of R in China’s Pharmaceutical Industry</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>PharmaRUG, China organizer <a href="https://shajoezhu.github.io/">Joe Zhu</a>, spoke with the R Consortium about the growing R community and the increasing use of R in the pharmaceutical industry in China. The group has contributed to the pharmaceutical R community through several R packages. Since its establishment last year, the group has organized large-scale hybrid events. Joe also shared some tools and techniques for smoothly organizing and running hybrid events.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/unnamed.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong><em>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</em></strong></p>
<p>I have a PhD in statistics and studied in New Zealand for my undergraduate and postgraduate degrees in statistics. My PhD work focused on theoretical coalescent theory and probabilistic modeling for phylogenetics models. I also completed a postdoc at Oxford, focusing on statistical genomics for the human genome and malaria parasite genome projects. During this time, I developed open source software tools for statistical genomics, primarily using R as a front end and developing C++ software.</p>
<p>For the past four years, I’ve worked at <a href="https://www.roche.com/innovation/structure/rnd-locations/pharma-shanghai">Roche</a>, where I started leading a major collaboration initiative in pharma three years ago. I’ve created TLG (table, listing, and figures) for regulatory submissions to the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/">FDA</a>. Throughout this initiative, we have open sourced around 30 software packages, including `<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/formatters/index.html">formatters</a>`, `<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rtables/index.html">rtables</a>`, `<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/rlistings/index.html">rlistings</a>` and `<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tern/index.html">tern</a>`. Last year, we submitted these packages to CRAN.</p>
<p>At first, we open sourced the project on GitHub and then submitted it to <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/">CRAN</a>. I’m heavily involved in one of China’s R user groups, PharmaRUG. We use the group to share posts about developments in the area, and we organize events and conferences. In March last year, we hosted the first <a href="https://pharmarug.github.io/pharmarug-2023/">event</a> with over 100 people on-site and around 100 online. The event covered topics like R package usage in the pharma industry. Later that year, we organized another event called “<a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/nest-2023-summeR/">Open Source Clinical Reporting summeR</a>“.&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/unnamed2.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Lately, I have been busy organizing several events. I recently gave a talk (about R package dependencies as directed in acyclic graphs) at a conference hosted by the R community in China. Early next month, on August 1st, I will attend a <a href="https://pharmarug.github.io/pharmasug2024-r-workshop/">pharma conference</a> where I will conduct a workshop on good practices in software package development. The conference schedule is quite packed for me as I also have a session on how teams operate and collaborate within the Pharma industry to develop R packages. On the third day of the conference, I will organize a series of 11 data visualization talks, one of which is about Python. Most of the talks will focus on using R, except for one discussion on Python.</p>
<p><strong><em>Can you share what the R community is like in China?</em></strong>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/unnamed3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have opened up seats for students to join our events in the pharmaceutical industry. In the past, fewer than 20 students, mostly from academia, have joined us for these conferences. The events include big names like Roche, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Novartis, Boehringer Ingelheim, and Sanofi and local companies such as Fosun, Hengrui, and Legend Biotech. There is a big R community in China across academia and industry. Our user group primarily focuses on the pharma industry. Our <a href="https://www.wechat.com/">WeChat</a> channel has nearly a thousand subscribers, and our group chat has almost 500 members. It’s a very active community.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Later this year, we will collaborate with the “<a href="https://rinpharma.com/">R in Pharma</a>” for the October conference. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/danielsabanesbove/?originalSubdomain=ch">Daniel Sabanes Bove</a> and I have contacted Harvey and Phil, and we will organize an APAC track, including India, China, Japan, Australia, Singapore, and Korea.&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong><em>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</em></strong></p>
<p>We have created a GitHub account called <a href="https://github.com/pharmarug">PharmaRUG</a>. We use this platform to share websites, posts, slides, and videos related to our events. The <a href="https://pharmarug.github.io/pharmarug-2024/">Pharma RUG 2024</a> conference was particularly successful this year, thanks to the support from the R Consortium. We also utilize WeChat groups to call for speakers and interact with others. In addition to GitHub and WeChat, we use <a href="https://www.tencentcloud.com/document/product">Tencent Docs</a> to share documents. This is particularly useful in China, where using company-specific platforms like Google or Microsoft can be hindered by firewalls. Tencent Docs works perfectly in China, making sharing and synchronizing documents easy.</p>
<p><strong><em>Can you share some valuable tips for organizing succesful Hybrid events?</em></strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/unnamed4.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We have a series of planning sessions where we actively communicate using WeChat. We meet at a community center where everyone is open, and we have preset meetings. We test the audio and everything beforehand. This is our second year organizing these events, so we have gained more experience. We are now familiar with the standards and know what needs to be done. For example, when two companies, like MNCs, use different systems, we find it better to use one shared system to ensure everything is synchronized.</p>
<p>We’ve found that <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-teams/group-chat-software">Microsoft Teams</a> is easy to use for setting up meetings and scheduling them ahead of time. For live demos, we recommend pre-recording the demos and taking questions. In the case of hybrid sessions with multiple locations, we prioritize asking and answering questions based on the primary and secondary locations, as well as online participation. If we cannot answer questions quickly, we host Q&amp;A sessions afterward and share them online.</p>
<p>I believe that for the event to be successful, timing is crucial. We must stick to the schedule because it’s a hybrid event. However, we should also allow for some flexibility when unexpected things come up. We haven’t created a YouTube account yet because YouTube isn’t accessible in China. One alternative could be setting up a Bilibili web page and account to share the videos. All our files are currently on GitHub, which is convenient. We need to trim the videos to smaller sizes to fit GitHub’s file size limits, maybe at four and a half speeds or similar.</p>
<p><strong><em>What trends do you currently see in R language and your industry?</em></strong></p>
<p>So, <a href="https://www.sas.com/en_us/home.html">SAS</a> has dominated the software space for the Pharma industry for decades. While it used to be used for exploratory and research purposes, there have been successes with using Office to support missions in recent years. Roche also has success stories in this area. There are several initiatives, with <a href="https://pharmaverse.org/">PharmaVerse</a> being a significant player. Roche is part of PharmaVerse, taking inspiration from the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/">tidyverse</a> multiverse concept. The end-to-end clinical reporting process is considered in this space, from data preparation to TLG generations. A lot has happened in the past three to four years, especially in China last year. There’s been significant development in China, and you can see a shift from SAS to R in the tools used. At the PharmaSUG meeting, which was previously dominated by SAS users, in the past few years, a quarter to one-third of the tools are using languages other than SAS. It’s clear that things are moving away from SAS towards software languages like R.</p>
<p>This year, I don’t have the complete statistics with me right now, but you do see a lot of topics. In my session, I’m sharing, and you know, many talks use visualization because it’s much likable. So, the trend is that R is becoming more acceptable than before, from PLCs to things in production. There are very high standards for codes and validation.</p>
<p>In the end, I would like to thank my dear friends and colleagues for their support and for making this happen</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yan-qiao-55877117/">Yan Qiao</a>, Associate Director of Scientific Programming, Beigene,&nbsp;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/baoqing-li-09a8b5167/">Baoqin Li</a>, China Head Clinical &amp; Statical Programming, Johnson &amp; Johnson</li>
<li>Dong Guo, China head of Stats Analyst, Eli-lilly&amp;Company</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yun-ma-79220629/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Egoogle%2Ecom%2F&amp;originalSubdomain=cn">Yun Ma</a>, Director, clinical data Sciences, Boehringer Ingelheim (china) Investment Co.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yanli-chang-00b765145/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Egoogle%2Ecom%2F&amp;originalSubdomain=cn">Yanli Chang</a>, Head of Data Operations China, Novartis</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>How do I Join?</strong></p>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/pharma-rug-the-rise-of-r/unnamed.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R-Ladies Rome: Empowering Women in Data Science Through Collaboration and Innovation</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://federicagazzelloni.com/">Federica Gazzelloni</a>, co-organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-rome/">R-Ladies Rome</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the fast-growing R community in Rome. The group collaborates with R user groups worldwide and has successfully attracted a diverse audience to its events. Federica also contributes to the R community through package development and is currently working on a book about using R for health metrics and tracking the spread of infectious diseases.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/federica.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The group is hosting an online event titled <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-rome/events/302078600/">“Building Reproducible Pipelines with R, Docker, and Nix”</a> on the 29th of July. R users from around the world are invited to attend this event.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/bruno.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong><em>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</em></strong></p>
<p>I am Federica Gazzelloni, an actuary and statistician interested in health studies. I am writing a book about health metrics and the spread of infectious diseases. As the lead organizer of R-Ladies Rome, one of the R user groups sponsored by the R Consortium, I am grateful for the support that enables us to organize monthly talks, tutorials, and workshops. Our events provide an inclusive and accessible learning environment free of charge, featuring exciting speakers and various engagement opportunities. Additionally, we have held events in partnership with <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2023/07/24/use-of-r-in-non-profit-social-policy-research-in-new-york">R-Ladies New York</a>, <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2023/11/16/highlights-from-r-ladies-paris-hybrid-meetup-empowering-community-outreach">R-Ladies Paris</a>, and <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2024/04/26/bridging-gaps-tunis-r-user-groups-journey-in-democratizing-r-in-bioinformatics">Tunis R User Group</a> and created a branded website: <a href="https://rladiesrome.org/">rladiesrome.org</a>!</p>
<p>R-Ladies Rome started in 2023 and has grown significantly since then. Our events consistently reach a substantial audience. For instance, our latest event with <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/blog/2024/07/03/diving-into-r-with-isabella-velasquez-perspectives-from-r-ladies-seattle">Isabella Velasquez</a> garnered over 100 RSVPs. During Data Viz Month, we received unexpected attention from the open tech community of learners. Our followers on Meetup have reached over 1.1k, and our social media presence is steadily growing.</p>
<p><strong><em>Can you share what the R community is like in Rome? </em></strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/r-ladies.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Since the kick-off of the chapter in 2023, R-Ladies Rome has played a pivotal role in fostering a dynamic community. We have successfully brought together an international group of R enthusiasts, ranging from beginners to experienced data scientists, creating a supportive and engaging environment for all. The popularity of the R language within the open source community, particularly for statistical analysis and medical research, is evident in Rome. R offers a wide range of libraries that can be easily applied to various topics, making it very convenient for users. Although Python is gaining attention in research and providing another accessible option for statistical analysis, the medical statistical community seems to prefer R over Python due to its extensive capabilities and strong community support.</p>
<p>Our events have consistently attracted significant attention and participation. For example, our latest event with Isabella Velasquez garnered over 100 RSVPs. We have also received unexpected attention during Data Viz Month from the open tech community of learners. Our Meetup followers have reached over 1.1k, and our social media presence is steadily growing.</p>
<p>The R community in Rome is expected to grow, with R-Ladies Rome at its heart, driving engagement and promoting the use of R for various applications. We are excited to continue growing and evolving, providing valuable learning opportunities and fostering connections within the community.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/unnamed.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/unnamed (1).png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong><em>What trends do you currently see in R language?</em></strong></p>
<p>We have reviewed all the events that R-Ladies’ groups have organized in the past years and, after considering the rebranding of RStudio to <a href="https://posit.co/">Posit</a> PBC and <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">RMarkdown</a> to <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>, realized that several exciting trends in the R language are shaping its usage and development within the data science community. Analyzing event titles, attendee numbers, and activity on past recordings, we found that events containing “Introduction” or “Tutorials” impact learners most, highlighting the growing interest in learning R for data analytics, reproducible research, and dynamic reporting.</p>
<p>Moreover, integrating R with other programming languages and platforms is gaining significant attention. The interoperability between R and languages like Python, HTML, or Java allows users to enhance their skills across multiple tools within a single environment. This has expanded R’s capabilities, making it a versatile choice for a diverse range of users.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/collage.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong><em>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</em></strong></p>
<p>We’ve been using <del><a href="https://www.canva.com/">Canva</a></del> extensively for various tasks and found <del><a href="https://openai.com/index/chatgpt/">ChatGPT</a></del> very helpful in crafting storytelling content. To enhance the planning and execution of events, <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">Copilot</a> assists with its excellent collaborative typing, saving time. Additionally, having a Meetup pro-account is valuable, mainly as <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-rome/">R-Ladies Rome</a> is part of the broader R Ladies group. It helps us connect with a wider audience while using Google Forms aids communication and prevents missing information. We also use <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@rladiesrome">YouTube</a> and have our channel, which is very useful for sharing past events recordings and making them available online to ensure accessibility for those unable to attend live events.</p>
<p><strong><em>You have a Meetup on <em>“<a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-rome/events/302078600/">Building reproducible pipelines with R, Docker and Nix</a>”</em>, can you share more on the topic covered? Why this topic? </em></strong></p>
<p>We have an upcoming Meetup titled “Building reproducible pipelines with R, Docker and Nix” , featuring speaker <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brodriguesco/">Bruno Rodrigues</a>. This topic was chosen based on feedback from our organizers, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/silacos/">Silvana Acosta</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rafaelagrlucas/">Rafael Ribeiro</a>, who polled our audience to identify a favorite speaker. Bruno Rodrigues emerged as a popular choice, highlighting the growing interest in robust and reproducible data science workflows.</p>
<p>In this session, Bruno Rodrigues will guide us through setting up reproducible data pipelines using R, <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a>, and <a href="https://nixos.org/">Nix</a>. These tools ensure that data analyses are consistent and can be easily shared and replicated across different environments. By learning to use Docker and Nix alongside R, our community members will gain valuable skills to enhance the reliability and reproducibility of their data science projects. This event aligns with our mission to provide practical and impactful learning opportunities that meet the evolving needs of the data science community.</p>
<p><strong><em>Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</em></strong></p>
<p>One of the key projects I am currently working on involves a quarto-book titled “<em>Health Metrics and the Spread of Infectious Diseases with R”</em>, which CRC Press will publish at the end of this year. This book aims to provide comprehensive insights into the intersection of health metrics, such as DALYs and infectious disease dynamics, using advanced statistical methods and machine learning techniques in R. The goal is to equip readers with the knowledge and tools to analyze and interpret health data effectively, thereby contributing to the broader field of public health.</p>
<p>In addition to the book, I have developed a couple of R data packages to aid in data analysis and visualization. One is “<a href="https://github.com/Fgazzelloni/oregonfrogs">oregonfrogs</a>,” which is expected to go on CRAN very soon. This package focuses on classification modeling for detecting frog habitats, utilizing spatial techniques. It provides a valuable function, <a href="https://fgazzelloni.github.io/oregonfrogs/reference/longlat_to_utm.html">longlat_to_utm()</a>. The development of these packages showcases R’s versatility in handling complex ecological data and emphasizes the importance of open source tools in advancing scientific research. Through these projects, I aim to demonstrate the practical applications of R in public health and environmental science, fostering a deeper understanding and appreciation of data-driven methodologies.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-join" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-join"><strong>How do I Join?</strong></h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 68,000 members in 33 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<!-- watermark -->
<div style="background-color:#FFFFFF">
<p style="color:#FFFFFF; font-size: 1px">
gd2md-html: xyzzy Mon Jul 29 2024
</p>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/r-user-group-support-program">Learn more</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-ladies-rome-empowering-women-in-data-science-through-collaboration-and-innovation/unnamed%20(2).png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
