<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>R Consortium</title>
<link>https://r-consortium.org/blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://r-consortium.org/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.31</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Reproducibility Without Containers: Bruno Rodrigues Introduces Nix and the {rix} R Package</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium Community Assistant, Caitlyn Oda</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/brunoheadshot.jpeg" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<p>At a <a href="https://r-consortium.org/webinars/rix-reproducible-data-science-environments-with-nix.html">recent R Medicine webinar hosted by the R Consortium</a>, Bruno Rodrigues, Head of the Statistics and Data Strategy Departments at Luxembourg’s Ministry of Research and Higher Education, presented an innovative approach to reproducibility in R: one that eliminates the complexity of containerization, works seamlessly across systems, and offers analysis reproducibility for years into the future.</p>
<hr>
<section id="the-challenge-of-reproducibility-in-data-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-challenge-of-reproducibility-in-data-science">The Challenge of Reproducibility in Data Science</h3>
<p>Reproducibility is a cornerstone of scientific research, yet achieving it in data science remains challenging. Rodrigues explains that reproducibility is on a continuum and depends on 4 factors: the version of R, package versions, operating systems, and hardware. Traditional tools like <code>{renv}</code> capture R package dependencies but fall short in tracking system-level libraries or the R interpreter itself. In my own work, I’ve utilized <code>{renv}</code>to import packages for implementing tables for R-powered websites. Containerization tools like Docker offer more comprehensive encapsulation but come with their own complexities and do not guarantee deterministic builds.</p>
<p>Rodrigues emphasized that true reproducibility requires capturing the entire computational environment, including system libraries, compilers, and the operating system. This holistic approach ensures that analyses can be rerun with identical results, regardless of changes in the software ecosystem.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/continuum.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="nix-a-functional-package-manager-for-reproducible-builds" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nix-a-functional-package-manager-for-reproducible-builds">Nix: A Functional Package Manager for Reproducible Builds</h3>
<p>Nix is a cross-platform package manager designed for reproducibility. It allows users to define environments declaratively, ensuring that builds are deterministic and environments can be recreated identically across different systems and over time. Nix manages not just R packages but also system dependencies, making it a comprehensive solution for reproducible research.</p>
<p>Rodrigues highlighted that Nix’s approach to package management eliminates issues related to hidden dependencies and environment drift, common pitfalls in data science workflows.</p>
<p>“Nix really makes it possible to reach this gold standard of reproducibility.”</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/nix.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="introducing-rix-bridging-r-and-nix" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introducing-rix-bridging-r-and-nix">Introducing <code>{rix}</code>: Bridging R and Nix</h3>
<p>To make Nix more accessible to R users, Rodrigues developed <code>{rix}</code>, an R package that simplifies the creation of reproducible environments using Nix. With <code>{rix}</code>, users can generate Nix expressions directly from R, specifying the R version, required packages, system dependencies, and preferred IDEs.</p>
<p>The core function, <code>rix()</code>, generates a <code>default.nix</code> file, which Nix uses to build the environment. This process ensures that the entire software stack, from the R interpreter to system libraries, is captured and can be reproduced reliably.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/rix.jpeg" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-magic-of-rix" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-magic-of-rix">The “Magic” of <code>{rix}</code></h3>
<p>One of the standout features of <code>{rix}</code> is its ability to “freeze” environments in time. By specifying a particular date, users can recreate the exact state of CRAN and Bioconductor repositories as they existed on that day. This temporal pinning ensures that analyses remain reproducible, even as packages evolve.</p>
<p>Rodrigues described this capability as the “magic” of <code>{rix}</code>, allowing researchers to maintain consistent environments without manual intervention.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="key-advantages-of-rix" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-advantages-of-rix">Key Advantages of <code>{rix}</code></h3>
<p>Rodrigues highlighted two critical benefits of using <code>{rix}</code>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>No Need for Pre-installed R</strong>: Once the Nix expression is generated, the environment can be built using Nix alone, eliminating the need for R to be pre-installed on the system. This feature is particularly useful for deploying environments on CI/CD systems or sharing with collaborators.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Seamless Integration with Docker</strong>: While Nix ensures reproducibility, Docker offers portability. <code>{rix}</code> allows users to wrap Nix-built environments into Docker containers, combining the strengths of both tools for long-term preservation and distribution.</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="real-world-applications-and-future-developments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="real-world-applications-and-future-developments">Real-world Applications and Future Developments</h3>
<p>Rodrigues demonstrated how <code>{rix}</code> can be used to create environments that include IDEs like RStudio or VS Code, as well as additional languages like Python and Rust. One example where <code>{rix}</code> could come into play is the R Consortium website, which is published using Quarto, and uses RStudio and <code>{renv}</code> as a main part of the workflow. The content is pushed to GitHub where it’s published using GitHub Actions. These environments can be deployed across various platforms, including CI/CD pipelines, ensuring consistent and reproducible workflows.</p>
<p>Looking ahead, Rodrigues is developing <code>{rixpress}</code>, a companion package inspired by <code>{targets}</code>. <code>{rixpress}</code> aims to facilitate the creation of reproducible analytical pipelines, further enhancing the capabilities of <code>{rix}</code> and Nix in data science projects.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="getting-started-with-rix" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="getting-started-with-rix">Getting Started with <code>{rix}</code></h3>
<p>To begin using <code>{rix}</code>, install the package from CRAN:</p>
<p>R<br>
Copy code<br>
<code>install.packages("rix")</code></p>
<p>Then, generate a Nix expression for your project:</p>
<p>R<br>
Copy code<br>
<code>library(rix)</code></p>
<p><code>rix(</code><br>
<code>date = "2024-12-14",</code><br>
<code>r_pkgs = c("dplyr", "ggplot2"),</code><br>
<code>system_pkgs = NULL,</code><br>
<code>git_pkgs = NULL,</code><br>
<code>ide = "code",</code><br>
<code>project_path = ".",</code><br>
<code>overwrite = TRUE,</code><br>
<code>print = TRUE</code><br>
<code>)</code></p>
<p>This command creates a <code>default.nix</code> file and an <code>.Rprofile</code>, setting up a reproducible environment tailored to your project’s needs.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="resources" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="resources">Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Bruno Rodrigues’s Slides</strong>: <a href="https://b-rodrigues.github.io/r-medicine-rix/#/title-slide\">https://b-rodrigues.github.io/r-medicine-rix/#/title-slide</a><br>
</li>
<li><strong>GitHub Repository</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/ropensci/rix">https://github.com/ropensci/rix</a><br>
</li>
<li><strong>CRAN Package</strong>: <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=rix">https://cran.r-project.org/package=rix</a><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Documentation</strong>: <a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/rix">https://docs.ropensci.org/rix</a><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Webinar Recording</strong>: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jhiRNQHbEXo">R/Medicine YouTube Channel</a><br>
</li>
<li><strong>Bruno Rodrigues’s Blog</strong>: <a href="https://brodrigues.co">https://brodrigues.co</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/reproducibility-without-containers-bruno-rodrigues-introduces-nix-and-the-rix-r-package/rix-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="78" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A unifying toolbox for handling persistence data</title>
  <dc:creator>Aymeric Stamm, Jason Cory Brunson</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="topological-data-analysis-in-r" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="topological-data-analysis-in-r">Topological data analysis in R</h2>
<p>Topological data analysis (TDA) is a rapidly growing field that uses techniques from algebraic topology to analyze the shape and structure of data. At its core, TDA provides tools to understand the geometric and topological features of datasets across multiple scales, with persistent homology (PH) being one of its fundamental techniques.</p>
<p>Several R packages have emerged to provide TDA capabilities to the R community, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=TDA">{TDA}</a> which focuses on statistical analysis of PH and density clustering by providing an R interface for the efficient algorithms of the C++ libraries <a href="https://project.inria.fr/gudhi/software/">GUDHI</a>, <a href="https://www.mrzv.org/software/dionysus/">Dionysus</a> and <a href="https://bitbucket.org/phat-code/phat/">PHAT</a>. This package also implements methods from <span class="citation" data-cites="fasy2014confidence">Fasy et al. (2014)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="chazal2014stochastic">Chazal et al. (2014)</span> for analyzing the statistical significance of PH features.</li>
<li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=TDAstats">{TDAstats}</a> which provides a comprehensive toolset for conducting TDA, specifically via the calculation of PH in a Vietoris-Rips complex <span class="citation" data-cites="wadhwa2018tdastats">(Wadhwa et al. 2018)</span>.</li>
<li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=ripserr">{ripserr}</a> which provides an R interface to the <a href="https://github.com/Ripser/ripser">Ripser</a> and <a href="https://github.com/CubicalRipser">Cubical Ripser</a> C++ libraries <span class="citation" data-cites="bauer2021ripser kaji2020cubical">(Bauer 2021; Kaji, Sudo, and Ahara 2020)</span>.</li>
<li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=TDAkit">{TDAkit}</a> which provides a variety of algorithms to learn with PH of the data based on functional summaries for clustering, hypothesis testing, and visualization <span class="citation" data-cites="wasserman2018topological">(Wasserman 2018)</span>.</li>
<li>Other packages that have been archived due to lack of maintenance (e.g. <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=kernelTDA">{kernelTDA}</a>).</li>
</ul>
<p>While these packages have made TDA more accessible, they’ve also introduced different data structures for representing persistence data, creating challenges for interoperability and workflow consistency. Moreover, workflows using tools from different packages will rely on some of the same low-level operations, like computing PH and calculating distances between persistence diagrams. When each package is built for purpose, this will lead to either duplication or cascading dependencies.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/">{phutil}</a> package addresses such fragmentation by providing a unified toolbox for handling persistence data. It offers consistent data structures and methods that work seamlessly with outputs from various TDA packages. As part of the <a href="https://github.com/tdaverse">TDAverse</a> initiative, {phutil} contributes to creating a coherent ecosystem for topological data analysis in R.</p>
</section>
<section id="minimal-mathematical-background" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="minimal-mathematical-background">Minimal mathematical background</h2>
<section id="persistent-homology" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="persistent-homology">Persistent homology</h3>
<p>The {phutil} <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/articles/validation-benchmark.html#definitions">documentation</a> provides an overview of persistent homology. For now, know that the result of this procedure is a <strong>persistence diagram</strong>: a multiset (set with multiplicity) of points in the plane—usually the upper-half plane and most often the first quadrant. Persistence diagrams encode topological features of different dimensions, and a single diagram may encode features of one or all dimensions. By <strong>persistence data</strong>, we mean a data structure that encodes diagrams of all dimensions, and possibly many diagrams coming from data sets of a common type.</p>
</section>
<section id="distances-between-persistence-diagrams" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="distances-between-persistence-diagrams">Distances between persistence diagrams</h3>
<p>Two persistence diagrams <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> are canonically compared using <strong>Wasserstein distances</strong>. These are a family of metrics determined by a <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?q">-Minkowski distance on the plane and a <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?p">-norm on the distances between pairs of points matched via some <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cvarphi%20:%20X%20%5Cto%20Y">:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%20%5Cleft(%20%5Csum_%7Bx%20%5Cin%20X%7D%7B%7B%5ClVert%0Ax-%5Cvarphi(x)%20%5CrVert_q%7D%5Ep%7D%20%5Cright)%5E%7B1/p%7D%20"></p>
<p>The distance <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?W_p%5Eq(X,Y)"> is defined to be the infimum of this expression over all possible matchings. See the <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/articles/validation-benchmark.html">vignette</a> on distances for more detail, or <span class="citation" data-cites="cohen2010lipschitz">Cohen-Steiner et al. (2010)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="bubenik2023exact">Bubenik, Scott, and Stanley (2023)</span> for detailed treatments and stability results on these families of metrics.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="implementations-in-phutil" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implementations-in-phutil">Implementations in {phutil}</h2>
<p>The {phutil} package aims at serving as a low-level package that defines a unifying toolbox for handling persistence data. This section describes the class that has been implemented to handle a single persistence diagram as well as the distances between persistence diagrams. The package also provides a class of persistence data that can be used to store multiple diagrams, which is simply a list of persistence diagrams. This class is not described here, but will be the backbone of the forthcoming {inphr} package for making inference on persistence diagrams.</p>
<section id="the-persistence-class" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-persistence-class">The <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/reference/persistence.html"><code>persistence</code></a> class</h3>
<p>The ‘persistence’ class is a list with the following components:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><code>pairs</code>: A list of 2-column matrices containing birth-death pairs. The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?i">-<em>th</em> element of the list corresponds to the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?(i-1)">-<em>th</em> homology dimension. If there is no pairs for a given dimension but there are pairs in higher dimensions, the corresponding element(s) is/are filled with a <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?0%20%5Ctimes%202"> numeric matrix.</p></li>
<li><p><code>metadata</code>: A list of length 6 containing information about how the data was computed:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>orderered_pairs</code>: A boolean indicating whether the pairs in the <code>pairs</code> list are ordered (i.e.&nbsp;the first column is strictly less than the second column).</li>
<li><code>data</code>: The name of the object containing the original data on which the persistence data was computed.</li>
<li><code>engine</code>: The name of the package and the function of this package that computed the persistence data in the form <code>"package_name::package_function"</code>.</li>
<li><code>filtration</code>: The filtration used in the computation in a human-readable format (i.e.&nbsp;full names, capitals where need, etc.).</li>
<li><code>parameters</code>: A list of parameters used in the computation.</li>
<li><code>call</code>: The exact call that generated the persistence data.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>Currently, the following <code>S3</code> methods for objects of class <code>persistence</code> have been implemented:</p>
<ul>
<li>coercers from matrix, data.frame, objects of class ‘diagram’ as produced by <code>TDA::*Diag()</code> functions, objects of class ‘PHom’ as produced by <code>ripserr::vietoris_rips()</code> and objects of class ‘hclust’ as produced by <code>stats::hclust()</code>;</li>
<li><code>format()</code> and <code>print()</code> which use the MIT-licensed <a href="https://cli.r-lib.org">{cli}</a> package behind the scene for printing out to the console a nice colourful but brief summary of the persistence data;</li>
<li><code>get_pairs()</code> to extract homological features from a specific dimension;</li>
<li>reverse coercers to go back to either matrix or data.frame representations.</li>
</ul>
<p>Some more details about how these coercers work can be found in the dedicated <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/articles/persistence-class.html">vignette</a> on the website of the package.</p>
<p>For instance, one can start by some simulated point cloud using the <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/tdaunif/">{tdaunif}</a> package:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1">point_data <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> tdaunif<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sample_ellipse</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">n =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">100</span>L, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ar =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-point-data" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-fig-align="center">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-point-data-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/index_files/figure-html/fig-point-data-1.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="672">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-point-data-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;1: A sample of 100 points drawn uniformly on the contour of an ellispe.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>A typical workflow would be to compute the persistence data from the point cloud shown in Figure&nbsp;1 using the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/TDA/index.html">{TDA}</a> package:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">ph_data <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> TDA<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ripsDiag</span>(</span>
<span id="cb2-2">    point_data,</span>
<span id="cb2-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">maxdimension =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>L,</span>
<span id="cb2-4">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">maxscale =</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.5</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5">)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="center">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div id="fig-ph-data" class="quarto-float quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored" data-fig-align="center">
<figure class="quarto-float quarto-float-fig figure">
<div aria-describedby="fig-ph-data-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
<img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/index_files/figure-html/fig-ph-data-1.png" class="img-fluid quarto-figure quarto-figure-center figure-img" width="672">
</div>
<figcaption class="quarto-float-caption-bottom quarto-float-caption quarto-float-fig" id="fig-ph-data-caption-0ceaefa1-69ba-4598-a22c-09a6ac19f8ca">
Figure&nbsp;2: Persistence data computed from the point cloud shown in Figure&nbsp;1.
</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The output that is displayed in Figure&nbsp;2 is a list with a component <code>diagram</code> that contains the persistence data in the form of an aobject of class ‘diagram’. The latter is a 3-column matrix with the first column containing the dimension of the homological feature, the second column containing the birth time and the third column containing the death time. The column names</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">colnames</span>(ph_data<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>diagram)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] "dimension" "Birth"     "Death"    </code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>mix lower and upper cases. Finally the object also has attributes:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">names</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">attributes</span>(ph_data<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>diagram))</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] "dim"          "dimnames"     "class"        "maxdimension" "scale"       
[6] "call"        </code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>that store information about how the diagram has been computed. The <code>persistence</code> class can coerce the ‘diagram’ object into a ‘persistence’ object:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb7" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb7-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(phutil)</span>
<span id="cb7-2">ph_data_pers <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as_persistence</span>(ph_data<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span>diagram)</span>
<span id="cb7-3">ph_data_pers</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>
── Persistence Data ────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
ℹ There are 100 and 2 pairs in dimensions 0 and 1 respectively.
ℹ Computed from a Vietoris-Rips filtration using `TDA::ripsDiag()`.
ℹ With the following parameters: maxdimension = 1 and maxscale = 1.5.</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="distance-computations-using-hera" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="distance-computations-using-hera">Distance computations using <a href="https://github.com/anigmetov/hera">Hera</a></h3>
<p>The {phutil} package inlcudes functions to compute bottleneck and Wasserstein distances either between two persistence diagrams or in a pairwise fashion from a set of persistence diagrams. The underlying computation is actually performed via the BSD-licensed <a href="https://github.com/anigmetov/hera"><em>Hera</em></a> C++ library. The latter library is bundled within {phutil} which required a <code>LinkingTo</code> dependency on <a href="https://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/bh.html">{BH}</a> for providing access to the <a href="https://www.boost.org"><em>Boost</em></a> headers for Hera compilation. To this end, the required Boost licensing terms have been copied over with the MIT license terms which {phutil} depends on. Specifically, the following functions are available:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>bottleneck_distance()</code> and <code>wasserstein_distance()</code> compute the eponymous distance between two diagrams;</li>
<li><code>bottleneck_pairwise_distances()</code> and <code>wasserstein_pairwise_distances()</code> compute pairwise distances among a sample of persistence diagrams; these functions have their C++ code parallelized via <a href="https://www.openmp.org">OpenMP</a>; to that end, they gain an optional <code>ncores</code> argument which is <code>1L</code> by default.</li>
</ul>
<p>For example, {phutil} has a built-in set of 100 persistence diagrams computed on 100 noisy versions of points on the 2-sphere. The diagrams are stored in the object <a href="https://tdaverse.github.io/phutil/reference/persistence_sample.html"><code>persistence_sample</code></a>. The following code computes the pairwise bottleneck distances between the first 7 diagrams in the set:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb9" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb9-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">bottleneck_pairwise_distances</span>(</span>
<span id="cb9-2">    persistence_sample[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>L<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">7</span>L],</span>
<span id="cb9-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ncores =</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>L</span>
<span id="cb9-4">)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>           1          2          3          4          5          6
2 0.06197453                                                       
3 0.06182617 0.03393206                                            
4 0.08125193 0.05359485 0.04198256                                 
5 0.04190589 0.06276444 0.06261608 0.08065585                      
6 0.02829251 0.05512256 0.05588969 0.09325840 0.03326582           
7 0.11170465 0.07960792 0.06338179 0.06507459 0.11249456 0.11927148</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="a-stable-modular-extensible-package-collection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-stable-modular-extensible-package-collection">A stable, modular, extensible package collection</h2>
<p>We are part of a loose-knit team of R developers interested in fostering a more sustainable and convenient package collection for TDA, which we’ve come to call the <a href="https://github.com/tdaverse">TDAverse</a>. The collection ranges from low-level, general-purpose packages like {tdaunif} and now {phutil}, through purpose-fit but interoperable packages like {ripserr} and {plt}, to Tidyverse extensions like {ggtda} and the forthcoming {tdarec}.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/aymeric.jpg" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"> <img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/Jason_Cory_Brunson.jpg" class="img-fluid" style="width:42.0%"></p>
<p>Development of {phutil} was directly funded by an Infrastructure Steering Committee grant from the R Consortium, together with several other packages that will be presented in upcoming blog posts. While we hope to secure funding for other specific projects in future, we also invite interested developers or users to reach out with their issues or ideas.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent" data-entry-spacing="0">
<div id="ref-bauer2021ripser" class="csl-entry">
Bauer, Ulrich. 2021. <span>“Ripser: Efficient Computation of Vietoris–Rips Persistence Barcodes.”</span> <em>Journal of Applied and Computational Topology</em> 5 (3): 391–423.
</div>
<div id="ref-bubenik2023exact" class="csl-entry">
Bubenik, Peter, Jonathan Scott, and Donald Stanley. 2023. <span>“Exact Weights, Path Metrics, and Algebraic Wasserstein Distances.”</span> <em>Journal of Applied and Computational Topology</em> 7 (2): 185–219.
</div>
<div id="ref-chazal2014stochastic" class="csl-entry">
Chazal, Frédéric, Brittany Terese Fasy, Fabrizio Lecci, Alessandro Rinaldo, and Larry Wasserman. 2014. <span>“Stochastic Convergence of Persistence Landscapes and Silhouettes.”</span> In <em>Proceedings of the Thirtieth Annual Symposium on Computational Geometry</em>, 474–83.
</div>
<div id="ref-cohen2010lipschitz" class="csl-entry">
Cohen-Steiner, David, Herbert Edelsbrunner, John Harer, and Yuriy Mileyko. 2010. <span>“Lipschitz Functions Have l p-Stable Persistence.”</span> <em>Foundations of Computational Mathematics</em> 10 (2): 127–39.
</div>
<div id="ref-fasy2014confidence" class="csl-entry">
Fasy, Brittany Terese, Fabrizio Lecci, Alessandro Rinaldo, Larry Wasserman, Sivaraman Balakrishnan, and Aarti Singh. 2014. <span>“Confidence Sets for Persistence Diagrams.”</span>
</div>
<div id="ref-kaji2020cubical" class="csl-entry">
Kaji, Shizuo, Takeki Sudo, and Kazushi Ahara. 2020. <span>“Cubical Ripser: Software for Computing Persistent Homology of Image and Volume Data.”</span> <em>arXiv Preprint arXiv:2005.12692</em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-wadhwa2018tdastats" class="csl-entry">
Wadhwa, Raoul R, Drew FK Williamson, Andrew Dhawan, and Jacob G Scott. 2018. <span>“TDAstats: R Pipeline for Computing Persistent Homology in Topological Data Analysis.”</span> <em>Journal of Open Source Software</em> 3 (28): 860.
</div>
<div id="ref-wasserman2018topological" class="csl-entry">
Wasserman, Larry. 2018. <span>“Topological Data Analysis.”</span> <em>Annual Review of Statistics and Its Application</em> 5 (2018): 501–32.
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/unifying-toolbox-for-handling-persistence-data/phutil-main-image.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Disease Outbreak Mapping, Open Source, and Outreach - Unijos R Users Group in Nigeria Leads the Way</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/iko-musa-a17a24114/">Iko Musa</a>, founder of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/unijos-r-users/">Unijos R Users Group</a> at the University of Jos (UNIJOS), Nigeria, spoke with the R Consortium about how the group built an inclusive and cross-disciplinary R community in northern Nigeria. Iko explained how the group supported students and professionals in transitioning from proprietary tools like SPSS to R. He highlighted their efforts to improve accessibility through online sessions, providing internet support for undergraduates, and hosting practical events like a recent Meetup on outbreak mapping in R.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/IkoMusa.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>I founded the Unijos R Users Group at Unijos whilst completing my MSc in Field Epidemiology at the University of Jos. The concept emerged from my experience as both a student and a professional Epidemiologist and Data Analyst Activity Manager with <a href="https://www.msf.org/">Médecins Sans Frontières</a> (MSF). I recognised the critical need for an inclusive community that extended beyond my department of Community Medicine to serve students across all faculties at Unijos. My vision was to create a supportive environment where both undergraduates and postgraduates could develop practical R programming skills applicable to their diverse research interests, regardless of their academic discipline.</p>
<p>Our group initially focused on postgraduate students, but my main goal has been to encourage undergraduates to adopt R for their undergraduate research projects. During my studies, both as an undergraduate and during my MSc in Field Epidemiology, we primarily used IBM SPSS Statistics, which has significant costs. In contrast, R is a free platform, which makes it much more accessible, especially for students in low-income regions like northern Nigeria. Switching from SPSS or other paid software to R would be more cost-effective and sustainable for us.</p>
<p>One of my key initiatives in founding this group is to engage undergraduate students after each session by providing a small incentive, not money, but support for internet access. Many of our members are from various universities across northern Nigeria, and this incentive encourages them to participate in learning R and expand their skills actively.</p>
<p>In my role with MSF, I also encourage my data entry teams and medical data supervisors to use R. Since joining MSF, we’ve started sessions on R, and it’s been rewarding to see team members learn, create visualisations, and gain insights from the data.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-unijos" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-unijos">Can you share what the R community is like in Unijos?</h2>
<p>Our university, the University of Jos, is commonly known as UNIJOS. Since founding this group, I’ve noticed that many who join our community are my MSc colleagues. Initially, there were just seven of us in the MSc Epidemiology program. At that time, we were using software like EpiInfo and SPSS for data analysis and outbreak investigations. Still, I realized the trend was shifting toward R. So, we formed a small group at UNIJOS to learn it together.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/UnijosRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Our community quickly expanded to include students from other programmes, such as MSc Clinical Epidemiology, MSc Chemistry, and MPH (Master of Public Health), who joined us because we offered free and accessible learning sessions. We hold online sessions every two weeks and also organise in-person sessions within our department. Sometimes, after classes, we gather for a session on R. Currently, our focus is on undergraduate students, although we also include postgraduates. We encourage participation across departments and post information on Meetup, WhatsApp, Facebook, and bulletin boards to invite anyone interested. It’s a free community open to anyone who wants to learn.</p>
<p>Our reach has grown beyond UNIJOS. In our recent online session, I noticed participants from other universities in northern Nigeria, such as Ahmadu Bello University, the Federal University of Health Sciences, Azare, National Open University of Nigeria-Maiduguri Study Centre, and the University of Maiduguri, with many undergraduates joining.</p>
<p>At MSF, I also encourage my team to use R for data analysis and other tasks. This integration has been beneficial, and I’m thrilled to see more people embracing R both within and outside UNIJOS.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/UnijosRUGMeeting.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Unijos R User Group First Meeting</p>
</section>
<section id="you-had-a-meetup-on-outbreak-mapping-in-r-on-march-22-2025.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered-why-this-topic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-had-a-meetup-on-outbreak-mapping-in-r-on-march-22-2025.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered-why-this-topic">You had a Meetup on <a href="https://www.meetup.com/unijos-r-users/events/306206070/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Outbreak Mapping in R</a> on March 22, 2025. Can you share more about the topic covered? Why this topic?</h2>
<p>During our March 22nd Meetup on Outbreak Mapping in R, we explored the essential role of spatial data visualisation in epidemiological investigations. We covered the workflow from data preparation to creating effective choropleth and spot maps using ggplot2 and the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sf/index.html">sf</a> packages. We chose this topic because mapping is crucial but often underutilised in outbreak response, helping investigators identify disease clusters and transmission patterns more efficiently. The event targeted public health professionals, residents in community medicine, epidemiologists, and data analysts with basic R knowledge who wanted practical skills for visualising outbreak data in their daily work.</p>
</section>
<section id="who-was-the-target-audience-for-attending-this-event" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-was-the-target-audience-for-attending-this-event">Who was the target audience for attending this event?</h2>
<p>Our sessions were designed to be inclusive of all skill levels, from undergraduate students to professionals interested in learning R. We kept it very basic so that anyone, whether new to R or with some experience, could participate comfortably. I felt that starting with the basics would encourage more people to join and help grow our community, making it accessible and welcoming for everyone. We also hold more advanced R sessions periodically to encourage broader participation.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-recommend-any-techniques-for-planning-for-or-during-the-event-github-zoom-other.-can-these-techniques-be-used-to-make-your-group-more-inclusive-to-people-who-cannot-attend-physical-events-in-the-future" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-recommend-any-techniques-for-planning-for-or-during-the-event-github-zoom-other.-can-these-techniques-be-used-to-make-your-group-more-inclusive-to-people-who-cannot-attend-physical-events-in-the-future">Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future?</h2>
<p>We primarily use Microsoft Teams for our online sessions, especially to reach participants in remote areas. As I mentioned, our last session included many participants from other universities and locations beyond the University of Jos and Plateau State. Microsoft Teams has been effective for these online sessions due to its ease of use.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/UnijosRUGOnlineMeeting.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Unijos R User Group First Online Meeting Using Microsoft Teams</p>
<p>Looking ahead, once we’ve grown and conducted more sessions, we’re planning to introduce advanced topics like using <a href="https://shiny.posit.co/">Shiny</a>, which I enjoy, and predictive modeling, possibly starting next year. At that point, we’ll also begin using GitHub to manage our data and resources, adding another layer of engagement for the community.</p>
<p>After each online session, we offer participants, especially undergraduates, a small internet token to help with connectivity costs. The program is free, and R Consortium has helped us make it accessible, so we want to keep it that way. Occasionally, if the network on Teams isn’t reliable, we switch to Google Meet. Additionally, we plan physical sessions for those nearby to foster in-person connections and learning opportunities.</p>
</section>
<section id="wed-like-to-get-to-know-you-better.-please-tell-me-a-little-about-yourself-such-as-your-hobbiesinterests-or-anything-else-you-want-to-share." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wed-like-to-get-to-know-you-better.-please-tell-me-a-little-about-yourself-such-as-your-hobbiesinterests-or-anything-else-you-want-to-share.">We’d like to get to know you better. Please tell me a little about yourself, such as your hobbies/interests or anything else you want to share.</h2>
<p>I’m a medical doctor by training, having graduated from Ahmadu Bello University. My transition from clinical practice to working with data began immediately after my internship, when I developed a strong interest in learning R. Previously, I had been using SPSS. I had even created a platform in Borno State called MTJ Data Analytics to offer free online sessions for SPSS. However, I found that many people struggled with SPSS due to the need for a paid license, and it required a lot of computer resources, making it difficult for those with older or less powerful devices.</p>
<p>Recognising these limitations, I saw the need to shift from SPSS to R, which is free and offers many powerful packages. My love for R grew as I explored its tools, like Shiny for interactive dashboards and the ‘<a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/sf/index.html">sf</a>’ package for mapping. These allow for flexible, detailed visualisations in outbreak investigations—something Epi Info and SPSS couldn’t fully support. R has become my go-to tool, offering a one-stop solution for analysis, mapping, and sampling without needing to switch between different software.</p>
<p>When I applied for my current role at MSF, I was pleasantly surprised to find that all the technical requirements were based on R. Looking back, if I hadn’t learned R, I wouldn’t have been able to secure this position. Recently, the Head of Epidemiology, Dr Franck Ale, from our headquarters even complimented my code, which was an incredibly proud moment and solidified my commitment to R.</p>
<p>I’m genuinely grateful for the support of the R Consortium, which has enabled us to build and expand this community in northern Nigeria, particularly at the University of Jos. Looking ahead, I plan to expand this platform further to the University of Maiduguri in the Northeast, where there is a need for R communities and support. Thank you for all you do to empower people with these resources and help grow this community—I’m excited to see where it goes.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/disease-outbreak-mapping-open-source-and-outreach-unijos-r-users-group-in-nigeria-leads-the-way/UnijosRUGlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="63" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Microservices, Randomization APIs, and R in the Medical Sector – Warsaw’s Data Community in Focus</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/microservices-randomization-apis-and-r-in-the-medical-sector-warsaws-data-community-in-focus/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kamilsijko/">Kamil Sijko</a>, organizer of both the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/spotkania-entuzjastow-r-warsaw-r-users-group-meetup/">R Users and R-Ladies Warsaw groups</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the evolving R community in Poland and the group’s efforts to connect users across academia, industry, and open-source development. Kamil shared his journey from discovering R as a student to taking over the leadership of the Warsaw R community in 2024. He discussed the group’s hybrid meetups, industry collaborations with companies like AstraZeneca and Appsilon, and the importance of making R accessible through recorded sessions and international outreach. He also highlighted a recent open-source project on patient randomization, demonstrating how R can be effectively integrated into modern software ecosystems, particularly in medical applications.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/microservices-randomization-apis-and-r-in-the-medical-sector-warsaws-data-community-in-focus/KamilSijko.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>I first encountered R during my studies, around the time of version 2, well before RStudio existed. I found it an interesting alternative to SPSS, which was widely used at my university. A key figure in my early experience with R was Professor <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pbiecek/">Przemyslaw Biecek</a>, whose 2008 book on the language marked my first serious engagement with the software. Since then, I have been using it more extensively across different industries.</p>
<p>Initially, I worked in academia, then moved to government institutions, and now I am in the business sector, all while continuing to use R.</p>
<p>Interestingly, Professor Biecek, who authored the book, later initiated the first meetups for our R community in Warsaw. In 2024, he stepped back from organizing these events and handed over the responsibilities to me—a passing of the torch that felt especially meaningful, given how I had started.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-poland" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-poland">Can you share what the R community is like in Poland?</h2>
<p>Poland is not fundamentally different from any other country in its use of programming languages. R is particularly relevant in academia and specific industries, especially the financial and medical sectors. In the medical field, the <a href="https://www.bioconductor.org/">Bioconductor</a> project plays a significant role, with researchers and pharmaceutical companies heavily relying on it and actively contributing to its development and broader open-source ecosystem.</p>
<p>Additionally, R is strong in geography and geographic computations. Its primary applications are within academia and specific niches outside it, such as the highly regulated medical sector. In this context, R is preferred for regulatory work because it allows rigorous validation to meet industry standards.</p>
<p>In my company, which operates in the medical field, using R is a natural choice. Many algorithms are already implemented in R that are not available in Python, making it logical to utilize R in such cases.</p>
</section>
<section id="so-now-that-youve-taken-over-the-r-user-group-what-are-your-plans-for-the-upcoming-months-what-topics-are-you-hoping-to-cover-are-your-meetings-in-person-online-or-a-hybrid" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-now-that-youve-taken-over-the-r-user-group-what-are-your-plans-for-the-upcoming-months-what-topics-are-you-hoping-to-cover-are-your-meetings-in-person-online-or-a-hybrid">So, now that you’ve taken over the R user group, what are your plans for the upcoming months? What topics are you hoping to cover? Are your meetings in-person, online, or a hybrid?</h2>
<p>Initially, I planned to host meetings exclusively in person and in Polish, without an online streaming option. However, people expressed interest in re-watching the meetings if they couldn’t attend. We have a relatively international community of users in Warsaw, so conducting the sessions in English made sense. Consequently, we changed our approach, and now the meetings are hybrid. They are recorded and stored on our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCq1v6SmgtmJeWDUtIKr0nVw">YouTube</a> channel, allowing anyone to rewatch them if they find them interesting.</p>
<p>We have some significant companies engaged in R development that present fascinating projects. At our last meeting, we hosted representatives from <a href="https://www.astrazeneca.pl/">AstraZeneca</a>, who discussed a large-scale project involving central data validation that utilized R. AstraZeneca also hosted our meetup at their office in Warsaw.</p>
<p>Additionally, we have <a href="https://www.appsilon.com">Appsilon</a>, an active open-source contributor. Though primarily an online organization, many of their team members are based in Warsaw. They have numerous projects to discuss and can provide instruction on various open-source initiatives.</p>
<p>My company, <a href="https://ttsi.com.pl/en/">Transition Technology Science</a>, also works with R and contributes to open-source projects, so there is plenty to discuss. Furthermore, we have a vibrant academic community. The <a href="https://www.mi2.ai/mi2redteam.html">MI2 RedTeam</a> is exploring explainable artificial intelligence, which is both fascinating and crucial right now; others work on packages related to econometrics. This local production and usage create intriguing topics of discussion.</p>
<p>Moreover, we touch upon subjects that address the current state of our community and its prospects, including relevant and active new tools. For example, at the last meetup, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tymoteusz-makowski/">Tymoteusz</a> discussed recent updates to R, including changes to the documentation and the introduction of <a href="https://positron.posit.co/">Positron</a>, the new IDE. These topics are all pertinent and vital.</p>
<p>It’s also worth mentioning that R has a distinctive characteristic of being highly relevant in academia, where many projects prioritize exploration and theory over immediate practical applications. However, it offers valuable insights and often sparks meaningful discussions. In one of the first meetings I organized, a participant presented a project that involved network analysis of conspiracy theories using R. This type of work might not align with typical grant criteria. Still, it offered a rich and engaging topic for discussion.</p>
<p>Overall, during these meetings, R often serves as a gateway to deeper and more intriguing areas of science and beyond.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-a-project-youre-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-your-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-a-project-youre-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-your-industry">Please share a project you’re currently working on or have worked on using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to your industry?</h2>
<p>I’d like to briefly preview one of the topics I covered in our last meetup, as I was one of the speakers. I discussed a project we completed at my company, which we have <a href="https://ttscience.github.io/unbiased/">open-sourced</a>. This project involves an API for randomization, a perfect example of why R is relevant.</p>
<p>Substantial work has been done in R on advanced randomization methods for clinical trials, including adaptive randomization — the kind of functionality that’s often hard to find elsewhere in such a mature and tested form. So why not use it? At the same time, it’s unrealistic to expect developers building electronic Case Report Forms (eCRFs) in Python or Java to learn R and integrate it natively into their systems suddenly.</p>
<p>To address this challenge, we developed an R package along with a Dockerized API for patient randomization. It runs R in the background, but from the developers’ perspective, integration is straightforward — with a decent connection, the whole setup (from ‘docker pull’ to ‘docker compose up’) takes less than a minute. There’s no need to work directly with R; they simply treat it like any other service in their stack.</p>
<p>This approach represents a promising way forward for many services available in R that can be integrated with other software, making them even more relevant. Modern software architecture often relies on microservices, and there’s no reason we can’t use R to build these microservices.</p>
<p>It makes logical sense to position R this way, especially since there is often a lack of tooling for building large-scale applications in R. We have encountered this limitation in other projects. Nevertheless, utilizing R as a microservice provider is a sensible direction.</p>
<p>I see the future of R not only in academic analysis but as a robust backend tool, especially for specific algorithms and statistical procedures that are mature and peer-reviewed. By wrapping R in services that are easy to use from other environments, we make its strengths more accessible to a broader audience without requiring a steep learning curve for engineers or product teams.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/microservices-randomization-apis-and-r-in-the-medical-sector-warsaws-data-community-in-focus/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/microservices-randomization-apis-and-r-in-the-medical-sector-warsaws-data-community-in-focus/KamilSijko-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="92" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Engineering, Scientific Applications and AI - Inside R User Group Philippines’ Growth</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joebrillantes/">Joe Brillantes</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-philippines/">R User Group Philippines</a> (RUG-PH), shares how the group has evolved with new interests emerging among its members. From a growing presence of data engineers exploring R to an increasing focus on scientific applications, the group continues to expand its reach. He discussed their upcoming plans for AI-focused meetups, the importance of ethical considerations in predictive modeling, and their efforts to support members in software engineering and analytics.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/RUG-PHAnniversary.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>RUG-PH 11th Anniversary Celebration 14th August 2024</em></p>
<p><strong>Since we last spoke, how has the R User Group Philippines evolved?</strong></p>
<p>Overall, we’re doing well. Since we last spoke, several themes have emerged that I’d like to highlight.</p>
<p>First, there’s a renewed interest in R, but this time, it’s coming from data engineers and individuals interested in data more broadly. Our meetups typically see one to three first-time attendees who are members of Data Engineering Filipinas. Their interest in R often stems from a desire to explore data professions.</p>
<p>Another theme is that we’ve had several speakers focused on scientific applications of R. For instance, our last speaker, who presented last month, discussed <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-philippines/events/305760876/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">mycology</a> and how R is used to analyze the colors of fungi, which was quite fascinating. We also had an online presentation from <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-philippines/events/296013229/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Jayson V. Pagaduan</a>, a director at a hospital in the U.S. He talked about how R produces efficient test results and research and which tests could be modified, eliminated, or made more efficient to ensure consistent outcomes.</p>
<p>Another speaker, <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-philippines/events/296013233/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">Dr.&nbsp;Pauline Del Mundo</a>, was also involved in public health research and discussed how R is applied in her work. This shift toward scientific topics is interesting because many of our previous speakers had backgrounds more aligned with the industry’s business side.</p>
<p>Lastly, we recorded all our meetups last year, which are now available for those who couldn’t attend due to time differences. While we haven’t made these recordings public on YouTube yet, we’ve shared them with attendees who missed the sessions. We also hosted a co-meetup with the <a href="https://ghana-rusers.org/">Ghana R Users Community</a>, where I co-hosted with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/francis-mensah-23b3262b5/?originalSubdomain=gh">Francis Mensah</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/samueltandoh/">Samuel Tandoh</a>, and we spoke about the swirl package.</p>
<p>These themes reflect the developments we’ve observed since our last conversation.</p>
<p><strong>What topics do you plan to cover in the upcoming months?</strong></p>
<p>This year, we have some exciting plans for the forthcoming months, mainly focusing on artificial intelligence (AI) and large language models. We’ve received numerous questions on implementing generative AI, not limited to large language models. Therefore, we aim to hold discussions over the next three months.</p>
<p>We have a Dynamic Programming in R planned for April. However, we will introduce a speaker each month in May and June, covering various aspects of AI. In May, a speaker will provide insights into the current state of AI research in the Philippines. In June, another speaker will discuss what it means when people claim that large language models can reason. Lastly, we plan to host a panel discussion in July featuring speakers from previous months and additional guests.</p>
<p>The July meetup will culminate the discussions on ethics and governance in AI. We want to address questions about how to critically evaluate claims made by AI companies and understand their significance. This discussion will not be limited to large language models but will also encompass generative AI and analytics.</p>
<p><strong>Your group has planned multiple meetups on artificial intelligence (AI) and ethics in the coming months. What inspired this focus, and what can attendees expect?</strong></p>
<p>I’ve had conversations with a beginner in our group working on fraud detection. While he’s enthusiastic about transitioning into his new career, I’ve noticed some questionable methodologies in his approach. It’s crucial to emphasize that while predictive models can indicate possible fraud, it is a significant difference to outright accuse someone of committing fraud based on those predictions. We must highlight the ethical implications of building models and their potential impact on people’s lives.</p>
<p>In our upcoming virtual meetups, we will also explore how the Philippines can advance the AI conversation within the country. Although not directly related to R programming, this dialogue will benefit our members by helping them become more informed and discerning about AI.</p>
<p>After this series, we plan to return to topics related to software engineering practices, as many of our members have expressed concerns about coding practices. Though I am not a programmer, my background is more analytical, and this focus will benefit our community. We aim to present a series of talks addressing these software engineering challenges and providing valuable insights.</p>
<p>My goal is not just to have very clean code. I’m also interested in how different groups can collaborate to make our code easier for software engineers to deploy and more scalable.</p>
<p>One insight I’ve gained during these discussions is that, given R’s versatility, we could cover an entire year of software engineering topics in R. However, focusing solely on software engineering might become monotonous for others.</p>
<p>We usually discuss analytics for the remaining topics. Earlier this year, I gave a presentation on <a href="https://www.meetup.com/r-user-group-philippines/events/303153606/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">creating maps in R</a>. Looking ahead, the later sessions will likely focus more on analytics topics, including predictive analytics and a talk on unsupervised learning.</p>
<p><strong>Your group maintains a well-structured lineup of topics for the entire year. How do you plan and organize these meetups?</strong></p>
<p>We begin each year by discussing the topics we want our speakers to cover. Once we have a list, we search for speakers relevant to those subjects. My role typically involves handling administration and finding speakers for analytics-related topics like data science. We also have a team member specialising in software engineering and another who is focusing on AI. They are responsible for contacting their networks to find suitable speakers for our user group.</p>
<p>We maintain a calendar with topics that we plan to discuss throughout the year. However, we aren’t as meticulously organized as some other groups might be. We may have to change the topic if we struggle to find a speaker for a meeting. We aim to have a consistent lineup of subjects for our monthly meetups, totaling 12 topics for the year.</p>
<p>We believe it’s essential to be reliable and consistent for our members. Even if attendance is low—say, just two or three people—we still hold the meetup as promised. This reliability fosters trust within the community.</p>
<p><strong>Who are some key collaborators and supporters that help keep the R User Group Philippines running smoothly?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/RUG-PH-Organizers.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Left to Right, Joma Miñoza, Joe Brillantes, Michelle Alarcon, and Rad Basa</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michelle-alarcon-91477513/?originalSubdomain=ph">Michelle Alarcon</a> is still with us to provide support, although she has taken a more hands-off approach since she’s now managing the AI and Analytics Association of the Philippines. She remains a valuable resource, and I can often count on her assistance when needed.</p>
<p>We also utilize other connections. For instance, I often contact <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jomaminoza/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Egoogle%2Ecom%2F&amp;originalSubdomain=ph">Joma Miñoza</a>, who works at the Center for AI Research in the Philippines, when we need expertise on AI topics. Additionally, we have Rad Basa involved in our efforts.</p>
<p>Rad Basa is a software engineer who works for <a href="https://www.appsilon.com/">Appsilon</a>. When we discuss software engineering practices, I typically consult him. We are also good friends with <a href="https://dataengineering.ph/">Data Engineering Pilipinas</a>. The founder of that group, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ogbinar/?originalSubdomain=hk">Myk Ogbinar</a>, is very supportive and assists me when I need help finding speakers for events.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/MykOgbinar.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><em>Myk Ogbinar</em></p>
<p>These are the key people I usually bounce ideas off when planning activities and selecting speakers. I ask for their perspectives regarding the needs of the R Users Group members. We also have many dedicated R users in academia. While we invite them to participate, we usually don’t involve them in planning since we understand they are swamped. However, if we have a specific topic in mind, we can reach out, and they often suggest that one of their professors speak on the subject.</p>
<p>Overall, many individuals contribute to the organization of the R Users Group in the Philippines, and their support is greatly appreciated.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/data-engineering-scientific-applications-and-ai-inside-r-user-group-philippines-growth/RUG-PHAnniversary-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="88" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quarterly Round Up from the R Consortium</title>
  <dc:creator>Terry Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/quarterly-round-up-from-the-r-consortium/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/quarterly-round-up-from-the-r-consortium/calendar-icon-apr-2025.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:20.0%"></p>
<p>It is April already! OK, a lot has been happening, and a lot is planned so, let’s get to it.</p>
<section id="events" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="events">Events</h2>
<section id="rmedicine" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rmedicine">R/Medicine</h3>
<p>Have you <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/RMedicine_website/Register.html">registered for R/Medicine</a> yet? It’s happening on June 10-13. This jam-packed, 3-day virtual event is back and better than ever. We are so thrilled to have Ziad Obermeyer delivering a keynote, “Reinventing Medicine with AI” and Erin LeDell delivering our second keynote, “Model Evaluation: From Machine Learning to Generative AI.” There are 9 different workshops and demonstrations, plus talks and panels.</p>
<p>Don’t forget to enter the <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/RMedicine_website/Competition.html">Data Challenge: How are vaccination rates and case rates changing for measles in 2025</a>? Two $200 prizes (student and pro) will be awarded to the best analyses of the public datasets we have highlighted. Submissions due on May 20, 2025.</p>
<p>A huge thank you to our sponsor, Genentech, for supporting this popular and high value event.</p>
</section>
<section id="user" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="user">useR!</h3>
<p><a href="https://user2025.r-project.org/">This year’s useR!</a> is coming up fast – August 8-10 at Duke University in Durham, North Carolina. The R Consortium is a platinum sponsor for this event, and we are very excited for the program the organizers are putting together. Be sure to register soon and maybe talk to your company about sponsoring and sending a bunch of you, together.</p>
<p>If you can’t make it to Durham to be with us in person, you can still get yourself a front row seat to the virtual event on August 1<sup>st</sup>. You can find more information <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/events/7313635592217518081/">here</a>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="more-3rd-party-events-we-are-sponsoring" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-3rd-party-events-we-are-sponsoring">More 3<sup>rd</sup> Party Events we are sponsoring:</h2>
<p>Every year the R Consortium tries to sponsor events around the world in support of the R language and our amazing community. Here are some that we hope you will consider attending and supporting:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Title</th>
<th>Dates</th>
<th>Location</th>
<th>Type</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><a href="https://rr2025.sciencesconf.org/">Rencontres 2025</a></td>
<td>May 19-21</td>
<td>Mons, Belgium</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><a href="https://ghana-rusers.org/forms/rconf2025/">Ghana R Conference 2025</a></td>
<td>Jun 19-20</td>
<td>Accra, Ghana</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><a href="https://cascadiarconf.com/">Cascadia R Conference</a></td>
<td>Jun 20-21</td>
<td>Portland, Oregon</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><a href="https://gbcc2025.bioconductor.org/">Galaxy and Bioconductor Community Conference 2025</a></td>
<td>Jun 23-26</td>
<td>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, NY</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><a href="https://eurobioc2025.bioconductor.org/">European Bioconductor Conference (EuroBioC2025)</a></td>
<td>Sept 17-19</td>
<td>Barcelona, Spain</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><a href="https://earl-conference.com/">EARL (Enterprise Applications of the R Language) Tech Conference 2025</a></td>
<td>Oct 14-16</td>
<td>Brighton, UK</td>
<td>Conference</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</section>
<section id="working-groups" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="working-groups">Working Groups</h2>
<p>Our volunteers are super busy driving progress across our working groups and we are so grateful for their efforts. The impact they are creating is being felt and recognized. If you want to “do more” with your R skills but don’t know where to start, our Working Groups do not require membership. It is an excellent opportunity to learn, collaborate and help steer the future of the open source R language with industry colleagues.</p>
<section id="take-a-look-and-get-involved-with-one-of-our-existing-working-groups-by-joining-their-mailing-list-or-submit-an-idea-for-your-own-working-group-by-reaching-out-to-us" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="take-a-look-and-get-involved-with-one-of-our-existing-working-groups-by-joining-their-mailing-list-or-submit-an-idea-for-your-own-working-group-by-reaching-out-to-us">Take a look and get involved with one of our existing working groups by <a href="https://lists.r-consortium.org/g/Rconsortium-main/subgroups">joining their mailing list</a> or <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/isc-working-groups.html">submit an idea for your own working group</a> by reaching out to us!</h4>
</section>
<section id="submissions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submissions">Submissions</h3>
<p>This team continues to engage with the FDA to finish up the WebAssembly work from Pilot 4 and Pilot 5 pushing R and Dataset-JSON forward for drug submissions. There’s a rumor that hex stickers are coming soon. Want to check out the work and get involved? Check out <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot5-datasetjson">the GitHub repo</a> and reach out.</p>
</section>
<section id="validation-hub" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="validation-hub">Validation Hub</h3>
<p>Coming off another successful developers’ day event the group is gearing up to provide an updated roadmap by May 2025. Fundraising is beginning to enable work on the Validation Repository to start. The team continues to focus on delivering meaningful ways for regulated industries to manage the risk associated with using open-source packages to each organization’s unique risk profile. To get involved and/or to contribute funding to the project, <a href="https://www.pharmar.org/contact/">please get in touch</a>!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="its-time-to-step-up-for-open-source-technologies" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-time-to-step-up-for-open-source-technologies">It’s time to step up for open-source technologies</h2>
<p>We have seen a lot of changes in these past months and as an industry sponsored 501(c)6 organization in support of the R statistical programming language, we want to encourage everyone to get involved and lend their talents and resources to open-source communities. Of course, we would love it if y’all joined us and <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/join.html#joining-the-r-consortium-is-easy.">here is the information for your organization to do exactly that</a>. Whether your company sponsors the R Consortium or not, your talents are vital to the work we do. We are so grateful for the continuing support and enthusiasm of our volunteers and the financial support of our industry members.</p>
<p>We’re working hard to bring you great content about R and opportunities to connect with the community. I’ll be back next quarter with more news. In the meantime, if you have suggestions or questions for the R Consortium, <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/contact.html">please contact us</a>. We’d love to hear from you.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/quarterly-round-up-from-the-r-consortium/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/quarterly-round-up-from-the-r-consortium/calendar-icon-apr-2025-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Strengthening R Communities Across Borders: Ozan Evkaya on Organizing the Edinburgh R User Group</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/strengthening-r-communities-across-borders-ozan-evkaya-on-organizing-the-edinburgh-r-user-group/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ozanevkaya/">Ozan Evkaya</a>, one of the local organizers of the <a href="http://edinbr.org/">Edinburgh R User group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about his journey in the R community and his efforts to strengthen R adoption in Edinburgh. He discussed his experiences hosting R events in Turkey during the pandemic, the importance of online engagement, and his vision for expanding collaborations with neighboring user groups. He also reflected on his research in dependence modeling and contributions to open-source R packages, highlighting how R continues to shape his work in academia and community building.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/strengthening-r-communities-across-borders-ozan-evkaya-on-organizing-the-edinburgh-r-user-group/Ozan_Evkaya.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Please share about your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>During my PhD program in statistics from 2012 to 2018, I took several courses in the field. I began engaging with programming languages relevant to my dissertation and applied work throughout that period. I started learning and using the R programming language, particularly after attending one academic workshop event in France.</p>
<p>Many of my colleagues, especially those from the statistics field, innovatively and effectively used these languages. This inspired me to invest more time in developing my skills in this area during my PhD studies. In addition to my postdoc research, I began participating in and organizing small online webinars during the pandemic and continued to do so afterward.</p>
<p>During that time, I met a couple of Turkish colleagues who were key in organizing some R-based events. It was my first experience with the official community-related groups associated with the R Consortium. With their support, we received a budget to help organize online events in Turkey during 2021 and 2022 called <a href="https://whyr.pl/2022/turkey/en/#:~:text=WhyR%20%3F,users%20from%20academia%20and%20industry.">Why R Turkiye</a>.</p>
<p>Initially, we started with simple online setups, but in 2022, we organized the event with paper submissions, an improved version of the previous year. The event was well-received, and everyone appreciated our efforts. In our first year, we had a group of six main organizers (including two undergraduate keen students from different universities). By 2022, our team had grown to eight members to foster gender diversity.</p>
<p>This experience taught me what can happen when people are passionate about organizing events online. It was also the first time I truly learned about the community and how others are working to expand their knowledge by sharing and collaborating.</p>
<p>When I joined the University of Edinburgh in March 2022, I began to explore the local R groups available in the area. I discovered the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/edinbr/">Edinburgh R user group (EdinbR)</a>, a local community, and promptly contacted the main organizer to express my interest in joining.</p>
<p>Since then, we have started organizing various local events. However, the group was not very active during 2022 because the lead organizer was busy with personal matters. Another colleague and I stepped in to revitalize the group.</p>
<p>Our organizing team currently consists of three members: myself, Alessia Calafiore (a colleague from the university), and the lead organizer, Mike Spencer, a PhD alumnus of the university who now works as a data scientist for a company based in Edinburgh. These shared connections help create a close-knit and collaborative community, especially since we use one of the university’s buildings for our activities. The team brings together one industry representative (Mike) and two university lecturers—myself from the School of Mathematics, and Alessia, who lectures in Sustainability and Urban Data Science at the Edinburgh School of Architecture and Landscape Architecture. We benefit from excellent group dynamics and a strong foundation of familiarity.</p>
<p><strong>How do you see the balance between industry and academia in the Edinburgh R community? Which industries are actively using R?</strong></p>
<p>In my experience, there is a balance between academics and industry in their use of programming languages. While Python is quite popular in specific fields, especially for certain packages tailored to research and data visualization, R is still preferred for many tasks.</p>
<p>Based on my interactions with members of the Edinburgh R Group and the<a href="https://rss.org.uk/">Royal Statistical Society</a>’s (RSS) local user groups, I see both industrial professionals and academics actively using R. For example, I can share the experience of one of our MSc students who recently started working at a company in the biostatistics field. They rely on R for data manipulation, and many similar examples are emerging here in Edinburgh.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/strengthening-r-communities-across-borders-ozan-evkaya-on-organizing-the-edinburgh-r-user-group/EdinburghRUG_Meetup.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Edinburgh R User Group Event: “<a href="https://www.meetup.com/edinbr/events/306226785/?eventOrigin=group_events_list">No likelihood? No problem! — Bayesian Statistics in R</a>”</p>
<p><strong>What are your plans for the coming months? What topics do you want to cover?</strong></p>
<p>We are currently organizing monthly events based on feedback gathered from our audience. These events occur on Thursday evenings, allowing participants from academia and industry to join after traditional working hours.</p>
<p>We currently hold these events once a month, featuring two speakers in each session. We connect their topics meaningfully to create a cohesive experience for the audience. We aim to accommodate various levels of expertise, including beginner, intermediate, and advanced users of our language. Last month, we successfully organized a joint event with the RSS local group in Edinburgh. We may consider collaborating with other communities for similar joint events.</p>
<p>This platform allows us to share and spread ideas, potentially creating new event styles. One of my dreams is to organize a more significant event, something we haven’t had enough time to pursue yet. There are local groups nearby, such as the one in Glasgow, that could be involved. I hope to organize a significant event once a year, and while we haven’t discussed it much with those groups yet, I look forward to collaborating with them on this idea.</p>
<p><strong>Do you recommend any techniques for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other.) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people who cannot attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>We primarily use the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/edinbr/">Meetup</a> group, which our main organizer, Mike, established several years ago. We are still active, and people are eager to join and register as local group members. Currently, we have 928 members, which is a significant number, I believe. Many of them are enthusiastic about attending our events, and it’s terrific to see so many familiar faces from various organizations at each gathering. The leading platforms we are currently using for the circulation of our events are <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/EdinbR.fosstodon.org.ap.brid.gy">BlueSky</a> and LinkedIn personal pages.</p>
<p>We want to promote our events through existing channels where our natural audience and contacts are already engaged. This is a fitting space for our outreach. Additionally, our speakers sometimes share their slides on GitHub, mainly when using R to create their presentations. This allows them to easily share their slides and the GitHub repository, enabling everyone to contribute to the open-source community. Aside from the above-mentioned ones, we don’t have any specific technical tools currently in use.</p>
<p><strong>How do you use R for your work?</strong></p>
<p>I rely heavily on R and the various packages for research/teaching and am also trying to contribute to those packages. This dependency started during my PhD, when I focused on dependence modeling with certain available R-based computational packages. A talented group of people who created these open-source packages has already developed many techniques related to dependence modeling in R. While some packages are now available in Python more recently, I still primarily depend on R for these topics.</p>
<p>During my first postdoctoral period, working with colleagues at KU Leuven, I worked on two packages and integrated them for my research project. I’m currently polishing this work before creating a more formal package or sharing it on GitHub—this is still one of my goals. In addition to my original research, I contributed to a Shiny-based research project initiated by a colleague at Boğaziçi University in 2021/2022 to create an R package version of their studies.</p>
<p>Overall, I want to explore various areas beyond my primary research. I’m also using R extensively for teaching purposes, particularly in the data science course I co-teach and the statistics and data visualization courses I run remotely. My reliance on R is significant for these courses, and I am regularly learning new tips or packages from the community that I have been part of.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/strengthening-r-communities-across-borders-ozan-evkaya-on-organizing-the-edinburgh-r-user-group/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/strengthening-r-communities-across-borders-ozan-evkaya-on-organizing-the-edinburgh-r-user-group/Ozan_Evkaya-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="75" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R in Maine: Connecting Ecologists, Medical Researchers, and Data Scientists</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://szlo.ai/">Donald Szlosek</a>, the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/maine-r-users-group/?eventOrigin=event_home_page">MaineR Users Group</a> organizer, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the group’s transition from a city-based meetup to a statewide community and its efforts to engage a diverse audience. Donald shared insights into organizing events, the challenges of hybrid formats, and the shift toward virtual workshops based on community feedback. He also highlighted his work in real-world evidence studies, where R is critical in causal inference and machine learning validation.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/DonaldSzlosek.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><em>Donald Szlosek presenting on exploring nature through {rvest}</em></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My name is Donald Szlosek, and I am a senior staff research biostatistician at <a href="https://www.idexx.com/en/">IDEXX</a> Laboratories. I got involved in the local R community when a small group in Portland, Maine, began its user group through <a href="https://www.mainehealth.org/maine-medical-center">Maine Medical Center</a>. I collaborated with one of the leads, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/adam-black-7904a26b/">Adam Black</a>, who sought to unite the community. He aimed to involve various groups, not just those focused on research but also from other industries, as there wasn’t much available back in 2015.</p>
<p>During the pandemic, our activities slowed down for about a year and a half, but I’m pleased to say we are starting to regain momentum. Over the past couple of years, we have become more active again.</p>
<p><strong>Please tell us what events you are currently hosting. Are they online, in-person, or hybrid? What kind of response do you receive for your events?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/MaineRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Last year, we primarily held online workshops, which proved immensely beneficial. One of our user group members, a fantastic professor, <a href="https://lauriebaker.rbind.io/">Dr.&nbsp;Laurie Baker</a>, received a community data science grant. She offered to run some workshops and asked if we could help promote them within our user group. We gladly agreed, and the workshops turned out to be fantastic. Her work was truly impressive, and we were thrilled to be a part of it.</p>
<p>Last year, we conducted a start-of-the-year survey to gather feedback from our community. We asked, “What do you want?” and compiled the responses using Google Sheets. We were surprised to learn that people wanted more virtual events, mainly since we had primarily focused on in-person gatherings. Additionally, many requested workshops, which we had never offered before. As a result, we shifted our focus last year. While we didn’t hold as many events as I would have liked—organizing them can be challenging—the ones we did hold turned out well.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/MaineRUGOrganizersPosit2023.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Left to right: Adam Black, Jaclyn Janis, Allison Hinton, and Donald Szlosek at the 2023 Posit Conference</p>
<p>However, the turnout at these events has been relatively small. We have a core group of about 12 people interested in attending, but typically, only two to three from that group show up at any event. Given this small number, it’s unrealistic to expect large turnouts. This situation was one of the reasons we transitioned from the Portland R User Group to a statewide R User Group in hopes of attracting more participants.</p>
<p>That said, when you shift from focusing on a city to an entire state, reaching everyone becomes much more challenging unless you host virtual events. This realization significantly influenced our decision to adopt a virtual event format.</p>
<p>On <a href="https://www.meetup.com/maine-r-users-group/events/306012911/?eventOrigin=group_past_events">February 11th, we hosted a virtual kickoff event</a> to start the year. During this event, we asked our community what they wanted to see from us this year. Our goal was to gather feedback on their interests and preferences. This event was less formal than a workshop or presentation, but we hope it will set us on the right path to better serve our community. We also hope to have a workshop on creating publication-ready tables with {gt} in March.</p>
<p><strong>Please share a bit about your experience in organizing the group. Over the years, have you discovered any techniques or tools that have helped organize the group and the events you host?</strong></p>
<p>My biggest lesson is that hybrid events are challenging to manage alone. I’ve essentially stopped organizing them unless I can get someone to assist me—either with the online component or by handling the hosting while I take care of the online side. It’s just tough to juggle both aspects simultaneously.</p>
<p>Additionally, I try to maintain a positive mindset by reminding myself that I’ll be excited even if just one person shows up. I aim to keep that energy level because these events often attract small groups, and people are busy. I want to be respectful and kind and genuinely appreciate having a single participant join.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/MaineRUGHikingTrip.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>What industry are you currently in? How do you use R in your work?</strong></p>
<p>I’m in the pharmaceutical medical device industry and utilize various methods in three main areas of my job. First, I conduct typical clinical trials, which involve the design and analysis in partnership with forty different universities worldwide. This process requires extensive data analysis, preparation, and statistical methodology. We utilize R Markdown documents for this purpose, and I’ve found them highly effective.</p>
<p>Another key focus of my work is real-world evidence studies, which have gained substantial traction over the past decade by leveraging large-scale electronic medical record data. In this area, we apply causal inference techniques to understand better the relationship between real-world clinical practice and medical data.</p>
<p>We engage in various activities, such as propensity score matching and targeted maximum likelihood estimation, which are fundamental to real-world evidence studies. This is a significant part of our work.</p>
<p>The last aspect we focus on is machine learning validation for regulatory bodies. We develop models that function as new medical devices, which need to be validated before they can be used in practice. While it’s great that a data science team has built a reliable model and performed internal validations, we must ensure it won’t negatively impact clinicians when they use it. Our goal is to prevent any additional concerns for them while they work.</p>
<p>Moreover, confirming that the model is effective within the specific population it is intended for is crucial. This is where the validation component plays a vital role. In this process, R programming is essential for matching datasets and pulling information from clinics’ relevant data sources. This allows us to analyze the model’s accuracy from a statistical perspective.</p>
<p><strong>Which Industries do you see using R in Maine?</strong></p>
<p>Surprisingly, most of our events in Maine attendees come from the ecology field rather than the medical side. However, this might change as new medical facilities are in the area. Boston, being only a couple of hours away, has many medical-related resources.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.gmri.org/">Gulf of Maine Research Institute</a> conducts significant work in marine biology, further emphasizing the focus on ecology, forest biology, and marine conservation among the people in our group. Seeing their perspective is refreshing since I come from a very different background.</p>
<p>Although our work might seem different on the surface, there’s a lot of common ground; for example, a statistician in one field is quite similar to a statistician in another. Learning about their data collection processes, such as collecting water samples, analyzing the data, and managing the information, is fascinating. Their approach to data gathering is quite distinct and presents different challenges. Hearing about their methods compared to ours is genuinely intriguing.</p>
<p><strong>Please tell us about the recent or current project you are working on using R.</strong></p>
<p>I am working on real-world evidence studies focusing on inverse propensity score weighting. These studies often involve imbalanced populations, requiring robust causal inference techniques to address disparities in treatment groups. By applying inverse propensity score weighting, I aim to balance treatment groups and covariates, enhancing comparability and making the analysis more comparable to a randomized controlled trial.</p>
<p>There is still considerable debate about whether techniques like inverse propensity score weighting offer more value than traditional multivariable regression. This remains an area of active discussion, and I am continuously working to deepen my understanding of the limitations of weighting. While propensity score methods help address confounding and improve balance in observational studies, their advantages over regression approaches depend on the specific context and assumptions of the analysis. My next step is to ensure that I am not overlooking any crucial aspects or limitations of these methodologies, especially considering their popularity based on my current understanding.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-in-maine-connecting-ecologists-medical-researchers-and-data-scientists/MaineRUGlogo1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Revitalizing the Melbourne Users of R Network: Hybrid Events, Collaboration, and the Future of R</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/l-p-cruz-phd/">Lito P. Cruz</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/melburn-melbourne-users-of-r-network/">Melbourne Users of R Network</a> (MELBURN), recently spoke with the R Consortium about the evolving R community in Melbourne and the group’s efforts to engage data professionals across government, academia, and industry. Lito shared insights into the group’s history, the impact of the pandemic on community engagement, and his ongoing efforts to revitalize in-person and hybrid events. He discussed new initiatives, including collaborations with the Statistical Society of Australia and interactive event formats featuring hands-on tutorials.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/LitoPCruz.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>I’ve had a long career in IT here in Melbourne, Australia, where I worked as a contract software developer and engineer. I focused primarily on mathematics during my university years, including my graduate studies and doctoral work. I took several graduate courses in statistics before switching to computer science. In my postgraduate studies, I concentrated more on discrete mathematics.</p>
<p>Around 2013, I noticed a growing interest in statistics among executives and managers. Many were introduced to statistics during their MBA programs and were now eager to apply it in their roles. This shift prompted me to think about the increasing relevance of statistics in decision-making processes.</p>
<p>In 2012, I noticed an opportunity as more people began to engage with statistics. This was exciting because I have a passion for modeling and statistics-related work. I started learning R in 2013 and took several online courses, including <a href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/rdpeng">Roger D. Peng</a>’s data science courses on Coursera. Through this, I learned more about R and its history, realizing that it originated from the S programming language inspired by functional languages like Lisp and <a href="https://www.scheme.org/">Scheme</a>. As a fan of functional programming, I appreciated that R supports this style.</p>
<p>As I delved deeper into R, I quickly fell in love with it. I believe it’s an excellent language, especially for data science work. I have successfully delivered many data pipelines in the industry using R and haven’t encountered any significant issues. My desire to gain more knowledge about the language only grew.</p>
<p>I particularly admire R’s functional style, which allows me to write concise code. This brevity makes debugging more manageable, and I’ve experienced significant success with it. Given the choice, I will always opt for R.</p>
<p><strong>Can you share what the R community is like in Melbourne?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/MELBURNlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>R programming is prominent in various sectors, including government, healthcare, finance, insurance, banking, and academia.</p>
<p>Within the federal government, R is widely relied on. Many agencies use R as a substitute for SAS due to licensing costs; R is a cost-effective alternative.</p>
<p>R is also widely utilized in healthcare, especially in hospitals where numerous statisticians are engaged in biostatistics. This makes R a valuable tool in that sector.</p>
<p>Additionally, actuaries in the finance and insurance industries frequently use R, favoring it for its analytical capabilities.</p>
<p>In the banking sector, certain divisions still employ R. In Australia, banks operate as conglomerates with separate business units that often have the autonomy to choose their technical tools. If a specific application requires it, R might be selected based on the recommendations of technical experts.</p>
<p>Academia also remains loyal to R, although there is a current trend leaning toward Python for its ease of use. Students studying statistics, econometrics, actuarial sciences, or life sciences will likely be taught R as part of their coursework. Fields such as biology and economics frequently incorporate R in their curriculum. The continued support for R in educational programs ensures its relevance and viability as a programming option.</p>
<p><strong>Can you tell us about the history of the Melbourne R User Group and how it has evolved over the years?</strong></p>
<p>The initial founder of an R User Group in 2010, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/eugene-dubossarsky-09208a1/?originalSubdomain=au">Dr.&nbsp;Eugene Dubossarsky</a>, was quite influential in the field of analytics, which, back then, was simply referred to as “analytics” before the term “data scientist” became popular.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/MELBURNMeetup.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Today, our database has grown to 2,900 members associated with the Melbourne R-Users group. I’ve actually asked our members to remove their names if they’re no longer interested in R, as we want to clean up the list. However, I haven’t had much success; many still want to remain in the community.</p>
<p>Since late 2020, we have conducted our meetings in a hybrid format, allowing in-person attendance and Zoom participation. Our member base includes individuals from all over the world—Canada, the US, the Middle East, and Africa—interested in our activities.</p>
<p>Historically, before the pandemic, our meetings consistently drew between 70 and 120 attendees. However, when COVID-19 hit, it felt like throwing water on a fire; attendance dropped significantly as people became concerned about their health and the health of their loved ones.</p>
<p>I have been working on reviving the group since last year, and our first in-person meeting took place in September 2024. We’re gradually getting back on track, little by little.</p>
<p><strong>Can you tell us about the recent activities of the Melbourne R User Group?</strong></p>
<p>We currently have the usual activities planned, and these are our current ideas. First, we always enjoy informal talks and fellowship at a restaurant, which allows us to network and build connections. We’re still trying to grow this group and have about a dozen regular attendees.</p>
<p>I want to make this group more interactive by reminding everyone that this is their user group and that we can shape its activities. I opened the floor for suggestions and asked what everyone would like to do this year. One idea was a barbecue, so we’ll be planning that. The group enjoys fellowship, interaction, and the opportunity to make new friends with similar interests.</p>
<p>Additionally, we’ve decided to split our talks into two segments. The main talk will last about 45 minutes, and we will introduce a new 15-minute tutorial segment. This segment will cover topics such as “How R can do X,” where we can showcase various R capabilities, like interfacing with JavaScript or generating Shiny code using AI.</p>
<p>We are also collaborating with the Victoria branch of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/statistical-society-of-australia-victorian-branch/">Statistical Society of Australia</a>. They are interested in cross-pollinating with us, meaning they want to attend our meetings and invite us to theirs since many statisticians in that group use R.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/MELBURNBBQ.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Another idea was to have a portion where someone could present how to utilize R for various tasks. R can be applied in many areas. I emphasized that the R Consortium webpage, run by Quattro, is powered by R. This is a fantastic showcase for R’s capabilities.</p>
<p><strong>What tools and techniques do you use to collaborate with other organizations and engage the community?</strong></p>
<p>In the past, I have observed how active members sometimes received support from companies that wanted to contribute positively to the R community and the industry.</p>
<p>In December 2024, a company sponsored one of our meetups by covering the venue costs. We are now looking to reopen this opportunity, as some companies have expressed interest in hosting our meetings at their corporate locations. We’re eager to facilitate this.</p>
<p>We utilize LinkedIn and Meetup to keep our community informed. I regularly communicate with attendees, sending them at least two messages before each event on the first Tuesday of every month.</p>
<p>Before each monthly event, I send a hello to our members as a reminder. I do this in hopes of getting them to return and participate. If you look at our pictures, you can see that historically, we have around 120 people attending our user group in Melbourne. We haven’t fully kick-started our relationship with the Statistical Society of Australia, Victoria branch. Still, I plan to improve our representation when we meet with them next month.</p>
<p>Coordinating with them can be challenging since their organizer is based in Sydney. However, I’ve noticed that some of our members are also members of the Statistical Society. We will have more activities planned as the months progress.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/revitalizing-the-melbourne-users-of-r-network-hybrid-events-collaboration-and-the-future-of-r/MELBURNlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exploring geometa: An R Package for Managing Geographic Metadata</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/exploring-geometa-an-r-package-for-managing-geographic-metadata/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>geometa</strong> provides an essential object-oriented data model in R, enabling users to efficiently manage geographic metadata. The package facilitates handling of ISO and OGC standard geographic metadata and their dissemination on the web, ensuring that spatial data and maps are available in an open, internationally recognized format. As a widely adopted tool within the geospatial community, geometa plays a crucial role in standardizing metadata workflows.</p>
<p>Since 2018, the <strong>R Consortium</strong> has supported the development of geometa, recognizing its value in bridging metadata standards with R’s data science ecosystem. You can try geometa yourself here: <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=geometa">CRAN – geometa</a>.</p>
<p>In this interview, we speak with <strong>Emmanuel Blondel</strong>, the author of geometa, ows4R, geosapi, geonapi and geoflow—key R packages for geospatial data management. With a background in <strong>Agronomic Sciences and Environmental &amp; Natural Resources Management</strong> from the French National Polytechnical Institute (<strong>INP-ENSAT</strong>), Emmanuel specializes in <strong>Geographic Information Systems (GIS)</strong> applied to fields such as agronomy, environment, fisheries, and aquatic sciences. As an active open-source developer, he shares insights into the evolution of geometa, the challenges of metadata standardization, and the future of geospatial data management in R.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/exploring-geometa-an-r-package-for-managing-geographic-metadata/emmanuel.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="what-is-the-significance-of-geometa-including-support-for-iso-19115-3-getting-published-on-cran-is-this-about-incorporating-new-standards" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-the-significance-of-geometa-including-support-for-iso-19115-3-getting-published-on-cran-is-this-about-incorporating-new-standards">What is the significance of geometa including support for ISO 19115-3 getting published on CRAN? Is this about incorporating new standards?</h2>
<p>Yes, it’s all about metadata standards. ISO standards can have a lifecycle from around five to ten years, and it takes time for institutions, governments, and software providers to adopt and implement them. The primary standard for geographic metadata has been ISO 19115 developed by the ISO/TC 211 (Technical Committee on Geographic Information/Geomatics). It defines the structure for describing geographic information. It is initially composed by the main geographic metadata standard (ISO 19115-1) and an extension to describe gridded and imagery datasets, called ISO 19115-2. To facilitate XML encoding, ISO 19139 provides the corresponding XML schema for implementing ISO 19115-compliant metadata.</p>
<p>ISO 19115 has been widely used in geographic information systems, software providers, and legal frameworks such as the INSPIRE directive in Europe or the Geospatial Data Act in the U.S.. Countries and international organizations have gradually adopted ISO 19115. Meanwhile a new version of the ISO 19115, called ISO 19115-3, was developed by ISO experts to refactor and consolidate the standard. However, adoption takes time.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-idea-behind-the-latest-geometa-project-funded-by-the-r-consortium-was-to-support-this-transition-by-implementing-the-newer-version-of-iso-19115.-thats-why-ive-been-pushing-for-this-update.-since-standardization-work-is-a-continuous-process-there-are-already-other-prospects-for-improvements-such-as-the-management-of-the-json-encoding-format-targeted-by-the-next-iso-19115-4-standard-under-development." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-idea-behind-the-latest-geometa-project-funded-by-the-r-consortium-was-to-support-this-transition-by-implementing-the-newer-version-of-iso-19115.-thats-why-ive-been-pushing-for-this-update.-since-standardization-work-is-a-continuous-process-there-are-already-other-prospects-for-improvements-such-as-the-management-of-the-json-encoding-format-targeted-by-the-next-iso-19115-4-standard-under-development.">The idea behind the latest <strong>geometa</strong> project funded by the R Consortium was to support this transition by implementing the newer version of ISO 19115. That’s why I’ve been pushing for this update. Since standardization work is a continuous process, there are already other prospects for improvements, such as the management of the JSON encoding format, targeted by the next ISO 19115-4 standard under development.</h2>
</section>
<section id="how-has-the-object-oriented-data-model-developed-with-r6-been-improved-and-what-are-the-main-advantages" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-has-the-object-oriented-data-model-developed-with-r6-been-improved-and-what-are-the-main-advantages">How has the object-oriented data model developed with R6 been improved? And what are the main advantages?</h2>
<p>ISO 19115 and related standards, such as GML (Geographic Markup Language), are built on large object-oriented information models. It made sense to use an object-oriented data model in R to align with these standards.</p>
<p>I chose <strong>R6</strong> because it was the most convenient and practical way to model objects. I had previously explored other approaches, but R6 offered flexibility and efficiency.</p>
<p>Now, I’m also keeping an eye on <strong>S7</strong>, an initiative from the R Consortium. In the future, I might explore new approaches for object modeling such as S7, and possibly adopt them in packages such as geometa.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="how-important-is-r-for-multidisciplinary-projects-involving-data-managers-analysts-statisticians-and-researchers-across-different-teams-what-are-its-main-advantages" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-important-is-r-for-multidisciplinary-projects-involving-data-managers-analysts-statisticians-and-researchers-across-different-teams-what-are-its-main-advantages">How important is R for multidisciplinary projects involving data managers, analysts, statisticians, and researchers across different teams? What are its main advantages?</h2>
<p>R’s main advantage is its broad accessibility across various roles—data managers, scientists, statisticians—who all understand and use it.</p>
<p>This was a key reason why I developed <strong>geometa</strong> in R. In the past, I worked with Java for similar projects, but my colleagues struggled with it because they weren’t Java developers, and the programming language was a barrier. R served as a common language among them, enabling better collaboration.</p>
<p>There are two main challenges:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>The technology constraint</strong> (R itself).</li>
<li><strong>The complexity of metadata standards</strong>, which are exhaustive and highly specialized.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>geometa</strong> provides fine-grained control, fully aligning with the standards. However, I’ve also developed tools to simplify metadata creation, making it easier for non-developers to generate metadata efficiently.</p>
</section>
<section id="seeing-my-colleagueswho-previously-couldnt-produce-metadatanow-able-to-generate-metadata-and-enable-services-has-been-rewarding.-this-is-particularly-valuable-in-data-science-where-the-volume-of-data-continues-to-grow.-instead-of-struggling-with-metadata-formats-they-can-focus-on-improving-data-quality-and-descriptions." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="seeing-my-colleagueswho-previously-couldnt-produce-metadatanow-able-to-generate-metadata-and-enable-services-has-been-rewarding.-this-is-particularly-valuable-in-data-science-where-the-volume-of-data-continues-to-grow.-instead-of-struggling-with-metadata-formats-they-can-focus-on-improving-data-quality-and-descriptions.">Seeing my colleagues—who previously couldn’t produce metadata—now able to generate metadata and enable services has been rewarding. This is particularly valuable in data science, where the volume of data continues to grow. Instead of struggling with metadata formats, they can focus on improving data quality and descriptions.</h2>
</section>
<section id="geometa-is-used-in-r-packages-such-as-ows4r-r-interface-to-ogc-web-services-geonapi-r-interface-to-geonetwork-api-and-geoflow-r-engine-for-geospatial-metadata-workflows.-whats-the-best-way-to-get-started" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="geometa-is-used-in-r-packages-such-as-ows4r-r-interface-to-ogc-web-services-geonapi-r-interface-to-geonetwork-api-and-geoflow-r-engine-for-geospatial-metadata-workflows.-whats-the-best-way-to-get-started">geometa is used in R packages such as ows4R (R Interface to OGC Web Services), geonapi (R Interface to GeoNetwork API), and geoflow (R engine for geospatial metadata workflows). What’s the best way to get started?</h2>
<p>All these packages are open-source and available on GitHub. The best way to start is by checking the documentation and vignettes—<strong>ows4R</strong>, for example, has detailed vignettes.</p>
<p>On GitHub, I’ve also enabled the <strong>Discussions</strong> panel, which acts as a forum where users can ask questions. I make an effort to answer questions in my spare time, and the discussions often help improve documentation and package functionality.</p>
<p>Some key differences between the packages:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=ows4R">ows4R</a></strong> standards for OGC Web-Services for R and includes tools to interact with these services including metadata services (Catalogue Service for the Web - CSW) but also data services (with the well-known Web Feature Service - WFS and Web Coverage Service - WCS). With this package, metadata produced with geometa can be published within standard metadata catalogues, and metadata fetched from there. Users interested in using standard protocols instead of software-specific APIs may prefer this package.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/package=geonapi">Geonapi</a></strong> is API-specific. It provides tools to manage metadata but with the <a href="https://geonetwork-opensource.org/">Geonetwork</a> API.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://github.com/r-geoflow/geoflow">Geoflow</a></strong> serves as an orchestrator, integrating metadata, data, and tasks to publish them into web catalogs, including non-geographic ones.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="for-beginners-geoflow-might-be-the-best-entry-point." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-beginners-geoflow-might-be-the-best-entry-point.">For beginners, <strong>geoflow</strong> might be the best entry point.</h2>
</section>
<section id="how-has-it-been-working-with-the-r-consortium-would-you-recommend-applying-for-an-isc-grant-to-other-r-developers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-has-it-been-working-with-the-r-consortium-would-you-recommend-applying-for-an-isc-grant-to-other-r-developers">How has it been working with the R Consortium? Would you recommend applying for an ISC grant to other R developers?</h2>
<p>My experience with the R Consortium has been positive. My <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/2018-group-2.html#strengthening-of-r-in-support-of-spatial-data-infrastructures-management-geometa-and-ows4r-r-packages">first project</a> on geometa was funded in 2018, and it was a significant boost for the package.</p>
<p>Since then, I had submitted another project twice, for enhancing the ows4R package, though it was not selected because maybe considered too specific. The R Consortium deals with a broad range of domains covered by the R community, so they have to prioritize. However, the interaction with them has always been great—both administratively and with the <strong>Infrastructure Steering Committee (ISC)</strong>.</p>
<p>Before submitting my first application, I reached out to the ISC for advice on proposal structuring, approval processes, and whether partial funding was an option. Their feedback was helpful, and I’d definitely recommend other developers consider applying. It’s a great opportunity for funding and support.</p>
<p>Get started with geometa now! <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/geometa/index.html">CRAN – geometa</a></p>
</section>
<section id="what-projects-does-the-r-foundation-fund" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-projects-does-the-r-foundation-fund">What Projects Does the R Foundation Fund?</h2>
<p>Our grants target projects that make a difference in the R community, focusing on:</p>
<p>Technical Infrastructure: Enhancements in key R packages, development tools like R-hub, and improvements for R on various operating systems.</p>
<p>Social Infrastructure: Projects like SatRDays that promote local engagement and initiatives for better tracking of R Consortium activities.</p>
<p>We’re eager to see your innovative ideas and how they can propel the R ecosystem forward. This is a call to action for all who wish to contribute to the growth and enhancement of R. Let’s build a stronger R community together!</p>
<p>Submit your proposal now and be a part of shaping the future of the R Ecosystem. Learn more about how to apply <a href="https://www.r-consortium.org/all-projects/call-for-proposals">here</a>.</p>
<p>We look forward to your submissions and furthering the R community’s advancement together!</p>
<section id="apply-now" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="apply-now"><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">Apply now!</a></h3>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/exploring-geometa-an-r-package-for-managing-geographic-metadata/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/exploring-geometa-an-r-package-for-managing-geographic-metadata/emmanuel-main.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="70" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Looking forward to seeing you at useR! 2025 this year!</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/looking-forward-to-seeing-you-at-useR2025-this-year/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/looking-forward-to-seeing-you-at-useR2025-this-year/user2025_conf_logo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="registration-is-now-open" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="registration-is-now-open"><a href="https://user2025.r-project.org/register">Registration is now open!</a></h3>
<p>The useR! conference is the main international conference for users of the R programming language. This year, useR! 2025 will be held at Duke University in Durham, North Carolina, on August 8-10, 2025.</p>
<p>The useR! conference has been held annually since 2004, bringing together R users, developers, and enthusiasts from around the world. The conference includes keynotes, tutorials, and presentations on various applications of R in fields such as finance, pharmaceuticals, epidemiology, data science, and more.</p>
<p>Initially, useR! was organized in Europe, with the first event taking place in Vienna, Austria. Over the years, it has expanded to different continents, including North America, Australia, and Asia.</p>
<p>It continues to be a key event for R users to network, share knowledge, and discuss the latest developments in the R ecosystem.</p>
<p>The event is hosted by the R Foundation and sponsored by the R Consortium, posit, Center for Computational Thinking, and Duke University.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-sponsor" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-sponsor">Why Sponsor</h2>
<p><a href="https://user2025.r-project.org/sponsors/">Sponsoring useR! 2025</a> is valuable for organizations looking to engage with the R community and promote their brand in data science, finance, healthcare, and other R-heavy industries. Here are some key reasons to sponsor:</p>
<section id="networking-collaboration-opportunities" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="networking-collaboration-opportunities">1. Networking &amp; Collaboration Opportunities</h3>
<ul>
<li>Partner with key R developers and companies for future collaborations.</li>
<li>Gain insights into cutting-edge R applications across industries.</li>
<li><h3 id="recruit-top-talent" class="anchored">2. Recruit Top Talent</h3></li>
<li>Attract skilled R programmers, data analysts, and engineers.</li>
<li>Engage with students and researchers who are early in their careers.</li>
<li><h3 id="support-the-open-source-ecosystem" class="anchored">3. Support the Open Source Ecosystem</h3></li>
<li>Strengthen the R community and contribute to its growth.</li>
<li>Align your brand with an open-source, innovation-driven culture.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/looking-forward-to-seeing-you-at-useR2025-this-year/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/looking-forward-to-seeing-you-at-useR2025-this-year/user2025_conf_logo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="72" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A new year and the same, unwavering commitment</title>
  <dc:creator>Terry Christiani</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-year-same-unwavering-committment/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As we open our first round for <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/callforproposals.html">Infrastructure Steering Committee call for proposals</a> and <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">R User Groups’ submissions</a>, we want to take a moment to reiterate our mission as the R Consortium.</p>
<p>The R Consortium promotes the growth and development of the R language and its ecosystem by supporting technical and social infrastructure, fostering community engagement, and driving industry adoption.</p>
<p>We work to ensure a thriving, diverse global R community by providing resources, facilitating collaboration, and advocating for the use of R in multiple industry sectors. We provide funding for technical infrastructure through grants and working groups. We provide funding for social infrastructure through grants for R user groups and events around the world.</p>
<p>We provide a neutral space where industry, academia, and government can collaborate on mission critical processes and standards.</p>
<p>Our efforts in support of the R language and the community that keeps it growing and relevant are a privilege and we are committed to ensuring that our actions are in compliance with our code of conduct.</p>
<p>We hope that you and your organization will join us in support of the R language and our community. We have a lot of work to do and we are excited to see the new and familiar faces come together for another fantastic year.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-year-same-unwavering-committment/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-year-same-unwavering-committment/commitment.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Promoting R in Nigeria: How Unilorin R User Group is Making an Impact</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mohammed-kabir-garba-46795823/?originalSubdomain=ng">Dr.&nbsp;M.K. Garba</a> and <a href="https://gbganalyst.github.io/">Ezekiel Ogundepo</a>, organizers of the University of Ilorin, shortened to <a href="https://www.meetup.com/unilorin-r-user-group/">Unilorin R User Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about their efforts to promote R programming in Nigeria and foster a thriving local R community. They discussed the group’s origins, their experiences teaching R across academia and industry, and the impact of their inaugural event. Dr.&nbsp;Garba and Ezekiel also shared their plans for future workshops and highlighted their outreach strategies to engage learners and expand R’s reach in Nigeria. Ilorin is the capital city of Kwara State and is located in the western region of Nigeria.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/MKGarba.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;M. K. Garba</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/EzekielOgundepo.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<p>Ezekiel Ogundepo</p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: I am Dr.&nbsp;M.K. Garba, a lecturer in the Department of Statistics at the <a href="https://www.unilorin.edu.ng/">University of Ilorin</a>. I organize the University of Ilorin R User Group, and my co-organizer and fellow instructor is Ezekiel.</p>
<p>I was introduced to R programming by a senior colleague in my department around 2011 or 2012, and I have been using R personally since then. During my PhD, I utilized R programming continuously from start to finish. In 2015 or 2016, I taught R programming as a course to a group of senior-level students just a year before graduation. I continued teaching it for several years before the course was handed over to another instructor.</p>
<p>Although I am no longer assigned as the lecturer for this course, I am motivated to share my knowledge and experiences with students. This desire led to the establishment of the R User Group. The group is not just for students in the Statistics department; it welcomes participants from other departments as long as they are interested in learning R programming.</p>
<p>Ezekiel: I am a statistician consultant with Data Science Nigeria. Additionally, I help Dr.&nbsp;Garba in teaching R programming. Dr.&nbsp;Garba was my lecturer at the University of Ilorin, where he served as my co-supervisor during my training. He introduced me to R programming in 2014, and we focused on statistical computing using this language. Since then, I have been using R programming across various industries.</p>
<p>In 2018, I became a <a href="https://education.rstudio.com/trainers/people/ogundepo+ezekiel_adebayo/">Tidyverse instructor</a> for R Studio and developed several R packages, including <a href="https://gbganalyst.github.io/bulkreadr/">bulkreadr</a> and <a href="https://gbganalyst.github.io/forstringr/">forstringr</a> packages. I am also a member of <a href="https://ropensci.org/champions/">R Champion</a>, an organization dedicated to promoting R programming in Nigeria and abroad.</p>
<p><strong>What is the local R community like in Nigeria? Is R being used in Academia and Industry?</strong></p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/UnilorinRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: I’ll focus on academia and leave the industry to Ezekiel. While I am a tenured staff member at the University of Ilorin, I also serve as a visiting professor at several universities in my state. In any course I teach, I introduce my students to R programming. I am pleased to share that one or two of these institutions have adopted R as the programming language for their statistical computing courses.</p>
<p>Every university typically offers at least one statistical computing course, and many institutions have embraced R. Some may not use R exclusively; instead, they combine it with other software like <a href="https://www.stata.com/">Stata</a>, <a href="https://vsni.co.uk/software/genstat/">GenSTAT</a>, or <a href="https://www.sas.com/en_us/home.html">SAS</a>. However, due to my introduction of R, it has gained traction in their programs. While some students hesitated to abandon their previous software, they embraced using R easily.</p>
<p>Ezekiel: We actively promote R programming across various industries in Nigeria. For example, we implement R programming solutions at <a href="https://datasciencenigeria.org/">Data Science Nigeria</a>, where I work as a consultant. Two months ago, we organized a boot camp that invited numerous instructors and trainers to teach attendees about programming languages such as Python, R, data science, machine learning, and AI. I had the opportunity to teach R to those participants. Additionally, we collaborate with several biotechnology companies in Nigeria, both in industry and academia.</p>
<p><strong>Please tell us about the first event from your R User Group. What topics were covered, and what kind of response did you receive for the event?</strong></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: The first meetup took place after a two-week delay primarily because our targeted audience, the students at the University of Ilorin, were on break. Once they returned, we allowed them to settle in a few weeks before organizing our meeting. It was held virtually, and we were pleased with both the attendance and the feedback we received.</p>
<p>I was thrilled with the responses, especially since the participants were selected from various departments, not just those related to statistics or mathematics. We began the session with the basics, and those with intermediate knowledge could also learn and engage with the material effectively.</p>
<p>Ezekiel served as the instructor for this first meetup. We have a calendar in place and assigned roles for upcoming sessions. I invited him to share insights about what we taught during the meeting, which mainly focused on introductory concepts.</p>
<p>Ezekiel: We introduced the participants to an introductory level of programming, teaching them how to install the software and use the essential components of the R programming language. We covered various concepts, including data types and structures, to prepare them for more advanced topics in future meetings. While there were some issues due to the large number of attendees, everyone enjoyed the event.</p>
<p><strong>What are your plans for the group in the coming year? How many events are you hoping to host, and what topics do you plan to cover?</strong></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: Based on our schedule, I want to cover numerous topics, and I plan to invite many instructors, both national and international. We will discuss reproducibility in research, specifically using RStudio Project and version control for this purpose. Additionally, we want to focus on data visualization using the <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot2</a> package.</p>
<p>We have a range of interesting topics on data analysis, various tidyverse libraries, and different aspects of geostatistics. These subjects will be valuable for participants from both academia and industry. R programming applications extend to areas of statistics, including econometrics, which are included in our calendar. Additionally, we will have a session on building a personal portfolio using Quarto.</p>
<p><strong>Do you plan to host your events in person or online?</strong></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: We will have in-person sessions. As I mentioned, our primary focus is the students who were just getting settled then. That is why we initially opted for online sessions. However, there is no way we won’t conduct in-person classes, especially when it comes to practical demonstrations of what we are teaching. The students need to showcase their learning in person.</p>
<p><strong>What tools and techniques do you plan to use to promote your events?</strong></p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Garba: We use the Meetup platform where students can register to participate in discussions about our training sessions. When participants have questions, they can raise them, and we respond accordingly. We also encourage other participants to answer questions if they have the expertise; if no one else can answer, we step in. This platform is where we share information about our meetup schedules.</p>
<p>Additionally, we have individual Twitter handles and LinkedIn profiles that we use to disseminate information. On the day of our training sessions, we stream the events live on Facebook. Although we also have a YouTube account, we encountered an issue and could not stream on that platform that day. However, the event was successfully streamed live on Facebook.</p>
<p>We promoted the initiative using hashtags like #rstats #DataScience #LearnR, which we knew would help retrieve any other relevant information related to R. We contacted the entire R ecosystem, including groups like<a href="https://ropensci.org/">R OpenSci</a>and other organizations. In Nigeria, we have numerous R user groups and we shared our message with them. They were also instrumental in helping us promote it. Overall, this strategy worked perfectly.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute.</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/promoting-r-in-nigeria-how-unilorin-r-user-group-is-making-an-impact/UnilorinRUGlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R Submissions Working Group: Pilot 5 Launch and more!</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/pilot5.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="pilot-5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pilot-5">Pilot 5</h3>
<p>Last year the <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">submission working group</a> was able to successfully deliver its third R-based submission to the FDA through the <a href="https://www.fda.gov/drugs/electronic-regulatory-submission-and-review/electronic-common-technical-document-ectd">eCTD portal</a> on September 20, 2024. We are excited to share news the Pilot 5 launch as we continue to demonstrate R’s capablities to deliver a high-quality drug submission.</p>
<p>A quick recap of previous Pilots:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/blog/2021/12/08/successful-r-based-test-package-submitted-to-fda">Pilot 1</a> delivered Tables and Figures to the FDA using R.</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/blog/2022/12/07/update-successful-r-based-package-submission-with-shiny-component-to-fda">Pilot 2</a> delivered the same Tables and Figures using a Shiny App using R. <a href="https://archive.r-consortium.org/announcement/2023/10/05/shiny-app-successfully-reviewed-by-fda-cder-staff-pilot-2-announcement-2">Pilot 2 Announcement 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/news-from-r-submissions-working-group-pilot-3/">Pilot 3</a> delivered the Tables and Figures using R as well as the ADaMs…you guessed it using R.</li>
<li><a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/using-r-to-submit-research-to-the-fda-pilot-4-successfully-submitted/">Pilot 4</a> is in the process of delivering the Shiny App from Pilot 2 using webassembly and containers (almost completed!).</li>
</ul>
<p>For information on these Pilots navigate to our <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/pilot_background.html">Pilot’s background page on submission working group</a></p>
<p>Now in 2025, we are launching Pilot 5!! We will be using R again, but instead of delivering all the datasets as <code>xpt</code> files we will make use of the new <code>datasetjson</code> format via the eponymously named R package <a href="https://atorus-research.github.io/datasetjson/">datasetjson</a> and hope to deliver two submissions for 2025 split into Part 1 and Part 2.</p>
<p><strong>Pilot 5 - Part 1</strong></p>
<p>Part 1 is going to replicate <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium/submissions-pilot3-adam">Pilot 3</a>. We will reuse the ADaMs, Tables and Figure programs that were written in R. However, the Pilot 3 ADaMs were written out as <code>xpt</code> files and we will instead use <code>datasetjson</code>! Hence Pilot 5 is really focused on using the new transport file type <code>datasetjson</code>.</p>
<p>Pilot 5 Part 1 will also submit all the other files you find in the Pilot 3 submission as part of our package. If you have a passion for submission work, R and <code>datasetjson</code> or just want to see what all the fuss is about then come and <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/rconsortium/shared_invite/zt-2w4t2jd38-Z7BYYse9tIlCZEmqHvHnbA">join us</a>!</p>
<p><strong>Pilot 5 - Part 2</strong></p>
<p>The Pilots are small! 5 ADaMs, 3 Tables and 1 Figure is not a typical submission package for a drug that can impact a patient’s health and well-being! The Pilots have always been about testing out and advocating that R can keep up with the best of the best. For Part 2, we want to build up this body of work and develop several more ADaMs and more Tables and Figures. As in Part 1, we will deliver everything using <code>datasetjson</code> that would of been delivered as an <code>xpt</code> file.</p>
<p>We plan on kicking Part 2 off mid-summer, but planning will probably start soon! Come <a href="https://join.slack.com/t/rconsortium/shared_invite/zt-2w4t2jd38-Z7BYYse9tIlCZEmqHvHnbA">join</a> in on the fun and help us build a larger body of work around drug submissions using R.</p>
</section>
<section id="progress-reports-and-future-plans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="progress-reports-and-future-plans">Progress Reports and Future Plans</h2>
<p><strong>Updates on Pilot 4</strong></p>
<p>The objective of the R Consortium R submission <em>Pilot 4 </em>Project is to explore the use of novel technologies such as Linux containers and WebAssembly to bundle a Shiny application into a self-contained package, facilitating a smoother process of both transferring and executing the application. The application was built using the source data sets and analyses contained in the R submission <em>Pilot 1-3</em>. To our knowledge, this is the first publicly available submission package that includes a WebAssembly component. We hope this submission package and what we have learned can serve as a good reference for future regulatory submission efforts. The WebAssembly technology compiles applications into a portable, consistent environment driven by a web browser, allowing agency reviewers to easily run and evaluate software without complex setups. The second half of the Pilot 4 Project (leveraging container technology to package a Shiny application) will be submitted as an additional package later this year. Additional agency feedback will be shared in future communications.</p>
<p>The R Consortium is excited to announce that, on September 20, 2024, the R Submissions Working Group successfully submitted its test submission package—featuring a WebAssembly component—through the FDA’s Electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD) gateway! This marks a significant milestone as the FDA Center for Drug Evaluation and Research (CDER) staff has officially received the submission package.</p>
<p>Statistician Eric Nantz at pharmaceuticals company Eli Lilly in Indianapolis, Indiana, says that using WebAssembly “will minimize, from the reviewer’s perspective, many of the steps that they had to take to get the application running on their machines.”</p>
<p><strong>Potential Pilot 6</strong></p>
<p>The Pilots have been making use of the original CDISC Pilot data from around 2008-2010 that were used as PoC for the FDA for CDISC standards. This data has been reused for many other projects across the industry as there is a severe lack of publicly available CDISC data. You can read about my quest to find some more data <a href="https://pharmaverse.github.io/blog/posts/2025-02-17_data__packages/data__packages.html">here</a>. The submissions working group would like to create new simulated data from raw, SDTM and ADaMs that could be used to test new techniques, ways of working, etc all brought up to modern standards. If interested get in touch!</p>
<p><strong>A Re-Envisioned ADRG</strong></p>
<p>The Analysis Data Reviewer’s Guide (ADRG) has been focused on the proprietary language SAS for delivering submissions over many years. As open-source languages such as R are accepted as valid mechanisms to deliver a submission the ADRG needs to “re-envisioned” to accommodate these languages. The pilots have had questions on how to document certain technical aspects in the ADRG of the R-based submission package, e.g.&nbsp;packages used and versions, R versions and layouts of the file folders.</p>
<p>Well we are in luck. Former Pilot members are working with the PHUSE Version Metadata for Open-Source Languages to support ADRG enhancements for open-source submissions and are sharing their recommendations to the Pilots. You can find out more at the below links:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://advance.hub.phuse.global/wiki/x/UzOZAQ">Communication of Version Metadata for Open-Source Languages</a></li>
<li><a href="https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/">Welcome to the PHUSE Open-Source Metadata Documentation Working Group Site</a></li>
<li><a href="https://phuse-org.github.io/OSDocuMeta/references/problem_statement.html">Problem Statement</a></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>More about the R Submissions Working Group</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg/">R Consortium R Submissions Working Group</a> is focused on improving practices for R-based clinical trial regulatory submissions.</p>
<p>Health authority agencies from different countries require electronic submission of data, computer programs, and relevant documentation to bring an experimental clinical product to market. In the past, submissions have mainly been based on the SAS language.</p>
<p>In recent years, the use of open source languages, especially the R language, has become very popular in the pharmaceutical industry and research institutions. Although the health authorities accept submissions based on open source programming languages, sponsors may be hesitant to conduct submissions using open source languages due to a lack of working examples.</p>
<p>Therefore, the R Submissions Working Group aims to provide R-based submission examples and identify potential gaps while submitting these example packages. All materials, including submission examples and communications, are publicly available on the <a href="https://github.com/RConsortium">R consortium GitHub page.</a></p>
<p><strong>Join the R Submissions Working Group</strong></p>
<p>The R Submissions Working Group comprises members from over 10 pharmaceutical companies, as well as regulatory agencies. We are a collaborative community open to anyone interested in contributing to this important work. For more information, or to get involved, visit <a href="https://rconsortium.github.io/submissions-wg">our website</a> or contact us directly at director@r-consortium.org.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/submissions-wg-pilot5-pilot6-and-more/pilot5.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Seville R Users Group: R’s Role in Optimization Research and Stroke Prevention</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alberto-torrej%C3%B3n-valenzuela/?locale=en_US">Alberto Torrejon Valenzuela</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/sevilla-r-users/">Seville R Users Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the dynamic growth of the R community in Seville and the group’s role in fostering collaboration across academia and industry. Alberto shared highlights from hosting the Third Spanish R Conference, which brought together local and international participants. He discussed the group’s initiatives, including monthly workshops and online outreach through platforms like YouTube. He also reflected on his research in optimization and a collaborative project analyzing stroke prevention, showcasing how R drives innovation in scientific research and community development.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/AlbertoValenzuela.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</strong></p>
<p>My name is Alberto Torrejon Valenzuela. I am from Los Barrios, a town in Cádiz, southern Spain. I have moved to Seville, which is a bit further north, where I studied for a double degree in Mathematics and Statistics. During my studies, one of my professors introduced me to R. Although I was learning several programming languages, I realized that I could accomplish everything I needed with just R. Since then, I have continued to use it throughout my studies.</p>
<p>I also joined the R group in Sevilla, which I discovered through Meetup. It was another motivation to enhance my R skills. The Sevilla R Users Group meets at the University of Sevilla’s facilities every one to two months. During these meetings, we discuss our work and share our experiences. Our group includes many users from academia and industry, making our discussions very diverse. We enjoy discussing our various implementation packages and applications; hearing from both perspectives is always interesting.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGOrganizers.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Your Group recently hosted the <a href="https://www.imus.us.es/congresos/IIIRqueR/">Third Spanish R Conference</a>. Please share some details about the event.</strong></p>
<p>The Third Spanish R Conference took place from November 6 to 8 in Seville, co-organized by the <a href="https://www.imus.us.es/www/">Institute of Mathematics at the University of Seville</a> and Sevilla R group, with support from the R Consortium and several other organizations.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference1.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>We used a catchy slogan for the conference: “R tiene un color especial” (R has a special color). This is a modification of the lyrics of a famous song about Seville that everyone in Spain knows. It became a hit!</p>
<p>The conference featured a wide range of activities from both scientific and social perspectives. We had four plenary speakers: <a href="https://jakubnowosad.com/">Jakub Nowosad</a>, from University of Münster, and <a href="https://www.frick.ws/">Hannah Frick</a> from POSIT, along with national speakers <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rosanaferrero/?originalSubdomain=es">Rosana Ferrero</a>, who is very active in social networking, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/javier-tejedor-aguilera/?originalSubdomain=es">Javier Tejedor Aguilera</a> from <a href="https://www.endesa.com/en">Endesa</a>, who represents the industry.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference2.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>Additionally, it’s important to mention that the group recognized the contributions of two founding members, <a href="https://frodriguezsanchez.net/">Francisco Rodriguez-Sanchez</a> and <a href="https://jeronimocarranza.github.io/">Jerónimo Carranza</a>, during the conference. We honored them with a gift to acknowledge their hard work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SpanishRConference3.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p><strong>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</strong></p>
<p>Organizing a conference, like the one in Spain, is quite a significant undertaking. In addition to the conference, the group hosts monthly meetings called “TalleR”, the Spanish word for workshop. We typically emphasize the “R” at the end of the word. We exchange knowledge about our packages and various other topics during these meetings.</p>
<p>We primarily use social networks to connect with the local community, including the former <a href="https://x.com/_SevillaR">Twitter</a> (now known as X), <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/sevillar.bsky.social">BlueSky</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gruposevillar/">LinkedIn</a>. We rely on our Meetup page to organise the event, where we post details about our seminars or talleres. People can indicate whether they will attend in person or online, making this a helpful tool. Additionally, since some members are researchers and professors in the University of Seville, we have support from Microsoft Teams to stream and record these meetings, as many participants come from South American and Spanish-speaking countries. For example, in our last meeting, we had attendees from Panama and Colombia.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGMeeting.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<p>After the meeting, we usually post our recordings on our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC4_SN0le5WFMu_LFaIufLbA">YouTube</a> channel. Every session is recorded there. We also have a <a href="https://sevillarusers.netlify.app/">website</a> and a <a href="https://t.me/+HE3IBL13swTfZwYI">Telegram</a> group where we engage in more active discussions. This is mainly for our meetings.</p>
<p>However, as you mentioned, organizing a large conference like the Spanish R Conference requires additional support. We received this support from the Institute of Mathematics at the University of Seville, which provided significant assistance regarding the location and logistics of our conference. Since our successful collaboration with the Institute of Mathematics, our local group has been keen to maintain and expand this partnership to enhance our meetings held at the Institute.</p>
<p>Additionally, a significant portion of our support came from the Spanish Association known as <a href="https://r-es.org/">R-Hispano</a>. They provided valuable tools and assistance when co-organizing our events, which has been incredibly helpful. We’re also thankful for financial support from the R Consortium.</p>
<p><strong>How do you use R for your work?</strong></p>
<p>I use both R and Python for my <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Alberto-Torrejon-Valenzuela">research</a>. I have two distinct lives: a professional and a personal one. In my free time, I enjoy programming, and I also need to program in my professional life. My research focuses on optimization.</p>
<p>Optimization models aim to find the best solution to a given problem. I work in a lab run by <a href="https://scholar.google.es/citations?user=koF66usAAAAJ&amp;hl=es">Justo Puerto</a>, a full professor in the Department of Statistics and Operations. One of the primary areas I’m involved in is ordered optimization, which involves sorting procedures to identify the best solutions to various combinatorial and decision optimization problems.</p>
<p>We study numerous problems, ranging from logistics issues, such as resource or facility location problems, to statistical issues like linear regression or efficient statistics computation. The framework of ordered optimization allows us to generalize these problems to include abstract concepts such as equity or minimizing envy among clients. For instance, we can optimize the location of a supermarket, hospital, voting center, or bus and train lines, ensuring equitable access so that no one feels envious of their neighbors.</p>
<p>Additionally, we apply these algorithms to statistical problems to improve the computation or estimators. The optimization community is familiar with Python algorithms and packages, but the R community is catching up. I use several R packages, including <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ROI/index.html">ROI</a> and <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/ompr/index.html">OMPR</a>, allowing comprehensive data analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, primarily related to your industry?</strong></p>
<p>I am discussing a topic that highlights one of R’s best uses in boosting and supporting community initiatives. Since I work at the Institute of Mathematics, a research team from Hospital Universitario Virgen Macarena contacted us for statistical support. I was the first to volunteer, and we signed a collaboration contract to begin our work.</p>
<p>The project I’m currently involved in focuses on<a href="https://www.ibis-sevilla.es/es/investigacion/neurociencias/neurovascular/">studying and preventing strokes through analyzing large databases</a>. Stroke is one of the worst medical conditions from the point of view of rapid care for the affected person because when it occurs, there is usually a very short period of time until brain death is reached. Timely care is essential for improving outcomes.</p>
<p>This research is crucial for the team led by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joanmanelmontaner/?originalSubdomain=es">Joan Montaner</a>, which is focused on finding the best combination of drugs for stroke prevention. They aim to provide effective medications to individuals diagnosed with a stroke to improve their chances of survival, especially within the critical first 24 hours.</p>
<p>The team has access to a historical dataset of more than 100,000 patients, and I am analyzing this data using our software tools. We are uncovering some interesting insights, and we hope this information will assist them in testing these drug combinations. Ultimately, we aim to help develop more extensive protocols for administering these medications to patients.</p>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/seville-r-users-group-rs-role-in-optimization-research-and-stroke-prevention/SevilleRUGOrganizers.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Connecting Nebraska Through R: Jeffrey Stevens’ Journey of Community Building</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jeffreyrstevens/">Jeffrey Stevens</a>, organizer of the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/nebraskarusergroup/">Nebraska R User Group</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about his efforts to establish a vibrant R community across Nebraska. Jeffrey shared insights into the group’s activities, including fostering connections between academics, industry professionals, and nonprofits, and creating a hybrid model to engage participants from across the state. He also discussed his passion for package development, open science initiatives like the Many Dogs Project, and the challenges of building an inclusive R ecosystem in a geographically dispersed region.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/JeffreyStevens.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h2>
<p>I am a professor of psychology at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln, where I lead the <a href="https://dogcog.unl.edu/">Canine Cognition and Human Interaction Lab</a>. My research focuses on animals, comparative psychology, and animal cognition, a field I have been involved in since the mid-1990s.</p>
<p>I have been using R for over 15 years, but I initially worked with S-Plus during my graduate studies in the late 1990s. For the past 15 years, R has been my primary tool for data analysis.</p>
<p>In the last three years, I have also ventured into package development. To date, I have published three packages on <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/">CRAN</a>. One package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/excluder/index.html">excluder</a> is designed for data wrangling specifically tailored for survey data that psychologists often encounter. Another package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/flashr/index.html">flashr</a> creates flashcard slide decks to assist learners in mastering R; it includes R functions and descriptions, allowing students to familiarize themselves with terms and functionalities. My most recent package <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web//packages/cocoon/index.html">cocoon</a> takes statistical objects. It generates <a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/">R Markdown</a> or <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a> text that can be easily inserted into documents, making extracting and presenting the statistics you need simpler.</p>
<p>I teach R to diverse learners, including undergraduates, graduate students, postdocs, lab managers, and some faculty members. Additionally, I serve as a data science mentor for <a href="https://posit.co/">Posit</a>, guiding corporate individuals through data science training programs. In this role, I lead cohorts of employees seeking to enhance their R and data science skills. I have participated in several of these mentoring sessions, and my extensive experience with R has made it an essential part of my daily work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebraskaRUGlogo.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="what-was-your-motivation-behind-starting-this-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-was-your-motivation-behind-starting-this-r-user-group">What was your motivation behind starting this R User group?</h2>
<p>I know a few people at my university who use R, but there are just a handful here and there—not many. Most of them were using it for their projects. Then, about two years ago, I discovered that there was a faculty member in the Statistics Department named <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/srvanderplas/">Susan VanderPlas</a>. She had joined the department a bit earlier, but that was when I first learned about her. I found out that she shared my passion for R; she is also an R user and an educator enthusiastic about building websites and engaging with the community. She was the first person at my university with whom I connected over our shared interest in R.</p>
<p>I proposed starting an R user group, but she initially suggested we take a different approach. Last year, instead of forming a formal user group, we contacted everyone on campus who used R. The goal was to gather and have informal monthly chats about R-related topics. During our meetings, we discussed various subjects. The first gathering occurred right after <a href="https://posit.co/conference/">Posit::Conf</a>, where we shared our experiences from that conference.</p>
<p>As we continued meeting, I realised that my original vision was establishing a dedicated user group for R enthusiasts. Susan and I started a user group after talking with others on board with the idea. I took the initiative to move forward with it, and the R consortium grant was the primary motivation that pushed us to get serious about this project. Preparing the grant proposal was what got things started. Without that grant, I’m not sure we would have progressed as far as we have.</p>
<p>While I’m leading this initiative, Susan is also helping out. It’s important to me that we extend our reach beyond the university. While most of my connections are within the university, I want to engage with other universities, government, and industry groups. That’s why we aim to connect with the broader community in Nebraska.</p>
<p>I learned there was a group in Omaha, about an hour from my location in Lincoln, Nebraska, but it has become inactive. We invited anyone from Omaha, Lincoln, and surrounding areas to join us.</p>
<p>Nebraska is not a very populous state. Most of the population is concentrated in Lincoln and Omaha, leaving many smaller towns with fewer residents. However, we wanted to ensure that people from these smaller areas also had the opportunity to participate, so we decided to make our initiative statewide rather than city-specific.</p>
<p>Traditionally, many of our user groups have focused on urban areas. Still, given Nebraska’s vast land area, creating a welcoming environment for those outside the major cities was important. Several hundred miles separate some of the smaller towns, and we want to ensure everyone feels included.</p>
<p>Our goal is to make as many of our meetings hybrid as possible. This way, we can include individuals in western Nebraska and other towns beyond Lincoln and Omaha. We want them to feel connected and engaged. Our first kickoff meeting was in person, but after that, we have implemented the hybrid model so that participants from all around Nebraska can join our discussions as well. It’s important to us to involve those outside the main urban centres.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-nebraska" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-nebraska">Can you share what the R community is like in Nebraska?</h2>
<p>Although I have little experience with industry connections, I want to involve more industry professionals in our group. I have sent out an email summarising our discussions. I encouraged industry professionals to reach out, as one of our kickoff meeting discussions focused on the topics people want to hear about in future talks.</p>
<p>All attendees at the kickoff meeting were from academia or involved in nonprofit or government roles, such as parks and recreation or public media. However, no one from a corporate background was present. A graduate student expressed a strong interest in moving from academia to industry and asked how a graduate student with academic skills can transition into an industry job.</p>
<p>I highlighted this topic in my email, emphasizing the desire for industry partners to participate and share their insights. The academic participants are significantly interested in how to transition to industry positions, an area I feel more comfortable discussing.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGCollinBerke.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: <a href="https://www.collinberke.com/">Collin Berke</a></p>
</section>
<section id="please-provide-details-about-the-kick-off-meeting-for-your-group.-what-topics-were-discussed-and-how-did-participants-respond" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-provide-details-about-the-kick-off-meeting-for-your-group.-what-topics-were-discussed-and-how-did-participants-respond">Please provide details about the kick-off meeting for your group. What topics were discussed, and how did participants respond?</h2>
<p>The kickoff meeting was fantastic. As I mentioned last year, the original group consisted of about five or six people from the university. Typically, only four of us met each month, which was relatively small. However, we had 20 people in attendance for the kickoff meeting, which was great! It was mostly folks from Lincoln; unfortunately, no one from Omaha could make it since the meeting was in person.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGRachelRogers.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rachelesrogers/">Rachel Rogers</a></p>
<p>I was excited about the turnout, mainly because most attendees were academics I already knew. Still, I also met a few new people from the university. Additionally, we had representatives from <a href="https://nebraskapublicmedia.org/en/watch/live/?gad_source=1&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiAqL28BhCrARIsACYJvkc0RJUmqAJrWTGT1J6o9P0anRam3rJyxk4FKHEJHotsnaxDMe_AClUaApW9EALw_wcB">Nebraska Public Media</a> and <a href="https://members.grownebraska.org/list/member/nebraska-game-and-parks-164?utm_source=google&amp;gad_source=1&amp;gclid=Cj0KCQiAqL28BhCrARIsACYJvkdMY_i--W_KWOLTzLpze8Izpcet2qEWRrFwRpTk0UPC00QdMMI9Nd4aAkCIEALw_wcB">Nebraska Game and Parks</a>, which was exciting because it included some nonprofit and governmental groups.</p>
<p>We did not have a specific topic to discuss, as the main goal was to spend most of the time networking. I wanted everyone to talk, make connections, and meet new people.</p>
<p>My main goal for the kickoff meeting was facilitating communication among the attendees. We dedicated a significant portion of time to this at the beginning and end of the meeting to ensure everyone had ample opportunity to chat. I also made introductory announcements and introduced myself, outlining what we hoped to achieve with the group.</p>
<p>We included a couple of lightning talks in the agenda. These were short, five-minute presentations showcasing the various projects participants had been working on. The aim was to help everyone build connections and gain insight into their peers’ work.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebRUGParticipants.png" class="img-fluid"> Nebraska R User Group Kickoff Meeting: Participants</p>
<p>One graduate student discussed a package they developed based on their research, while a faculty member presented an R course they created along with its accompanying website. A representative from Nebraska Public Media shared how they utilize R in their daily operations. Lastly, I provided a brief overview of my flashcard package.</p>
<p>The goal was to provide a brief insight into what various people are doing from different perspectives. The event was very successful. The attendees enjoyed it; they were excited to learn about what others were doing and to get involved. Overall, I was pleased with how the kickoff meeting turned out.</p>
</section>
<section id="do-you-have-a-plan-for-this-year-what-is-the-frequency-of-the-events-you-plan-to-host-and-what-topics-will-you-cover" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="do-you-have-a-plan-for-this-year-what-is-the-frequency-of-the-events-you-plan-to-host-and-what-topics-will-you-cover">Do you have a plan for this year? What is the frequency of the events you plan to host, and what topics will you cover?</h2>
<p>I’m still working on that piece. I plan to hold these events roughly once a month during the academic year. So, starting in February, I envision having sessions in February, March, April, and May. Over the summer, we could get creative and consider doing something different instead of just talking. An in-person event could be a good option.</p>
<p>As mentioned, I want to involve some industry professionals. They would like to discuss the role of R in the industry and explore how people learning R can leverage their skills to seek job opportunities.</p>
<p>I recently attended our second meeting, which was our initial discussion. I asked the group if they wanted to share topics, ideas, or presentations. One suggestion was to have a “beginner’s night” for those with little exposure to the subject. This would help newcomers by introducing them to the basics.</p>
<p>User groups often contain members with varying experience levels, and it is essential to have a sense of how to cater to everyone. Our last meeting featured an advanced talk on extensions to <a href="https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/">ggplot2</a>, specifically building geoms, which is quite complex. We want to ensure that we also engage those new to R. It’s essential that they feel included, have the opportunity to ask questions, and learn something valuable by attending the group.</p>
<p>I don’t have a fully developed plan yet, but I have two initial ideas I’m still working on. I aim to be as inclusive as possible, engaging participants from various experience levels and backgrounds—from the industry, academia, government, or non-profits. I want to involve everyone and see what we can achieve together.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-primarily-related-to-your-industry" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-primarily-related-to-your-industry">Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting, primarily related to your industry?</h2>
<p>My work involves running the Canine Cognition and Human Interaction Lab with two main focuses. One focus is studying dog cognition. We invite pet dog owners to bring their dogs to our lab on campus, where we play games involving treats. We hide food in specific locations or provide choices, measuring the dogs’ decisions. These activities aim to understand how dogs think and process information.</p>
<p>One project I’m particularly excited about is called the <a href="https://manydogsproject.github.io/">Many Dogs Project</a>. This initiative is a consortium of dog labs from around the world. Several labs participate in a collaborative study, each conducting the same experiment in their respective locations. Ultimately, we aggregate all the data, allowing us to analyze a large sample size. For our first study, 20 labs tested 700 dogs, which provided us with a remarkable dataset for our behavioral research. I’m looking forward to the insights we can gain from these projects!</p>
<p>It’s a fantastic project because it brings together a diverse group. It’s collaborative and collegial, strongly emphasising open source and open science. We use R for our analyses; everything we do is made public, allowing everyone access to the data and scripts. I’m excited to be a part of this project. In fact, after my initial involvement, I ran to become the co-director of the Many Dogs Project, which I am now. I truly enjoy contributing to such initiatives.</p>
<p>I recently had the chance to work with Shiny for the first time. I developed my first <a href="https://manydogs.shinyapps.io/ManyDogs1/">Shiny app</a>, which allows users to explore some of the data collected from the Many Dogs Project. We gathered substantial information about the dogs, including their aggression, fearfulness, and training history. This app allows users to examine correlations, such as the relationship between a dog’s aggression and trainability.</p>
<p>I haven’t publicized the app yet because I want to get feedback from my colleagues in the Many Dogs Project before making it fully available. It’s been a fun experience. Initially, I hadn’t worked much with Shiny because it seemed different from R, and I was unsure if I could manage it. However, I attended a workshop on Shiny designed for data science mentors, and I decided to use it to build the Many Dogs Project app as my project for that workshop.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/connecting-nebraska-through-r-jeffrey-stevens-journey-of-community-building/NebraskaRUGlogo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="75" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New R User Group in Thailand is Building Awareness of R</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/logo_final-05.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:30.0%"></p>
<p><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/nwiroonsri/">Dr.&nbsp;Nathakhun Wiroonsri</a> is an academic at the Department of Mathematics, Faculty of Science, King Mongkut’s University of Technology Thonburi in Thailand. With a strong foundation in applied mathematics, Dr.&nbsp;Wiroonsri’s expertise lies in theoretical probability, machine learning, and statistical analysis. His research aims to bridge these areas to develop innovative methodologies for solving real-world problems, particularly in clustering and healthcare applications.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/nathakhun1.jpeg" class="img-fluid" style="width:40.0%"></p>
<p>Beyond his academic pursuits, Dr.&nbsp;Wiroonsri is deeply involved in promoting the use of R in Thailand. He founded <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rxthailand/">R x TH, Thailand’s R user group supported by the R Consortium</a>, to foster collaboration and build a vibrant community for R enthusiasts. His efforts include organizing workshops for beginners, experienced users, and professionals, aiming to make R more accessible and appealing across industries, especially among the younger generation.</p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-r-x-th." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-r-x-th.">Please share your background and involvement with R x TH.</h3>
<p>I’d like to share a bit about my personal background and my journey with R. I completed my PhD in applied mathematics at USC, focusing on theoretical probability. During that time, I didn’t use R extensively, but I was familiar with it and occasionally relied on it for simple simulations to validate my research results.</p>
<p>After graduating, I taught a statistical consulting course at USC, assisting my advisor, who used R in his teaching. That experience provided me with additional exposure to the language.</p>
<p>When I returned to Thailand, I was assigned to teach a statistics and data science program, which marked the beginning of my regular use of R. I also began conducting research in machine learning, where R became an integral tool in my work.</p>
<p>This year, I had the opportunity to attend the useR! conference in Salzburg, which was a fantastic experience.</p>
<p>Inspired by that event and recognizing a gap in Thailand, my students and I decided to establish R x TH, a user group for R enthusiasts in Thailand. At the time, there weren’t any Thai groups officially supported by the R Consortium, so we started this initiative to organize workshops for both beginners and experienced users. We also aim to foster research collaboration within the group.</p>
<p>To clarify, I’m based in Bangkok and work at the King Mongkut’s University of Technology under a government contract, which initially sent me to study in the U.S.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-bangkok-and-more-broadly-in-thailand" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-bangkok-and-more-broadly-in-thailand">Can you share what the R community is like in Bangkok and more broadly in Thailand?</h3>
<p>I’d say R isn’t very popular in Thailand, especially compared to Python, which dominates industry environments. However, there are some R users, particularly in sectors like insurance and also healthcare.</p>
<p>Before starting the R x TH user group, there were already a few R communities in Thailand, but they were mostly small and centered within universities. Many R users here work in academia, using it in traditional ways—primarily for teaching and data analysis in their fields.</p>
<p>A funny story: I recently met an old friend who graduated from UC San Diego and works in pure mathematics. He had never coded before and started learning Python to assist his new research. When I mentioned R, he thought it was some kind of instant software where you just input data, click a few times, and get results! I explained what R is, and he was intrigued, so I invited him to one of our workshops. Stories like this highlight how much awareness we still need to build around R.</p>
</section>
<section id="your-group-recently-held-its-very-first-event.-how-did-it-go-can-you-share-more-about-the-topics-covered" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-group-recently-held-its-very-first-event.-how-did-it-go-can-you-share-more-about-the-topics-covered">Your group recently held its very first event. How did it go? Can you share more about the topics covered?</h3>
<p>Our first event focused on providing a solid introduction to R. We covered foundational topics such as basic syntax, coding practices, and essential packages like ggplot2. The session was hands-on, starting with how to install R and the key packages, so participants could follow along easily.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/event-participants.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The event was a success, thanks in large part to my master’s students: Onthada and Noppanon, who played a key role in organizing and leading the workshop. It even sparked interest among younger students—several approached me afterward, eager to take my data science course next semester, even though it’s typically designed for junior students.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/speaker.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>As for the course itself, I initiated it about four years ago as a special topic, and after receiving positive feedback, it became a core part of the program. For the workshop, we prepared tutorial materials that participants could follow step by step. Right now, those materials are only shared within the group, but we may consider making them public in the future.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/speaker2.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in">Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</h3>
<p>I’m currently wrapping up my grant, during which I published several papers related to cluster validity indices. My research focuses on cluster validation techniques, which are used to detect optimal clusters hidden in datasets. My team and I have also contributed to the R community by developing two R packages, <em><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/UniversalCVI/index.html">UniversalCVI</a></em> and <em><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/BayesCVI/index.html">BayesCVI</a></em>, both available on CRAN. These packages are specifically designed for those working with cluster analysis.</p>
<p>In addition, I’m collaborating with a medical doctor to develop a new methodology for classifying diabetes patients. Once this project is complete, we plan to create an R package based on our methodology. We also aim to organize a workshop for healthcare professionals who use R in their work.</p>
<p>Interestingly, R is still widely used in the healthcare sector in Thailand, particularly by doctors and researchers. However, I’ve noticed a shift among younger generations toward Python, but R remains prevalent in this field.</p>
<p>Any techniques you recommend using for planning for or during the event? (Github, Zoom, other) Can these techniques be used to make your group more inclusive to people that are unable to attend physical events in the future?</p>
<p>We had a great turnout at the event, but the level of interest varied among participants. Some attendees were genuinely enthusiastic, while others seemed to come along with friends or just to check things out. That was a bit of a challenge because we wanted everyone to feel engaged.</p>
<p>To address this, we reviewed the participant list and adjusted our approach. For those who seemed less familiar with the material, we made the content more beginner-friendly and interactive to capture their interest. We also added activities to make the event more fun and engaging, especially since many attendees were young and appreciated a lively atmosphere.</p>
<p>For example, we incorporated Q&amp;A sessions where participants could answer questions, and we gave out small prizes to encourage participation. This approach resulted in better engagement and made the event more enjoyable for everyone.</p>
</section>
<section id="which-isc-projects-have-you-used-if-none-which-ones-look-like-something-you-might-look-into-and-why" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-isc-projects-have-you-used-if-none-which-ones-look-like-something-you-might-look-into-and-why">Which <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/funded-projects.html">ISC project</a>(s) have you used? If none, which one(s) look like something you might look into (and why)?</h3>
<p>To be honest, I only recently realized that the R Consortium funds ISE projects after you sent me the question. I looked into them briefly, and they all seem quite interesting. One that caught my attention is <a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/2023-group-1.html#autotest-automated-testing-of-r-packages">autotest</a>.</p>
<p>As someone with experience publishing R packages, I know how challenging it is to catch every error. Despite double- and triple-checking for issues, once a package is released and used by real users, unexpected errors often surface. A tool like <em>autotest</em>, which helps identify potential issues before publishing, would be incredibly helpful. Being able to ensure the package is as close to error-free as possible before release would make a big difference. I’m definitely planning to use <em>autotest</em> in the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-trends-do-you-see-around-the-r-language" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-trends-do-you-see-around-the-r-language">What trends do you see around the R language?</h3>
<p>In Thailand, there’s a clear trend among the younger generation toward learning Python. Even students in our statistics and data science program express interest in Python. However, we still focus on using R in our curriculum. The challenge is that many R users in Thailand, particularly in academia, tend to use it in traditional ways—relying on existing packages for data analysis. This makes it harder to attract younger users to R.</p>
<p>When I attended the useR! conference this past year, I discovered many modern techniques and packages in R that could appeal to younger users, such as tools for creating content, slides, and publications—like Quarto. I tried Quarto myself recently and found it very promising. I believe introducing these modern tools through workshops could resonate with younger users and professionals in industry, showing them that R can be just as innovative and versatile as other tools.</p>
<p>Our user group is based at a university, so it naturally draws students. However, we’re also planning workshops tailored to professionals, starting with healthcare. Since we’re currently working on a project related to diabetes classification, we plan to hold a workshop for healthcare professionals once the project is complete. This will give us a chance to share our new methodology, demonstrate its applications in healthcare, and encourage attendees to explore R further. I think this approach will help us reach new audiences and grow interest in R.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/new-r-user-group-in-thailand-is-building-awareness-of-r/event-participants.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>R en Buenos Aires: New Generations Working to Strengthen the Community</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community" class="level1">
<h1>R en Buenos Aires: New Generations Working to Strengthen the Community</h1>
<p><br> <br></p>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/andrea-gomez-vargas.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:5%;">

</div><div class="column" style="width:65%;">
<p>The R Consortium recently interviewed Andrea Gomez Vargas to find out about the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/en-AU/renbaires/">R in Buenos Aires</a> User Group. Andrea has a degree in sociology. Currently, she works as an analyst of population statistics at the National Institute of Statistics and Census - INDEC Argentina. She also teaches at universities in social science and data science.</p>
<p>Andrea has been an active member of the R community in Argentina and Latin America since 2018. She has been part of <a href="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/">R-Ladies Buenos Aires</a> and is currently part of the R-Ladies global team and the LatinR organizing committee.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Andrea was part of the 2023-2024 cohort of the rOpenSci champions program, and in 2024 she decided to take over the leadership of R en Buenos Aires.</p>
<section id="why-did-you-decide-to-take-the-lead-of-the-chapter" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-did-you-decide-to-take-the-lead-of-the-chapter">Why did you decide to take the lead of the chapter?</h3>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<p><br> I decided to take on the leadership of the chapter to actively contribute to the local impact of the R user community. Most of my knowledge has come from these communities - the trust and selfless support I’ve received has helped me grow as a professional and inspired me to take on projects I never thought I could. For this reason, I believe it is essential to reengage in activities to invite new generations to participate, explore new tools and opportunities, and collaborate in a space that welcomes all levels of experience and diverse professional backgrounds.</p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-motivates-you-to-continue-promoting-r-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-motivates-you-to-continue-promoting-r-learning">What motivates you to continue promoting R learning?</h3>
<p>Communities are essential spaces for breaking down barriers to access information and knowledge, especially when it comes to free and open-source software. When these resources are paid or only reach a small percentage of people, it creates inequities. As a public university teacher, I am driven by the belief that everyone, regardless of background, should have the opportunity to learn and grow in a collaborative, open environment. That’s what keeps me motivated to continue spreading R knowledge and ensuring it remains accessible for all.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants from the December 20th, 2024, meetup</em></p>
</section>
<section id="what-are-your-main-objectives-for-the-r-chapter-in-buenos-aires-and-what-challenges-do-you-anticipate-in-achieving-them" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-your-main-objectives-for-the-r-chapter-in-buenos-aires-and-what-challenges-do-you-anticipate-in-achieving-them">What are your main objectives for the R chapter in Buenos Aires, and what challenges do you anticipate in achieving them?</h3>
<p>The main objectives at this moment for the R chapter in Buenos Aires are to have more events to disseminate relevant topics in the community, such as the use of Quarto, Shiny, R packages, Git, and GitHub. A key challenge is ensuring that volunteer work doesn’t overwhelm us or lead to burnout, as organizing these events requires a lot of behind-the-scenes work. Currently, in addition to myself, Emanuel and Ariana are part of the local team coordinating activities—and although teamwork is essential, we must find a balance between collective effort and the well-being of the chapter members.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-currently-working-on-or-have-worked-on-in-the-past-using-the-r-language.-goalreason-result-anything-interesting-especially-related-to-the-industry-you-work-in">Please share about a project you are currently working on or have worked on in the past using the R language. Goal/reason, result, anything interesting, especially related to the industry you work in?</h3>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:70%;">
<p><br> <br> I’m working on the development of the <code>arcenso</code> package, a package with census data from Argentina, now in its first version on Github, but we are looking to reach CRAN.</p>
<p><code>arcenso</code> is a project supported by the rOpenSci Champions Program cohort 2023-2024, with me as lead developer, Emanuel Ciardullo as co-developer and Luis D. Verde as mentor. It is a very important project because it makes census data accessible and homogenized in a way that any user can work with it in R.</p>
</div><div class="column" style="width:30%;">
<p><br> <br> <img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/arcenso.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Details from the arcenso page:</p>
<p>arcenso is a package under development that will allow access to the official data of the national population censuses in Argentina from the National Institute of Statistics and Census - INDEC. Currently, the results of the historical censuses of 1970, 1980, 1991, 2001, 2010 and 2022 are available in different formats through physical books, PDFs, Excel files or in REDATAM, without having a unified system or format that allows working with the data of these six census periods as a database. In addition, the presentation of the data is not homogeneous between the periods, making it difficult to make historical or serial comparisons of the available information.</p>
<p>This package aims to make census data available, homogenized and ready to use. It will include the census data from 1970 to 2022. Having a package of census information will allow the public and private sectors, citizens and other actors in society to access current and historical information on Argentina’s population, households and housing in a more accessible way.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For more information, see <a href="https://soyandrea.github.io/arcenso/">soyandrea.github.io/arcenso</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="what-r-resourcestechniques-dodid-you-use-posit-rstudio-github-tidyverse-etc." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-r-resourcestechniques-dodid-you-use-posit-rstudio-github-tidyverse-etc.">What R resources/techniques do/did you use? (Posit (RStudio), Github, Tidyverse, etc.)</h3>
<p>I use R on a daily basis to teach, work and collaborate in the community. Part of my work requires processing and combining various data sources (censuses, surveys and administrative records) to produce socio-demographic indicators for the country. I also design and develop digital statistical products, such as a Shiny app or dashboards. For all this I rely on several R packages for ETL and visualisation <em>(gt, tidyverse, expss, plotly, quarto, and many more).</em> And this is what I try to teach my students or the people who attend the workshops.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-5.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Photo of Betsy, Ariana, and Andrea, organizers of the October 29, 2024, meetup, from left to right</em></p>
</section>
<section id="you-had-a-meetup-on-october-29th-2024.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-had-a-meetup-on-october-29th-2024.-can-you-share-more-about-the-topic-covered">You had a Meetup on October 29th, 2024. Can you share more about the topic covered?</h3>
<p><em>[Editor’s note: There were two more events held by R en Buenos Aires at the end of 2024. Please see the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/en-AU/renbaires/events/?type=past">meetup page</a> for more information (in Spanish).]</em></p>
<p>The topic of the workshop was socio-demographic analysis in R using data from the Argentine Labour Force Survey. We learned about the R packages needed to calculate the indicators and how to present the results in graphs and tables.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-3.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>The workshop was aimed at university students who are taking their first steps in R and who would like to do real-life practice guided by people from the community with experience in the field.</p>
<p>After the workshop a specific website <a href="https://r-unlam.netlify.app/">r-unlam.netlify.app</a> was created. We believe it is a good practice for people who cannot attend physically to have access to all the materials and to have the activities documented.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-4.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <em>Participants from the October 29th, 2024, meetup</em></p>
</section>
<section id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="you-can-reach-out-to-r-in-buenos-aires-through-the-following">You can reach out to R in Buenos Aires through the following:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Linkedin: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires/" class="uri">https://www.linkedin.com/company/r-en-buenos-aires/</a></li>
<li>Github: <a href="https://github.com/renbaires" class="uri">https://github.com/renbaires</a></li>
<li>X: <a href="https://x.com/renbaires">https://x.com/renbaires</a><br>
</li>
<li>Instagram: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires">https://www.instagram.com/renbuenosaires</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h3>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html" class="uri">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.html</a></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/r-en-buenos-aires-new-generations-working-to-strengthen-the-community/renBA-4.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Transforming Academic Research with R in Santa Rosa, Argentina</title>
  <dc:creator>R Consortium</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marina-cock-49b1b5171/">Marina Cock</a>, co-organizer of <a href="https://www.meetup.com/rladies-santa-rosa/">R-Ladies Santa Rosa</a>, recently spoke with the R Consortium about the growth of the R community in La Pampa and the transformative role of R in local academic research. Marina shared insights into the community’s activities, including introducing students to R, organizing meetups, and encouraging advanced statistical techniques like generalized linear mixed models. She also highlighted the challenges of promoting R in her university setting and her efforts to foster a supportive environment for learning and collaboration.</p>
<section id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-your-background-and-involvement-with-the-rugs-group.">Please share your background and involvement with the RUGS group.</h3>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/MarinaCock.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Marina Cock at first R ladies meet up in Santa Rosa, La Pampa</em></p>
<p>I am a natural resources engineer from the National University of La Pampa. I completed my PhD in plant ecology at the University of Buenos Aires. Currently, I work as both a teaching assistant and a research assistant at the National University of La Pampa.</p>
<p>I first engaged with the R community about seven years ago, roughly one year after I began using R. During that time, I was learning R. I shared my experiences and questions with <a href="https://yabellini.netlify.app/">Yanina Bellini</a>, founder of R-ladies Santa Rosa and a significant R-ladies member. [<em>Editor’s note: Bellini is also <a href="https://r-consortium.org/about/governance.html">a member of the R Consortium Infrastructure Steering Committee</a>.</em>] She was also just starting and suggested that we join a global network to help each other, share our doubts, and expand our knowledge and ideas in La Pampa, specifically in our city, Santa Rosa. During that conversation, she invited me to organize the first meetup here.</p>
<p>We began our journey with R Ladies in Santa Rosa, La Pampa. Our first event occurred at a college, where we started engaging with students. We explained what R is, how we use it, and how they could apply it professionally. Yanina discussed data mining while I shared how I utilize R for generalized linear mixed models.</p>
<p>That meeting marked the beginning of our activities in Santa Rosa. Following this, Yanina invited me to join the committee for the <a href="https://latinr.org">Latin R Conference</a>. This key conference in Latin America showcased various uses and applications of R and was an opportunity to broaden my understanding of R.</p>
<p>Since then, I have shared knowledge and learned much about R from these communities. My journey with R started with a free online course, and after learning the basics, I began asking questions and learning from the global community.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/YaninaBellini.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><em>Yanina Bellini at the Latin R conference</em></p>
</section>
<section id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-la-pampa" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-you-share-what-the-r-community-is-like-in-la-pampa">Can you share what the R community is like in La Pampa?</h3>
<p>I can speak from my experience in academia, as this is where I primarily use R. I’ve noticed that R has become increasingly popular over the years. For instance, we didn’t use any software when I was studying for my degree. Now, I am a teaching assistant for statistics, and we teach R and its applications for research to our students.</p>
<p>While pursuing my PhD, only some people were using R, making me question my decision regarding data analysis. After I collected my data, I considered whether to analyze it using traditional software. At that time, it felt daunting because, in my location, there were few users of R. However, I decided to dedicate a summer to learning the R language. I applied what I learned to analyze my data, and it was a great experience. It opened up numerous possibilities for analysis and helped me develop valuable skills in data wrangling, such as organizing and cleaning the data.</p>
<p>Although I’m not an expert—just someone who has learned the basics—I found many helpful resources that have significantly enhanced my statistical skills.</p>
<p>That’s why I believe Yanina and I should spread the word about R. In my case, I tell the students that using R isn’t something to be afraid of. Many people think it’s impossible to learn, but that’s not true. Once you start using it, you’ll see that it’s manageable. There’s plenty of help available online and at the university, making it an excellent tool for our work. However, I still think we have much to do to alleviate the fear surrounding R. Many university students are still intimidated by it, and we should continue supporting each other in learning it.</p>
</section>
<section id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="please-share-about-a-project-you-are-working-on-or-have-worked-on-using-the-r-language.-what-is-the-goalreason-result-or-anything-interesting-related-to-your-industry">Please share about a project you are working on or have worked on using the R language. What is the goal/reason, result, or anything interesting related to your industry?</h3>
<p>R became essential for me after I completed my PhD, mainly for data wrangling. During the last year of my PhD, I received a scholarship to spend three months in the US. Because it was a short-term stay, I could not take my research samples. Instead, I proposed carrying out a data analysis project. At that point, I needed to improve my data analysis skills, and my experience with R was limited. While in the US, I worked on a research question related to plant ecology, focusing mainly on plant-plant interactions, particularly positive plant facilitation. We were investigating whether plants that grow in association with others show different traits or strategies than those that grow in isolation.</p>
<p>There is already a significant amount of knowledge regarding how facilitation and positive interactions vary in stressful environments. However, we aimed to understand more about the types of plants that depend on being close to other plants for survival and reproduction.</p>
<p>I was provided with two large databases for my analysis. One database contained information on plants in alpine systems, including the richness and biodiversity of plants living close to each other versus those more isolated. Another included a big worldwide database about plant traits. Initially, I struggled to interpret the databases and sought help downloading their data. Once I obtained it, I began the process of data wrangling and tidying it up using the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/">tidyverse</a> and reshaping packages in R.</p>
<p>During the final phase of my PhD, I dedicated time to learning the basics of R, which enabled me to organize the data effectively. Ultimately, our analysis revealed no significant differences in traits between isolated plants and those associated with others. Nonetheless, this project underscored the importance of using R in my research.</p>
<p>I’m unsure how to analyze large databases with other software. The main project I worked on involved R, and after that, I continued my postdoctoral studies, still investigating some of that data. I primarily use generalized linear mixed models.</p>
<p>We often deal with hierarchical experimental designs in ecology, particularly plant ecology. For example, plants within fields are then within regions. It’s essential to account for this lack of independence in our data. Generalized linear mixed models have proven extremely helpful for ecologists. Our techniques and packages now enable us to perform analyses that we previously couldn’t even consider.</p>
<p>These models are fundamental tools for plant ecologists. Other types of ecologists, like those studying animals, may also use them, but they are particularly crucial for our study designs.</p>
<p>I gathered my courage and started creating some maps. Initially, I hesitated to make graphs because achieving them would require many scripts and specifications. However, I soon realized that graphs and maps are handy. I couldn’t believe the maps I could create in R! Now, as a research assistant, I might be asked to make maps or handle a lot of data wrangling for various research projects that have accumulated over time.</p>
<p>I organize all the data needed to perform analyses, and I often tell people here that I strive to incorporate more R into our statistics courses. We encourage students to integrate more R into learning and embrace modern tools and techniques. Other universities might use R more extensively than we do, but we have been growing in our use of R over the past few years.</p>
<p>If you have any questions, ideas, or suggestions, my email is <a href="marinacock@gmail.com">marinacock@gmail.com</a>.</p>
<p>You can also contact <a href="mailto:yabellini@gmail.com">Yanina Bellini Saibene</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-do-i-build-an-r-user-group">How do I Build an R User Group?</h2>
<p>R Consortium’s R User Group and Small Conference Support Program (RUGS) provides grants to help R groups organize, share information, and support each other worldwide. We have given grants over the past four years, encompassing over 76,000 members in over 90 user groups in 39 countries. We would like to include you! Cash grants and meetup.com accounts are awarded based on the intended use of the funds and the amount of money available to distribute</p>
<p><a href="https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm">https://r-consortium.org/all-projects/rugsprogram.htm</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/transforming-academic-research-with-r-in-santa-rosa-argentina/MarinaCock.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="108" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Clinical Reporting Collaborative Triumph: Roche’s NEST and Admiral Teams</title>
  <dc:creator>Joe Zhu, Leena Khatri, Emily de la Rua, Edoardo Mancini, Kangjie Zhang, Daphne Grasselly</dc:creator>
  <link>https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Guest Post contributed by Joe Zhu, Leena Khatri, Emily de la Rua, Edoardo Mancini, Kangjie Zhang, Daphne Grasselly</em></p>
<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>In the dynamic world of clinical research, innovation and collaboration are key drivers of success. The NEST and admiral teams exemplify this through their groundbreaking partnership. By leveraging open-source tools and fostering a community-driven approach, they have significantly advanced data integration and reporting methodologies in the clinical research setting. This story celebrates their journey and achievements.</p>
<p><img src="https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/nest-admiral.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="the-nest-team" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-nest-team">The NEST Team</h2>
<p>The NEST team, an acronym for <a href="https://insightsengineering.github.io/nest/">Next-Generation Exploratory and Standardized Tools</a>, has pioneered a collection of open-sourced R packages designed to expedite insight generation under clinical research settings. Originating at Roche, NEST has attracted a diverse array of collaborators from academia, the pharmaceutical industry, and clinical research institutes, largely due to efforts like <a href="https://pharmaverse.org/">pharmaverse</a>. Their mission is to accelerate clinical reporting and welcome contributions from the broader scientific community.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-admiral-team" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-admiral-team">The Admiral Team</h2>
<p>Focused on a complementary goal, the admiral team is dedicated to providing an <a href="https://pharmaverse.github.io/admiral/">open-source, modularized toolbox for creating ADaM datasets in R</a>. Their approach is transparent and collaborative, empowering users to co-create and refine a harmonized methodology for ADaM development across the pharmaceutical industry. The admiral team designs their tools to be user-friendly and versatile, capable of addressing a wide range of data requirements.</p>
</section>
<section id="setting-the-stage-for-collaboration" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="setting-the-stage-for-collaboration">Setting the Stage for Collaboration</h2>
<p>Recognizing the potential for synergies, the NEST and Admiral teams embarked on a collaborative journey to enhance their respective toolsets.</p>
<p>Their shared objectives included:</p>
<ul>
<li>Developing a robust toolbox of reusable functions and utilities for ADaM dataset creation and Tables/Listings/Graphs creation.</li>
<li>Ensuring comprehensive documentation and testing of these functions.</li>
<li>Creating detailed vignettes to guide users in generating and manipulating various datasets, and for subsequent tabulation.</li>
<li>Encouraging contributions from the pharmaceutical community to foster a unified and robust development environment.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="overcoming-initial-challenges" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overcoming-initial-challenges">Overcoming Initial Challenges</h2>
<p>Initially, the NEST team relied on simulated data for integration testing, which often lacked realism and failed to cover corner cases or expose software limitations. The opportunity arose to address these challenges by switching to using the more realistic test data offered by the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/pharmaverseadam/index.html">{pharmaverseadam} package</a>, whose original source is real SDTM data published through the CDISC Test Data pilot. This pivot allowed the NEST team to achieve more realistic and comprehensive testing, thus enhancing the robustness of their development work, and the {pharmaverseadam}/{admiral} team to improve the quality of their templates and test data through the constructive feedback that was received during the implementation phase.</p>
</section>
<section id="key-milestones-achieved" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-milestones-achieved">Key Milestones Achieved:</h2>
<p><strong>Realistic Data Integration:</strong> Transitioning from simulated to more realistic data provided the NEST team with more accurate and relevant testing conditions. This change was crucial in identifying and rectifying potential software limitations.</p>
<p><strong>Scope and Dependency Management:</strong> Both teams agreed to avoid creating strong interdependencies that could extend release cycles. NEST packages maintained minimal data for documentation purposes, while admiral preserved extensive datasets separately.</p>
<p><strong>CI Integration and Automation:</strong> New CI integration tests ensured that template updates were automatically verified against stored pharmaverseadam datasets. This maintained consistency and allowed users to identify intended changes promptly.</p>
<p><strong>Strategic Pipelines:</strong> An automated pipeline was established to update pharmaverseadam ADaMs for each new release, reflecting any template changes Accurately.</p>
</section>
<section id="recent-developments" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recent-developments">Recent Developments</h2>
<p>The collaboration bore fruit as the teams uncovered critical insights and improvements:</p>
<p>Using pharmaverseadam data in the scda.test package helped the NEST team identify and correct issues in their table template development, specifically in calculating denominator values.</p>
<p>The realistic test data also revealed minor inconsistencies in the derivation of ECG data within the admiral framework, which were promptly addressed, enhancing data accuracy.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The collaboration between the NEST and admiral teams showcases the power of open-source initiatives and community-driven efforts such as the pharmaverse in advancing clinical research. By integrating realistic data and refining their testing processes, they have significantly enhanced the robustness and reliability of their tools. This partnership not only accelerates insight generation but also cultivates a culture of collaboration and innovation, benefiting the broader pharmaverse community.</p>
<p>The success of this collaboration highlights the profound impact of shared goals and collective innovation, paving the way for future advancements in clinical research methodologies and outcomes.</p>
<section id="acknowledgement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h3>
<p>We would like to thank Ben Straub, Jeff Dickinson, Stefan Bundfuss, Ross Farrugia, Zelos Zhu’s valuable contributions to this collaborative work.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://r-consortium.org/posts/clinical-reporting-roches-nest-and-admiral-teams/nest-admiral.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="79" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
